<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht000187.v1" study_id="phs000101.v4" participant_set="1" date_created="Mon Mar 17 14:51:07 2014"><variable id="phv00024159.v1"><name>Catalog_ID</name><description>Subject ID number assigned by NINDS Repository</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024160.v1"><name>In_Panel</name><description>Indicates whether DNA of this subject is included in any panels available through the NINDS Repository catalog</description><type/><value code="Y">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00024161.v1"><name>Age</name><description>Subject's age at sampling</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024162.v1"><name>Gender</name><description>Subject's gender</description><type/><value code="F">Female</value><value code="M">Male</value></variable><variable id="phv00024163.v1"><name>Race</name><description>Subject's race</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024164.v1"><name>Ethnicity</name><description>Ethnic category (as reported by subject) - check one:  Hispanic or Latino, Not Hispanic or Latino</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024165.v1"><name>Clinical_Data_Source</name><description>The source of the clinical data</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024166.v1"><name>Clinician_Type</name><description>Type of clinician who collected the clinical data</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024167.v1"><name>Country_Origin</name><description>Subject's country of birth</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024168.v1"><name>Zip_Abbrev</name><description>First 3 digits of subject's zip code</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024169.v1"><name>Data collected by:This data was collected by</name><description>Defines category of person who completed the form.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024170.v1"><name>Family History:Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</name><description>The presence or absence of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024171.v1"><name>Family History:Ataxia</name><description>The presence or absence of ataxia in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024172.v1"><name>Family History:Autism</name><description>The presence or absence of autism in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024173.v1"><name>Family History:Bipolar (manic-depressive)</name><description>The presence or absence of bipolar disorder in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024174.v1"><name>Family History:Brain aneurysm</name><description>The presence or absence of brain aneurysm in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024175.v1"><name>Family History:Cancer</name><description>The presence or absence of cancer in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024176.v1"><name>Family History:Dementia</name><description>The presence or absence of dementia in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024177.v1"><name>Family History:Depression</name><description>The presence or absence of depression in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024178.v1"><name>Family History:Diabetes</name><description>The presence or absence of diabetes in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024179.v1"><name>Family History:Dystonia</name><description>The presence or absence of dystonia in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024180.v1"><name>Family History:Epilepsy</name><description>The presence or absence of epilepsy in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024181.v1"><name>Family History:Heart disease</name><description>The presence or absence of heart disease in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024182.v1"><name>Family History:Hypertension</name><description>The presence or absence of hypertension in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024183.v1"><name>Family History:memory loss</name><description>The presence or absence of memory loss in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024184.v1"><name>Family History:Migraine</name><description>The presence or absence of migraine in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024185.v1"><name>Family History:Multiple sclerosis</name><description>The presence or absence of multiple sclerosis in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024186.v1"><name>Family History:Muscle disease</name><description>The presence or absence of any type of muscle disease in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024187.v1"><name>Family History:Obsessive Compulsive</name><description>The presence or absence of obsessive compulsive disorder in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024188.v1"><name>Family History:Other</name><description>The clinician interviewing the subject asks about any other known medical illnesses in blood relatives and notes them as comments if they exist.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024189.v1"><name>Family History:Parkinson's</name><description>The presence or absence of Parkinson's disease in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024190.v1"><name>Family History:Schizophrenia</name><description>The presence or absence of schizophrenia in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024191.v1"><name>Family History:Stroke</name><description>The presence or absence of cerebrovascular disease in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024192.v1"><name>Family History:Suicide/Attempt</name><description>The presence or absence of a suicide attempt in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024193.v1"><name>Family History:Tourettes</name><description>The presence or absence of Tourette's syndrome in the subject's blood relatives as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024194.v1"><name>Longitudinal Data:Is this data Longitudinal (Follow-Up) Data?</name><description>Is the data longitudinal or an initial assessment</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024195.v1"><name>Medical History:Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</name><description>The presence or absence of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024196.v1"><name>Medical History:Ataxia</name><description>The presence or absence of ataxia in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024197.v1"><name>Medical History:Autism</name><description>The presence or absence of autism in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024198.v1"><name>Medical History:Bipolar (manic-depressive)</name><description>The presence or absence of bipolar disorder in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024199.v1"><name>Medical History:Brain aneurysm</name><description>The presence or absence of brain aneurysm in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024200.v1"><name>Medical History:Cancer</name><description>The presence or absence of cancer in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024201.v1"><name>Medical History:Dementia</name><description>The presence or absence of dementia in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024202.v1"><name>Medical History:Depression</name><description>The presence or absence of depression in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024203.v1"><name>Medical History:Diabetes</name><description>The presence or absence of diabetes in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024204.v1"><name>Medical History:Dystonia</name><description>The presence or absence of dystonia in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024205.v1"><name>Medical History:Epilepsy</name><description>The presence or absence of epilepsy in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024206.v1"><name>Medical History:Heart disease</name><description>The presence or absence of heart disease in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024207.v1"><name>Medical History:Hypertension</name><description>The presence or absence of hypertension in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024208.v1"><name>Medical History:memory loss</name><description>The presence or absence of memory loss in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024209.v1"><name>Medical History:Migraine</name><description>The presence or absence of migraine in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024210.v1"><name>Medical History:Multiple sclerosis</name><description>The presence or absence of multiple sclerosis in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024211.v1"><name>Medical History:Muscle disease</name><description>The presence or absence of muscle disease in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview; if present, the clinical interview will describe the type of muscle disease and thus may capture disorders that result in weakness, but are not considered to be a disease of the muscle.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024212.v1"><name>Medical History:Obsessive Compulsive</name><description>The presence or absence of obsessive compulsive disorder in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024213.v1"><name>Medical History:Other</name><description>The clinician interviewing the subject asks about any other medical illnesses and notes them as comments if they exist.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024214.v1"><name>Medical History:Parkinson's</name><description>The presence or absence of Parkinson's disease in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024215.v1"><name>Medical History:Schizophrenia</name><description>The presence or absence of schizophrenia in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024216.v1"><name>Medical History:Stroke</name><description>The presence or absence of cerebrovascular disease in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024217.v1"><name>Medical History:Suicide/Attempt</name><description>The subjects themselves indicate a past suicide attempt as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024218.v1"><name>Medical History:Tourettes</name><description>The presence or absence of Tourette's syndrome in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician's interview.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024219.v1"><name>Optional data:Handedness</name><description>The subject has a hand preference (left, right), or uses both hands equally well (ambidextrous).</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024220.v1"><name>Optional data:MMSE (enter score and date)</name><description>The score obtained in the Folstein Mini Mental Status examination.</description><type/><logical_min>30</logical_min></variable><variable id="phv00024221.v1"><name>Optional data:Neurological examination</name><description>The subject either did (yes) or did not (no) undergo a neurological examination.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024222.v1"><name>Optional data:smoking history</name><description>Record of an individual's background with regard to smoking tobacco. This would include such factors as start date, end date (if applicable), number of cigarettes smoked, attempts to quit, and others.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00024223.v1"><name>Optional data:years smoking</name><description>How many years did the person smoke ( if the person is a current or former smoker)?</description><type/><logical_min>0</logical_min><logical_max>99</logical_max></variable><variable id="phv00024224.v1"><name>Type of Control:Type of Control</name><description>Population/convenience control, spousal control, other control.</description><type/></variable></data_table>
