<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht004368.v1" study_id="phs000007.v25" participant_set="9" date_created="Fri Dec 12 15:52:59 2014"><description>Cognitive Impairment, Original and Offspring Cohorts, cases reviewed through 2013. Participants whose performance on the MMSE drops 5 or more points across multiple examinations or 3 or more points from the previous examination or who are referred by themselves, their family, a physician from the community or from a FHS ancillary study examination, are flagged for a follow-up neurological and neuropsychological evaluation.  Those found to be cognitive impaired by either evaluation are brought to a diagnostic  consensus meeting to determine if dementia is evident, and if so, what subtype.</description><variable id="phv00220743.v1"><name>shareid</name><description>Unique study participant identification number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00220744.v1"><name>idtype</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type/><comment>IDTYPE and ID taken together form a unique study participant ID number.</comment><value code="0">Original Cohort</value><value code="1">Offspring Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00220745.v1"><name>cogimp_status</name><description>Cognitive impairment status</description><type/><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00220746.v1"><name>cogimp_stat</name><description>Cognitive impairment comment</description><type/><comment>Character variable.</comment></variable><variable id="phv00220747.v1"><name>entry_date</name><description>Date of entry</description><type/><unit>days</unit><logical_min>2016</logical_min><logical_max>10749</logical_max><comment>For display purposes, only month and year are listed.
		Number of days since Exam 1. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00220748.v1"><name>cogimp_survdate</name><description>Date of cognitive impairment, death, or censoring</description><type/><unit>days</unit><logical_min>2882</logical_min><logical_max>22904</logical_max><comment>For display purposes, only month and year are listed.
		If the month was known, but the day was not, the 15th was used.  If the year was known, but the month and day were not, then June 30th was used.  This logic was used for event dates only, this does not apply to censoring dates or dates of death. 
		Number of days since Exam 1. </comment></variable></data_table>
