<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht004730.v1" study_id="phs000912.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Fri Aug 28 10:19:34 2015"><description>Subject ID, consent group, and case or control status of participants with or without breast cancer and involved in the "San Francisco Bay Area Latina Breast Cancer Study" project.</description><variable id="phv00226540.v1"><name>SUBJECT_ID</name><description>Subject ID</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00226541.v1"><name>Consent</name><description>Consent group as determined by DAC</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>CHALLENGE =*Up for a Challenge - Use of this data is limited to research described for the National Cancer Institute (NCI) "Up for A Challenge" breast cancer genetic epidemiology competition. The goal of this challenge is to use innovative approaches to identify novel biology involved in breast cancer susceptibility including new genes, genetic variants, or sets of genomic features, leading to novel biological hypotheses. Individuals NOT participating in the challenge would NOT be granted access. Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community. CHALLENGE-COL = *Up for a Challenge (Collaboration required) - Use of this data is limited to research described for the National Cancer Institute (NCI) "Up for A Challenge" breast cancer genetic epidemiology competition. The goal of this challenge is to use innovative approaches to identify novel biology involved in breast cancer susceptibility including new genes, genetic variants, or sets of genomic features, leading to novel biological hypotheses. Individuals NOT participating in the challenge would NOT be granted access. Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community. Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s).</comment><value code="1">Up for a Challenge (Publication required) (CHALLENGE)</value><value code="2">Up for a Challenge (Collaboration required, Publication required) (CHALLENGE-COL)</value></variable><variable id="phv00226542.v1"><name>case_status</name><description>Case or control status</description><type/><value code="1">Case</value><value code="2">Control</value></variable></data_table>
