<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?>
<data_table id="pht000322.v1" study_id="phs000126.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Tue Aug 12 13:49:28 2008">

<variable id="phv00045238.v1">
	<name>Age</name>
	<description>Age at enrollment (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
	<unit>Years old</unit>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00065479.v1">
	<name>CLUSTERS_AS_CAUCASIAN</name>
	<description>Individuals were within the bounds of the main cluster derived from the first two components of the multidimensional scaling algorithm in plink utilizing all case-control samples as well as CEU, YRI and CHB_JPT HapMap controls (CHB_JPT data was downloaded from Illumina).</description>
	<value code="0">Not part of Caucasian cluster</value>
	<value code="1">Part of Caucasian cluster</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045244.v1">
	<name>Country_Origin</name>
	<description>Subject&#39;s country of birth (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00065481.v1">
	<name>DNA_SOURCE</name>
	<description>Source of DNA</description>
	<value code="1">Blood</value>
	<value code="2">Whole genome amplified (WGA)</value>
	<value code="3">Lymphoblastoid cell line (LCL)</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045241.v1">
	<name>Ethnicity</name>
	<description>Subject&#39;s ethnicity (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
	<value code="0">Not Hispanic/Latino</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045247.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Amyotrophic_lat</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in the subject blood relatives as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection): present= The individual themselves have a history or diagnosis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis;  absent=The individual themselves have no history or diagnosis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</description>
	<value code="absent">The individual themselves have no history or diagnosis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</value>
	<value code="present">The individual themselves have a history or diagnosis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045248.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Ataxia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of ataxia in the subject blood relatives as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045249.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Autism</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of autism in the subject blood relatives as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045250.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Bipolar</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of bipolar disorder in the subject blood relatives as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045251.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Brain_aneurysm</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of brain aneurysm in the subject blood relatives as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045252.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Cancer</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of cancer in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045253.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Dementia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of dementia in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045254.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Depression</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of depression in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045255.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Diabetes</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of diabetes in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045256.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Dystonia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of dystonia in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045257.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Epilepsy</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of epilepsy in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045258.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Heart_disease</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of heart disease in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045259.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Hypertension</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of hypertension in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045260.v1">
	<name>Family_History_memory_loss</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of memory loss in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045261.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Migraine</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of migraine in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045262.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Multiple_scleros</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of multiple sclerosis in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045263.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Muscle_disease</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of muscle disease of any type in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045264.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Obsessive_Comp</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of obsessive compulsive disorder in the subject&#39;s blood relatives as determined by clinician&#39;s interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045265.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Other</name>
	<description>The clinician interviewing the subject asks about any other known medical illnesses in blood relatives and writes in as comments if so (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045266.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Parkinson_s</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of Parkinson disease in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045267.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Schizophrenia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of schizophrenia in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045268.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Stroke</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of cerebrovascular disease in the subject blood relatives, to be delineated, as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045269.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Suicide_Attempt</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of suicide attempt in the subject&#39;s blood relatives as documented based on clinician interview of the subject (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045270.v1">
	<name>Family_History_Tourettes</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of Tourette&#39;s syndrome in the subject&#39;s blood relatives as determined by clinician&#39;s interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00048458.v1">
	<name>FAM_NO</name>
	<description>Family number (3000-3999 from Coriell) (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045239.v1">
	<name>Gender</name>
	<description>Gender: male, female (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
	<value code="F">Female</value>
	<value code="M">Male</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045296.v1">
	<name>Handedness</name>
	<description>The subject has a hand preference (left, right), or uses both hands equally well (ambidextrous) (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00065482.v1">
	<name>LOW_CALL_RATE</name>
	<description>Call rate below 96%</description>
	<value code="0">Acceptable quality</value>
	<value code="1">Poor quality</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00065483.v1">
	<name>LOW_INTENSITY_CNV</name>
	<description>Poor data quality for copy number variant data (standard deviation for log R ratio for chromosome 1 above 0.25)</description>
	<value code="0">Acceptable quality</value>
	<value code="1">Poor quality</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045272.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Amyotrophic_lat</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in the subject themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045273.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Ataxia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of ataxia in the subject themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045274.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Autism</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of autism in the subject themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045275.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Bipolar</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of bipolar disorder in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045276.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Brain_aneurysm</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of brain aneurysm in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045277.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Cancer</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of cancer in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045278.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Dementia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of dementia in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045279.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Depression</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of depression in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045280.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Diabetes</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of diabetes in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045281.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Dystonia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of dystonia in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045282.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Epilepsy</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of epilepsy in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045283.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Heart_disease</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of heart disease in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045284.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Hypertension</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of hypertension in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045285.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_memory_loss</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of memory loss in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045286.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Migraine</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of migraine in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045287.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Multiple_scleros</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of multiple sclerosis in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045288.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Muscle_disease</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of muscle disease in the subjects themselves as determined by clinical interview; if present, the clinical interview will describe the type of muscle disease and thus may capture disorders that result in weakness, but are not considered to be a disease of the muscle (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045289.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Obsessive_Comp</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of obsessive compulsive disorder in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician&#39;s interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045290.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Other</name>
	<description>The clinician interviewing the subject asks about any other medical illnesses and writes in as comments if so (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045291.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Parkinson_s</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of Parkinson disease in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045292.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Schizophrenia</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of schizophrenia in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045293.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Stroke</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of cerebrovascular disease in the subjects themselves as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045294.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Suicide_Attempt</name>
	<description>The subject themselves endorses a past suicide attempt as documented based on clinician interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045295.v1">
	<name>Medical_History_Tourettes</name>
	<description>The presence or absence of Tourette&#39;s syndrome in the subjects themselves as determined by clinician&#39;s interview (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045297.v1">
	<name>MMSE_score</name>
	<description>Mini Mental Status Score (the subject has a score on the Folstein Mini mental status exam as specified) (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
	<unit>Score</unit>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045298.v1">
	<name>Neurological_exam</name>
	<description>The subject either did (yes) or did not (no) undergo a neurological examination (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045240.v1">
	<name>Race</name>
	<description>Race (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
	<value code="1">Caucasian</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045236.v1">
	<name>ref</name>
	<description>Coriell ID (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045299.v1">
	<name>Smoking_history</name>
	<description>A record of an individual&#39;s background in regard to smoking tobacco. This would include such factors as start date, end date (if applicable), number of cigarette smoked, attempts to quit, and others. (Current indicates a current smoker; former indicates the subject smoked in the past but does not smoke now; never indicates that the individual has never smoked). (See phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00048459.v1">
	<name>SUBJ_NO</name>
	<description>Individual number (first digit is always a 3 and is followed by the numerical portion of the Coriell ID) (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045301.v1">
	<name>Type_of_Control</name>
	<description>Defines the type of control (see phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00065485.v1">
	<name>USED_IN_MARKER_QC</name>
	<description>Clean dataset used to create marker QC filter thresholds</description>
	<value code="0">Not used</value>
	<value code="1">Used</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00065484.v1">
	<name>USED_IN_PRELIM_ANALYSES</name>
	<description>Clean dataset used to perform &quot;pre-computes&quot; of association analyses</description>
	<value code="0">Not used</value>
	<value code="1">Used</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00065480.v1">
	<name>XO_OR_XO_MOSAIC</name>
	<description>XO (only one X chromosome and no Y chromosome observed) or XO mosaic - possible Turner syndrome, probable artifact of the cell line.</description>
	<value code="0">Normal</value>
	<value code="1">Mosaic</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00045300.v1">
	<name>Years_smoking</name>
	<description>How many years did the person smoke, if the person is a current or former smoker? (Number of years smoked total). (See phs000004: NINDS Repository Neurologically Normal Control Collection).</description>
	<unit>Years</unit>
</variable>

</data_table>
