<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?>
<data_table id="pht000309.v2" study_id="phs000014.v4" participant_set="2" date_created="Fri Dec  5 17:15:14 2008">

<unique_key phv="00036469" version="2">EVENT</unique_key>
<unique_key phv="00036471" version="2">date</unique_key>
<unique_key phv="00036472" version="2">shareid</unique_key>

<variable id="phv00036471.v2">
	<name>DATE</name>
	<description>DATE OF EVENT, NUMBER OF DAYS SINCE EXAM 1 </description>
	<comment>WHEN EXACT DATE IS UNAVAILABLE, AN APPROXIMATE DATE *OR* A MIDPOINT DATE BETWEEN TWO EXAMS, TWO MEDICAL ENCOUNTERS OR EXAM AND MEDICAL MAY BE USED. </comment>
	<unit>DAYS</unit>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00036469.v2">
	<name>EVENT</name>
	<description>EVENT NUMBER ON SEQUENCE OF EVENTS</description>
	<value code="1">MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION RECOGNIZED, WITH DIAGNOSTIC ELECTROCARDIOGRAM</value>
	<value code="10">DEFINITE CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT AT EXAM 1, BUT QUESTIONABLE TYPE.</value>
	<value code="11">ATHEROTHROMBOTIC INFARCTION</value>
	<value code="12">TRANSIENT ISCHEMIC ATTACK (ONLY THE 1ST TIA IS CODED)</value>
	<value code="13">CEREBRAL EMBOLISM</value>
	<value code="14">INTRACEREBRAL HEMORRHAGE</value>
	<value code="15">SUBARACHNOID HEMORRHAGE</value>
	<value code="16">OTHER CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT</value>
	<value code="19">QUESTIONABLE CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT AT EXAM 1, DATE OF EXAM 1 (UNLESS DATE AVAILABLE)</value>
	<value code="2">MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION RECOGNIZED, WITHOUT DIAGNOSTIC ELECTROCARDIOGRAM, WITH ENZYMES AND HISTORY</value>
	<value code="20">DEATH, NOT REVIEWED</value>
	<value code="21">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE   SUDDEN, WITHIN 1 HOUR</value>
	<value code="22">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE, 1-23 HOURS, NONSUDDEN</value>
	<value code="23">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE, 24-47 HOURS, NONSUDDEN</value>
	<value code="24">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE, 48 HOURS OR MORE, NONSUDDEN</value>
	<value code="25">DEATH, CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT</value>
	<value code="26">DEATH, OTHER CARDIOVASCULAR DISEASE</value>
	<value code="27">DEATH, CANCER</value>
	<value code="28">DEATH, OTHER CAUSES</value>
	<value code="29">DEATH, CAUSE UNKNOWN</value>
	<value code="3">MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION RECOGNIZED, WITHOUT DIAGNOSTIC ELECTROCARDIOGRAM, WITH AUTOPSY EVIDENCE, NEW EVENT (SEE ALSO CODE 09)</value>
	<value code="30">INTERMITTANT CLAUDICATION, DATE MIDPOINT OF INTERVAL AS ANGINA PECTORIS, ALSO DATE ONLY FIRST EVENT</value>
	<value code="39">QUESTIONABLE INTERMITTANT CLAUDICATION AT EXAM 1, USE EXAM 1 DATE FOR ORIGINAL COHORT AND OFFSPRING COHORT. FOR THE OTHER COHORT GROUPS, A DATE 
 OTHER THAN THE EXAM 1 DATE IS USED IF AVAILABLE.</value>
	<value code="4">MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION UNRECOGNIZED, SILENT</value>
	<value code="40">CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE NOT HOSPITALIZED, ON EXAM OR MD NOTES (IF CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE FOUND ON FHS EXAM, USE FHS EXAM DATE)</value>
	<value code="41">CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE HOSPITALIZED</value>
	<value code="49">QUESTIONABLE CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AT EXAM 1, USE EXAM 1 DATE FOR ORIGINAL COHORT AND OFFSPRING COHORT.  FOR THE OTHER COHORT GROUPS, A DATE 
 OTHER THAN THE EXAM 1 DATE IS USED IF AVAILABLE.</value>
	<value code="5">MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION UNRECOGNIZED, NOT SILENT</value>
	<value code="6">ANGINA PECTORIS, FIRST EPISODE ONLY. IF DATE OF ANGINA PECTORIS WAS UNAVAILABLE, ANGINA PECTORIS IS DATED AS MIDPOINT OF INTERVAL BETWEEN MEDICAL ENCOUNTERS 
 (FHS EXAMS, HOSPITALIZATIONS OR MD OFFICE VISITS). IF ANGINA PECTORIS OCCURRED WITH MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, THEN USE SAME DATE AS MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY.  BEFORE 1987, IF ANGINA PECTORIS OCCURED JUST BEFORE MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, THEN ANGINA PECTORIS DATE WAS ASSIGNED 3 MONTHS BEFORE	MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY.  IF AP OCCURRED JUST AFTER MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, THEN AP DATE WAS ASSIGNED 3 MONTHS AFTER MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY. BEGINNING IN 1987, IF APPROXIMATE OR EXACT DATE OF NEW ANGINA WAS AVAILABLE, THEN THAT DATE WAS ASSIGNED AS DATE OF ANGINA PECTORIS.</value>
	<value code="7">CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, DEFINITE BY BOTH HISTORY AND ELECTROCARDIOGRAM.</value>
	<value code="8">QUESTIONABLE MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION AT EXAM 1, DATE SAME DATE AS EXAM 1 FOR ORIGINAL COHORT AND OFFSPRING COHORT. FOR THE OTHER COHORT GROUPS, A DATE 
 OTHER THAN THE EXAM 1 DATE IS USED IF AVAILABLE. ANY QUESTIONABLE MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION EPISODE AT EXAM 1:  DEFINITE MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION HISTORY WITHOUT ENZYMES OR AUTOPSY, OR POSSIBLE MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION-ELECTROCARDIOGRAM.  DOES NOT INCLUDE QUESTIONABLE ANGINA PECTORIS.</value>
	<value code="9">MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION ACUTE AUTOPSY, NOT A NEW EVENT.  THIS IS CODED WHEN THERE HAS BEEN A PREVIOUSLY CODED MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION (1 OR 2) AND THAT MYOCARDIAL INFARCATION SHOWS ON AUTOPSY.</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00036470.v2">
	<name>IDTYPE</name>
	<description>COHORT IDENTIFIER</description>
	<value code="0">ORIGINAL COHORT GROUP</value>
	<value code="1">OFFSPRING GROUP</value>
	<value code="2">NEW OFFSPRING SPOUSE</value>
	<value code="3">GENERATION 3</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00036472.v2">
	<name>shareid</name>
	<description>UNIQUE PARTICIPANT ID</description>
</variable>

</data_table>
