<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002235.v4" study_id="phs000007.v28" participant_set="10" date_created="Mon Apr 25 18:20:27 2016"><description>Soluble ST2 (sST2), Offspring Cohort Exam 6. Soluble ST2 is a peptide with a structural sequence that identifies it as an interleukin-receptor family member. ST2 exists both in membrane-bound form (ST2 ligand, or ST2L) as well as in a shed, truncated soluble form (soluble ST2, or sST2). Although described to play a role in inflammation and tolerance (mediating function of T-helper cells), ST2 clearly has a cardiovascular role, which may be more important than its function in the inflammatory system. Lee and colleagues demonstrated that ST2 gene transcripts were dramatically upregulated in a model of myocyte stretch in a manner reminiscent of BNP. Furthermore, in the context of left ventricular pressure and volume overload, interruption of the ST2 gene leads to a deleterious phenotype marked by unchecked myocardial hypertrophy, dilatation of ventricular chambers, and reduction in ejection fraction. The functional ligand for ST2L and sST2 is interleukin-33, a cardiac fibroblast protein also produced in response to stretch. Interleukin-33 is known to mediate the negative effects of pressure and volume overload on ventricular myocytes; for instance, infusion of this hormone prevents remodeling when the heart is acutely exposed to pressure overload. Collectively, these experimental data suggest that the ST2/IL-33 system plays a key role in the cardiovascular response to pressure and volume overload. Multiple studies have now shown that, in patients with HF or myocardial infarction, elevated sST2 concentrations predict an increased prevalence of cardiac structural abnormalities, elevated filling pressures, recurrent HF events, and death. The prognostic value of sST2 is additive to conventional troponins and BNP/NT-proBNP. Samples were collected from citrated plasma.</description><variable id="phv00159550.v4"><name>shareid</name><description>Framingham Heart Study participant SHARe ID number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00159551.v4"><name>ST2</name><description>Soluble ST2 (sample: citrated plasma)</description><type>decimal</type><unit>ng/mL</unit><logical_min>3.16</logical_min><logical_max>119.55</logical_max></variable><variable id="phv00159552.v4"><name>IDTYPE</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort group</description><type>encoded</type><value code="1">Offspring Cohort</value></variable></data_table>
