<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht003095.v1" study_id="phs000007.v28" participant_set="10" date_created="Mon Apr 25 18:41:51 2016"><description>Methylmalonic Acid (MMA), Generation 3 Exam 1. This assay was performed on Generation 3 Exam 1 study participants who had a bone mineral density measured by CT and available plasma samples at Exam 1. This dataset is part of the ancillary study Framingham Osteoporosis Study (FOS). Individuals with homocystinuria, a biochemical abnormality causing elevated plasma Hcy concentrations, have an increased prevalence of osteoporosis. This observation suggested that milder elevations of Hcy may have adverse effects on bone. A recent study by our group found that elevated plasma Hcy concentration was associated with a two to four-fold increased risk of hip fracture in community-dwelling elders. These results were confirmed in the Rotterdam Study for all fractures. None of these studies, however, were able to establish a causal mechanism for the effect of Hcy on fracture. Thus, it is still unclear whether or not Hey directly affects bone strength or is an "innocent bystander." Potential candidates for the true causative factor may lie along the pathway of Hcy metabolism. Hcy is metabolized through two metabolic pathways: remethylation and transsulfuration. In remethylation, Hcy is converted to methionine by the donation of a methyl group from 5-mehtyltetrahydrofolate, the main circulating form of folate. 5-methyltetrahydrofolate is synthesized from 5, 10-methylenetetrahydrofolate by the enzyme methylenetetrahydrofolate reductase (MTHFR). The remethylation of Hey to methionine is catalyzed by the enzyme methionine synthase (MTR). which is activated by the vitamin B12-dependent enzyme methionine synthase reductase (MTRR). Through the trans-sulfuration pathway, Hey is converted to cystathionine in a reaction catalyzed by the vitamin B6-containing enzyme cystathionine (3-synthase (CBS). Thus the aim of this study is to test the association between common variants in the above four genes and volumetric BMD of the spine and to test for an interaction between common variants in these four genes and levels of B12, MMA, folate and B6 on volumetric BMD of the spine.</description><variable id="phv00177784.v1"><name>shareid</name><description>Unique study participant identification number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00177785.v1"><name>IDTYPE</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type>encoded</type><comment>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</comment><value code="3">Generation 3 Cohort</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00177786.v1"><name>mma</name><description>Methylmalonic acid (sample: EDTA plasma)</description><type>decimal</type><unit>pmol/mL</unit><logical_min>45.42</logical_min><logical_max>1445.4</logical_max><value code=".">Missing</value></variable></data_table>
