<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht000691.v10" study_id="phs000007.v26" participant_set="10" date_created="Fri Jul 17 11:37:49 2015"><description>Moderate Dementia Plus, Original and Offspring Cohorts where cases were reviewed through 2013. Variables includes dementia status (at least mild), dementia subtype (classified with Alzheimer's disease and stroke), date known to be cognitively intact and date of incident dementia, death or censoring. The Epidemiology of Dementia Study has tracked incident cases of dementia in the Framingham cohort. Although not formally initiated until 1986, the initial baseline dementia-free Original cohort was determined from 1976-78. Tracking for incident dementia in the Offspring cohort also began in 1976 and subjects have had serial MMSE since 1991. Participants whose performance on the MMSE drops 5 or more points across multiple examinations or 3 or more points from the previous examination or who are referred b themselves, their family, a physician from the community or from a FHS ancillary study examination, are flagged for a follow-up neurological and neuropsychological evaluation. Those found to be cognitive impaired by either evaluation are brought to a diagnostic consensus meeting to determine if dementia is evident, and if so, what subtype. Additional information about disease progression (when applicable) is also recorded.</description><variable id="phv00069851.v9"><name>shareid</name><description>Unique study participant identification number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00069847.v9"><name>idtype</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type/><comment>IDTYPE and ID taken together form a unique study participant ID number.</comment><value code="0">Original Cohort</value><value code="1">Offspring Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00069846.v9"><name>type</name><description>Dementia subtype</description><type/><comment>Text field.
		Blank = Dementia status, at least moderate = No. </comment><value code="AD_STR">Alzheimer's disease with stroke</value><value code="AD_VaD">Mixed dementia: Alzheimer's disease and vascular dementia</value><value code="AD_noSTR">Alzheimer's disease without stroke</value><value code="VaD_noAD">Vascular dementia with no Alzheimer's disease</value><value code="other">Neither Alzheimer's disease nor vascular dementia</value></variable><variable id="phv00069845.v9"><name>modDEM_status</name><description>Dementia status, moderate</description><type/><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00219218.v1"><name>modAD_status</name><description>Alzheimer's disease status, moderate</description><type/><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00069848.v9"><name>entry_date</name><description>Date of entry</description><type/><unit>days</unit><logical_min>2016</logical_min><logical_max>10749</logical_max><comment>For display purposes, only month and year are listed.
		Number of days since Exam 1. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00069850.v9"><name>moddem_survdate</name><description>Date of incident dementia, death, or censoring</description><type/><unit>days</unit><logical_min>2882</logical_min><logical_max>23739</logical_max><comment>For display purposes, only month and year are listed.
		If the month was known, but the day was not, the 15th was used.  If the year was known, but the month and day were not, then June 30th was used.  This logic was used for event dates only, this does not apply to censoring dates or dates of death. 
		Number of days since Exam 1. </comment></variable></data_table>
