<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht000338.v1" study_id="phs000086.v3" participant_set="1" date_created="Tue Nov  4 13:23:24 2014"><description>EDIC. Health care delivery of participants with Type 1 diabetes and involved in the "Diabetes Control and Complications Trial (DCCT) and Epidemiology of Diabetes Interventions and Complications Study (EDIC)" project.</description><variable id="phv00050312.v1"><name>CLINIC</name><description>A1. Identifying information: deidentified EDIC clinic number</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050313.v1"><name>FORM</name><description>EDIC form number</description><type>int</type></variable><variable id="phv00050314.v1"><name>EDICYEAR</name><description>EDIC year</description><type>byte</type><unit>Years</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050315.v1"><name>GOB1</name><description>B1. Health care delivery: were you a patient in a nursing home</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050316.v1"><name>GOB1A</name><description>B1a. Health care delivery: number of  nights stayed in nursing home</description><type>byte</type><unit>Number of  nights</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050317.v1"><name>GOB2</name><description>B2. Health care delivery: did you stay in hospital overnight</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050318.v1"><name>GOB2A</name><description>B2a. Health care delivery: total number of times stay in hospital</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050319.v1"><name>GOB2B</name><description>B2b. Health care delivery: how many nights all together in hospital</description><type>byte</type><unit>Nights</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050320.v1"><name>GOB2D</name><description>B2d. Health care delivery: number of nights in hospital overnight not paid for</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050321.v1"><name>GOB2DI</name><description>B2di. Health care delivery: number of times hospital stay overnight not paid for</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050322.v1"><name>GOB2DII</name><description>B2dii. Health care delivery: total number of nights in hospital not paid for</description><type>byte</type><unit>Nights</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050323.v1"><name>GOB3A</name><description>B3a. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: endocrinologist</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050324.v1"><name>GOB3B</name><description>B6b. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: ophthalmologist,  (check-up) ever seen</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050325.v1"><name>GOB3C</name><description>B3c. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: ophthalmologist, (other reason) cataracts, ever seen</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050326.v1"><name>GOB3D</name><description>B3d. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: optometrist</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050327.v1"><name>GOB3E</name><description>B3e. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: cardiologist, ever seen</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050328.v1"><name>GOB3F</name><description>B3f. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: podiatrist, ever seen</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050329.v1"><name>GOB3G</name><description>B3g. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nephrologists, ever seen</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050330.v1"><name>GOB3H</name><description>B3h. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: practitioner, ever seen</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050331.v1"><name>GOB3I</name><description>B3i. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: other doctor, ever seen</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050332.v1"><name>GOB4A</name><description>B4a. Health care delivery. How many visits per year does the doctor who treats your diabetes recommend that you make to:  eye doctor, visits per year</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">More than 2 visits per year</value><value code="2">About two visits per year</value><value code="3">About one visit per  year</value><value code="4">Less than one visit per year</value><value code="5">Does not recommend</value></variable><variable id="phv00050333.v1"><name>GOB4B</name><description>B4b. Health care delivery. How many visits per year does the doctor who treats your diabetes recommend that you make to: foot doctor, visits per year</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">More than 2 visits per year</value><value code="2">About two visits per year</value><value code="3">About one visit per  year</value><value code="4">Less than one visit per year</value><value code="5">Does not recommend</value></variable><variable id="phv00050334.v1"><name>GOB4C</name><description>B4c. Health care delivery. How many visits per year does the doctor who treats your diabetes recommend that you make to: education specialist, visits per year</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">More than 2 visits per year</value><value code="2">About two visits per year</value><value code="3">About one visit per  year</value><value code="4">Less than one visit per year</value><value code="5">Does not recommend</value></variable><variable id="phv00050335.v1"><name>GOB4D</name><description>B4d. Health care delivery. How many visits per year does the doctor who treats your diabetes recommend that you make to: dietitian, visits per year</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">More than 2 visits per year</value><value code="2">About two visits per year</value><value code="3">About one visit per  year</value><value code="4">Less than one visit per year</value><value code="5">Does not recommend</value></variable><variable id="phv00050336.v1"><name>GOB5</name><description>B5. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: past 2 weeks total visits to doctors</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050337.v1"><name>GOB6A</name><description>B6a. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: diabetes doctor, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050338.v1"><name>GOB6A1</name><description>B6a1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: diabetes doctor, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050339.v1"><name>GOB6A2</name><description>B6a2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: diabetes doctor, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050340.v1"><name>GOB6A3</name><description>B6a3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: diabetes doctor, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050341.v1"><name>GOB6A4</name><description>B6a4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: diabetes doctor, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050342.v1"><name>GOB6B</name><description>B6b. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: endocrinologist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050343.v1"><name>GOB6B1</name><description>B6b1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: endocrinologist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050344.v1"><name>GOB6B2</name><description>B6b2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: endocrinologist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050345.v1"><name>GOB6B3</name><description>B6b3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: endocrinologist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050346.v1"><name>GOB6B4</name><description>B6b4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: endocrinologist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050347.v1"><name>GOB6C</name><description>B6c. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: ophthalmologist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050348.v1"><name>GOB6C1</name><description>B6c1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: ophthalmologist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050349.v1"><name>GOB6C2</name><description>B6c2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: ophthalmologist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050350.v1"><name>GOB6C3</name><description>B6c3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: ophthalmologist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050351.v1"><name>GOB6C4</name><description>Bbc4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: ophthalmologist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050352.v1"><name>GOB6D</name><description>B6d. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: optometrist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050353.v1"><name>GOB6D1</name><description>B6d1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: optometrist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050354.v1"><name>GOB6D2</name><description>B6d2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: optometrist: number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050355.v1"><name>GOB6D3</name><description>B6d3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: optometrist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050356.v1"><name>GOB6D4</name><description>B6d4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: optometrist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050357.v1"><name>GOB6E</name><description>B6e. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: cardiologist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050358.v1"><name>GOB6E1</name><description>B6e1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: cardiologist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050359.v1"><name>GOB6E2</name><description>B6e2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: cardiologist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050360.v1"><name>GOB6E3</name><description>B6e3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: cardiologist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050361.v1"><name>GOB6E4</name><description>B6e4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: cardiologist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050362.v1"><name>GOB6F</name><description>B6f. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nephrologist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050363.v1"><name>GOB6F1</name><description>B6f1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nephrologist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050364.v1"><name>GOB6F2</name><description>B6f2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nephrologist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050365.v1"><name>GOB6F3</name><description>B6f3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nephrologist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050366.v1"><name>GOB6F4</name><description>B6f4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nephrologist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050367.v1"><name>GOB6G</name><description>B6g. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: surgeon, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050368.v1"><name>GOB6G1</name><description>B6g1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: surgeon, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050369.v1"><name>GOB6G2</name><description>B6g2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: surgeon, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050370.v1"><name>GOB6G3</name><description>B6g3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: surgeon, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050371.v1"><name>GOB6G4</name><description>B6g4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: surgeon, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050372.v1"><name>GOB6H</name><description>B6h. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: urologist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050373.v1"><name>GOB6H1</name><description>B6h1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: urologist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050374.v1"><name>GOB6H2</name><description>Bh2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: urologist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050375.v1"><name>GOB6H3</name><description>Bh3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: urologist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050376.v1"><name>GOB6H4</name><description>B6h4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: urologist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050377.v1"><name>GOB6I</name><description>B6i. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: psychiatrist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050378.v1"><name>GOB6I1</name><description>B6i1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: psychiatrist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050379.v1"><name>GOB6I2</name><description>B6i2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: psychiatrist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050380.v1"><name>GOB6I3</name><description>B6i3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: psychiatrist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050381.v1"><name>GOB6I4</name><description>B6i4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: psychiatrist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050382.v1"><name>GOB6J</name><description>B6j. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: general internist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050383.v1"><name>GOB6J1</name><description>B6j1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: general internist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050384.v1"><name>GOB6J2</name><description>B6j2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: general internist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050385.v1"><name>GOB6J3</name><description>B6j3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: general internist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050386.v1"><name>GOB6J4</name><description>B6j4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: general internist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050387.v1"><name>GOB6K</name><description>B6k. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: podiatrist, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050388.v1"><name>GOB6K1</name><description>B6k1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: podiatrist, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050389.v1"><name>GOB6K2</name><description>B6k2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: podiatrist, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050390.v1"><name>GOB6K3</name><description>B6k3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: podiatrist, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050391.v1"><name>GOB6K4</name><description>B6k4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: podiatrist, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050392.v1"><name>GOB6L</name><description>B6l. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nurse practitioner, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050393.v1"><name>GOB6L1</name><description>B6l1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nurse practitioner, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050394.v1"><name>GOB6L2</name><description>B6l2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nurse practitioner, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050395.v1"><name>GOB6L3</name><description>B6l3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nurse practitioner, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050396.v1"><name>GOB6L4</name><description>B6l4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: nurse practitioner, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050397.v1"><name>GOB6M</name><description>B6m. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: dietitian, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050398.v1"><name>GOB6M1</name><description>B6m1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: dietitian, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050399.v1"><name>GOB6M2</name><description>B6m2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: dietitian, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050400.v1"><name>GOB6M3</name><description>B6m3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: dietitian, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050401.v1"><name>GOB6M4</name><description>B6m4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: dietitian, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050402.v1"><name>GOB6N</name><description>B6n. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: other provider, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050403.v1"><name>GOB6N1</name><description>B6n1. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: other provider, number of visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050404.v1"><name>GOB6N2</name><description>B6n2. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: other provider, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050405.v1"><name>GOB6N3</name><description>B6n3. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: other provider, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050406.v1"><name>GOB6N4</name><description>B6n4. Health care delivery. Have you ever seen this type of doctor: other provider, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050407.v1"><name>GOB7</name><description>B7. Health care delivery. Past 6 month total number of health care visits</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050408.v1"><name>GOB8A</name><description>B8a. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test of blood glucose</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050409.v1"><name>GOB8A1</name><description>B8a1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test of blood glucose: how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050410.v1"><name>GOB8A2</name><description>B8a2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test of blood glucose: number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050411.v1"><name>GOB8A3</name><description>B8a3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test of blood glucose: number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050412.v1"><name>GOB8A4</name><description>B8a4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test of blood glucose: number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050413.v1"><name>GOB8B</name><description>B8b. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: other blood tests</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050414.v1"><name>GOB8B1</name><description>B8b1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: other blood tests, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050415.v1"><name>GOB8B2</name><description>B8b2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: other blood tests, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050416.v1"><name>GOB8B3</name><description>B8b3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: other blood tests, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050417.v1"><name>GOB8B4</name><description>B8b4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: other blood tests, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050418.v1"><name>GOB8C</name><description>B8c. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: ECG, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050419.v1"><name>GOB8C1</name><description>B8c1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: ECG, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050420.v1"><name>GOB8C2</name><description>B8c2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: ECG, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050421.v1"><name>GOB8C3</name><description>B8c3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: ECG, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050422.v1"><name>GOB8C4</name><description>B8c4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: ECG, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050423.v1"><name>GOB8D</name><description>B8d. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: echocardiogram, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050424.v1"><name>GOB8D1</name><description>B8d1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: echocardiogram: how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050425.v1"><name>GOB8D2</name><description>B8d2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: echocardiogram, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050426.v1"><name>GOB8D3</name><description>B8d3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: echocardiogram, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050427.v1"><name>GOB8D4</name><description>B8d4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: echocardiogram, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050428.v1"><name>GOB8E</name><description>B8e. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: stress test, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050429.v1"><name>GOB8E1</name><description>B8e1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: stress test, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050430.v1"><name>GOB8E2</name><description>B8e2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: stress test, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050431.v1"><name>GOB8E3</name><description>B8e3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: stress test, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050432.v1"><name>GOB8E4</name><description>B8e4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: stress test, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050433.v1"><name>GOB8F</name><description>B8f. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: chest x-ray, seen past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050434.v1"><name>GOB8F1</name><description>B8f1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: chest x-ray, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050435.v1"><name>GOB8F2</name><description>B8f2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: chest x-ray, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050436.v1"><name>GOB8F3</name><description>B8f3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: chest x-ray, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050437.v1"><name>GOB8F4</name><description>B8f4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: chest x-ray, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050438.v1"><name>GOB8G</name><description>B8g. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: urine tests, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050439.v1"><name>GOB8G1</name><description>B8g1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: urine tests, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050440.v1"><name>GOB8G2</name><description>B8g2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: urine tests, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050441.v1"><name>GOB8G3</name><description>B8g3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: urine tests, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050442.v1"><name>GOB8G4</name><description>B8g4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: urine tests, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050443.v1"><name>GOB8HA</name><description>B8ha. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: A. other major tests, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050444.v1"><name>GOB8HA1</name><description>B8ha1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: A. other major tests, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050445.v1"><name>GOB8HA2</name><description>B8ha2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: A. other major tests, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050446.v1"><name>GOB8HA3</name><description>B8ha3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: A. other major tests, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050447.v1"><name>GOB8HA4</name><description>B8ha4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: A. other major tests, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050448.v1"><name>GOB8HB</name><description>B8hb. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: B. other major tests, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050449.v1"><name>GOB8HB1</name><description>B8hb1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: B. other major tests, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050450.v1"><name>GOB8HB2</name><description>B8hb2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: B. other major tests, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050451.v1"><name>GOB8HB3</name><description>B8hb3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: B. other major tests, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050452.v1"><name>GOB8HB4</name><description>B8hb4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: B. other major tests, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050453.v1"><name>GOB8HC</name><description>B8hc. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: C. other major tests, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050454.v1"><name>GOB8HC1</name><description>B8hc1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: C. other major tests, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050455.v1"><name>GOB8HC2</name><description>B8hc2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: C. other major tests, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050456.v1"><name>GOB8HC3</name><description>B8hc3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: C. other major tests, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050457.v1"><name>GOB8HC4</name><description>B8hc4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: C. other major tests, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050458.v1"><name>GOB8HD</name><description>B8hd. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: D. other major tests, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050459.v1"><name>GOB8HD1</name><description>B8hd1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: D. other major tests, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050460.v1"><name>GOB8HD2</name><description>B8hd2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: D. other major tests, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050461.v1"><name>GOB8HD3</name><description>B8hd3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: D. other major tests, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050462.v1"><name>GOB8HD4</name><description>B8hd4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: D. other major tests, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050463.v1"><name>GOB8HE</name><description>B8he. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: E. other major tests, in past 6 months</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050464.v1"><name>GOB8HE1</name><description>B8he1. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: E. other major tests, how many times</description><type>byte</type><unit>Times</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050465.v1"><name>GOB8HE2</name><description>B8he2. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: E. other major tests, number of visits paid for by insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050466.v1"><name>GOB8HE3</name><description>B8he3. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: E. other major tests, number of visits paid for by other insurance</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050467.v1"><name>GOB8HE4</name><description>B8he4. Health care delivery. During the past 6 months have you had laboratory test: E. other major tests, number of visits paid for by self</description><type>byte</type><unit>Visits</unit></variable><variable id="phv00050468.v1"><name>GOC1</name><description>C1. Reimbursements. Insurance provides for diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050469.v1"><name>GOC1A</name><description>C1a. Reimbursements. Medicare provides for diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050470.v1"><name>GOC1B</name><description>Cb1. Reimbursements. Medicaid provides for diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050471.v1"><name>GOC1C</name><description>C1c. Reimbursements. Government plan provides for diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050472.v1"><name>GOC1C1</name><description>C1c1. Reimbursements. Government: plan obtained from</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Employment</value><value code="2">Spouse's employment</value><value code="3">Parent's employment</value><value code="4">Private money</value></variable><variable id="phv00050473.v1"><name>GOC1D</name><description>C1d. Reimbursements. Blue Cross/ Blue Shield provides for diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050474.v1"><name>GOC1D1</name><description>C1d1. Reimbursements. Blue Cross/ Blue Shield plan obtained from</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Employment</value><value code="2">Spouse's employment</value><value code="3">Parent's employment</value><value code="4">Private money</value></variable><variable id="phv00050475.v1"><name>GOC1E</name><description>C1e. Reimbursements. HMO plan provides for diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050476.v1"><name>GOC1E1</name><description>C1e1. Reimbursements. HMO plan obtained from</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Employment</value><value code="2">Spouse's employment</value><value code="3">Parent's employment</value><value code="4">Private money</value></variable><variable id="phv00050477.v1"><name>GOC1F</name><description>C1f. Reimbursements. Private insurance provides diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050478.v1"><name>GOC1F1</name><description>C1f1. Reimbursements. Private insurance obtained from</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Employment</value><value code="2">Spouse's employment</value><value code="3">Parent's employment</value><value code="4">Private money</value></variable><variable id="phv00050479.v1"><name>GOC1G</name><description>C1g. Reimbursements. Other provides for diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050480.v1"><name>GOC1G1</name><description>C1g1. Reimbursements. Other obtained from</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Employment</value><value code="2">Spouse's employment</value><value code="3">Parent's employment</value><value code="4">Private money</value></variable><variable id="phv00050481.v1"><name>GOC2A</name><description>C2a. Reimbursement: insulin</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050482.v1"><name>GOC2B</name><description>C2b. Reimbursement: blood glucose meters</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050483.v1"><name>GOC2C</name><description>C2c. Reimbursement: blood glucose strips</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050484.v1"><name>GOC2D</name><description>C2d. Reimbursement: syringes, infusion pump</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050485.v1"><name>GOC2E</name><description>C2e. Reimbursement: hemoglobin A1c test</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050486.v1"><name>GOC2F</name><description>C2f. Reimbursement: doctors visits</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050487.v1"><name>GOC2G</name><description>C2g. Reimbursement: diabetes educational services</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050488.v1"><name>GOC2H</name><description>C2h. Reimbursement: mental health service</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050489.v1"><name>GOC2I</name><description>C2i. Reimbursement: diabetes complications</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value><value code="3">Uncertain</value></variable><variable id="phv00050490.v1"><name>GOD1</name><description>D1. Health care scheduling. Did not see doctor and would have liked to</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050491.v1"><name>GODACARE</name><description>D1.  Health care conditions: general, did not think condition was serious</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050492.v1"><name>GODAEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, did not think was serious</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050493.v1"><name>GODAFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, did not think was serious</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050494.v1"><name>GODAOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, did not think was serious</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050495.v1"><name>GODBCARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: general, thought would cost too much</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050496.v1"><name>GODBEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, thought would cost to much</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050497.v1"><name>GODBFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, thought would cost too much</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050498.v1"><name>GODBOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, thought would cost too much</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050499.v1"><name>GODCCARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: general, did not have time</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050500.v1"><name>GODCEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, did not have time</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050501.v1"><name>GODCFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, did not have time</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050502.v1"><name>GODCOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, did not have time other</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050503.v1"><name>GODDCARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: general, could not get appointment</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050504.v1"><name>GODDEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, could not get appointment</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050505.v1"><name>GODDFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, could not get appointment</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050506.v1"><name>GODDOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, could not get appointment</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050507.v1"><name>GODECARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: general, did not have way to doctor</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050508.v1"><name>GODEEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, did not have way to doctor</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050509.v1"><name>GODEFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, did not have way to doctor</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050510.v1"><name>GODEOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, did not have way to doctor</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050511.v1"><name>GODFCARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: genital, did not have care for children</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Genital</value></variable><variable id="phv00050512.v1"><name>GODFEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, did not have care for children</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050513.v1"><name>GODFFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, did not have care for children</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050514.v1"><name>GODFOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, did not have care for children</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050515.v1"><name>GODGCARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: general, doctor could not do much for condition</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050516.v1"><name>GODGEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, doctor could not do much for condition</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050517.v1"><name>GODGFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, doctor could not do for condition</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050518.v1"><name>GODGOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, doctor could not do for condition</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050519.v1"><name>GODHCARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: general, afraid of finding</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050520.v1"><name>GODHEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, afraid of finding</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050521.v1"><name>GODHFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, afraid of finding</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050522.v1"><name>GODHOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, afraid of finding</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050523.v1"><name>GODICARE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: general, other care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">General</value></variable><variable id="phv00050524.v1"><name>GODIEYE</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: eye care, other</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Eye care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050525.v1"><name>GODIFOOT</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: foot care, other</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Foot care</value></variable><variable id="phv00050526.v1"><name>GODIOTH</name><description>D1. Health care conditions: other, specify</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050527.v1"><name>GOD2</name><description>D2. Health care scheduling. Past year, delayed seeing doctor</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">No</value><value code="2">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00050528.v1"><name>GOD2A</name><description>D2a. Health care scheduling. Delay reason: principal reason, office hours were inconvenient</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">Could not get an appointment, office hours were inconvenient</value><value code="2">The costs of medical care were too high</value><value code="3">You did not have time to see a doctor</value><value code="4">You did not have a way to get to the doctor</value><value code="5">You thought the problem would go away</value><value code="6">You did not have anyone to care for the children</value><value code="7">Other</value></variable><variable id="phv00050529.v1"><name>GOE1</name><description>E1. Setting of usual health care. Where you most often receive medical care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">A doctor's private office</value><value code="2">A hospital outpatient diabetes clinic</value><value code="3">A hospital emergency room</value><value code="4">A health center</value><value code="5">A company clinic</value><value code="6">Other, specify</value></variable><variable id="phv00050530.v1"><name>GOE2</name><description>E2. Setting of usual health care. Who is currently giving diabetes care</description><type>byte</type><value code="1">EDIC staff</value><value code="2">Another physician at EDIC site</value><value code="3">Another physician at separate site</value></variable><variable id="phv00050531.v1"><name>FSASDATE</name><description>A4. Identifying information. Deidentified date form completed</description><type>int</type></variable><variable id="phv00050532.v1"><name>MASK_PAT</name><description>A2. Identifying information. Deidentified patient ID</description><type>int</type></variable><variable id="phv00050533.v1"><name>GOB3A1</name><description>B3a1. Health care delivery. Deidentified endocrinologist: date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050534.v1"><name>GOB3B1</name><description>B3b1. Health care delivery. Deidentified ophthalmologist (check-up) date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050535.v1"><name>GOB3C1</name><description>B3c1. Health care delivery. Deidentified ophthalmologist (other reason) most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050536.v1"><name>GOB3D1</name><description>B3d1. Health care delivery. Deidentified optometrist: date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050537.v1"><name>GOB3E1</name><description>B3e1. Health care delivery. Deidentified cardiologist: date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050538.v1"><name>GOB3F1</name><description>B3f1. Health care delivery. Deidentified podiatrist: date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050539.v1"><name>GOB3G1</name><description>B3g1. Health care delivery. Deidentified nephrologist: date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050540.v1"><name>GOB3H1</name><description>B3h1. Health care delivery. Deidentified practitioner: date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable><variable id="phv00050541.v1"><name>GOB3I1</name><description>B3i1. Health care delivery. Deidentified other doctor: date most recent visit</description><type>byte</type></variable></data_table>
