<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht003411.v2" study_id="phs000200.v10" participant_set="3" date_created="Tue May 19 12:53:52 2015"><description>Outcomes - Fracture (Form 123), data for Calcium and Vitamin D (CaD) Trial. Note: The rel# in the file name is used by the submitter to track embargo releases. Files that have "rel2" or later may either contain additional variables or more recent data as compared to the previous rel#. There will not be a "rel3" file.</description><unique_key phv="00193570" version="2">SUBJID</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193572" version="2">BKANKLE</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193573" version="2">BKCARPAL</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193574" version="2">BKCLAVICLE</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193575" version="2">BKELBOWNOS</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193576" version="2">BKHIP</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193577" version="2">BKLELBOW</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193578" version="2">BKHAND</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193579" version="2">BKPATELLA</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193580" version="2">BKPELVIS</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193581" version="2">BKLARM</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193582" version="2">BKCOCCYX</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193583" version="2">BKSCAPULA</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193584" version="2">BKUPPERLEG</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193585" version="2">BKOHUMERUS</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193586" version="2">BKFOOT</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193587" version="2">BKTIBIAFIBULA</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193588" version="2">BKTIBIAL</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193589" version="2">BKUHUMERUS</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193590" version="2">BKUELBOW</unique_key><unique_key phv="00193591" version="2">BKSPINE</unique_key><variable id="phv00193570.v2"><name>SUBJID</name><description>WHI dbGaP Subject ID</description><type>integer</type></variable><variable id="phv00193571.v2"><name>ASCSOURCE</name><description>Ascertainment Source</description><type>encoded value</type><value code="1">Local Form 123</value><value code="2">Central Form 123</value></variable><variable id="phv00193572.v2"><name>BKANKLE</name><description>Ankle Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Ankle Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Ankle Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193573.v2"><name>BKCARPAL</name><description>Carpal Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Carpal bones in wrist
		Carpal Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Carpal Fracture is not counted if pathologic. </comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193574.v2"><name>BKCLAVICLE</name><description>Clavical Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Clavical Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Clavical Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193575.v2"><name>BKELBOWNOS</name><description>Elbow NOS Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Elbow, not otherwise specified
		Elbow NOS Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Elbow NOS Fracture is not counted if pathologic. </comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193576.v2"><name>BKHIP</name><description>Hip Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>This file contains outcomes collected through Ext1.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193577.v2"><name>BKLELBOW</name><description>Lower End of Humerus Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Lower End of Humerus Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Lower End of Humerus Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193578.v2"><name>BKHAND</name><description>Metacarpal Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Metacarpal Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Metacarpal Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193579.v2"><name>BKPATELLA</name><description>Patella Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Patella Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Patella Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193580.v2"><name>BKPELVIS</name><description>Pelvis Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Pelvis Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Pelvis Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193581.v2"><name>BKLARM</name><description>Radius or Ulna Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Radius or Ulna Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Radius or Ulna Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193582.v2"><name>BKCOCCYX</name><description>Sacrum or Coccyx Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Sacrum or Coccyx Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study. It was  adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants.  Sacrum or Coccyx Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193583.v2"><name>BKSCAPULA</name><description>Scapula Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Scapula Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Scapula Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193584.v2"><name>BKUPPERLEG</name><description>Shaft of Femur Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Shaft of Femur Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study. It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Shaft of Femur Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193585.v2"><name>BKOHUMERUS</name><description>Shaft of Humerus Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Fracture of humerus, shaft or unspecified part
		Shaft of Humerus Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Shaft of Humerus Fracture is not counted if pathologic. </comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193586.v2"><name>BKFOOT</name><description>Tarsal or Metatarsal Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Tarsal or Metatarsal Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Tarsal or Metatarsal Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193587.v2"><name>BKTIBIAFIBULA</name><description>Tibia or Fibula Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Tibia or Fibula Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Tibia or Fibula Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193588.v2"><name>BKTIBIAL</name><description>Tibial Plateau Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Tibial Plateau Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Tibial Plateau Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193589.v2"><name>BKUHUMERUS</name><description>Upper End of Humerus Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Upper End of Humerus Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Upper End of Humerus Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193590.v2"><name>BKUELBOW</name><description>Upper Radius/Ulna Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Upper Radius/Ulna Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Upper Radius/Ulna Fracture is not counted if pathologic.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193591.v2"><name>BKSPINE</name><description>Vertebral Fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Defined as the first occurence of Lumbar Spine Fracture or Thoracic Spine Fracture.  Vertebral Fracture was adjudicated during the core WHI study.  It was adjudicated at all clinics for CT participants, but only adjudicated at the bone density clinics for OS participants. Does not include cervical fractures.</comment><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00193592.v2"><name>HIPFSITE</name><description>Fracture site (hip)</description><type>encoded value</type><value code="1">Neck of femur</value><value code="2">Intertrochanteric fracture</value><value code="3">Greater trochanter</value><value code="4">Unspecified part of proximal femur</value></variable><variable id="phv00193593.v2"><name>HIPFSIDE</name><description>Side of hip fracture</description><type>encoded value</type><value code="1">Right</value><value code="2">Left</value><value code="3">Both sides</value><value code="9">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00193594.v2"><name>HIPFBASE</name><description>Hip Fracture Based On</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Not collected on early versions of F123. Value 5 was not collected after WHI closeout.</comment><value code="1">Radiology &amp; discharge summary dx new hip fracture</value><value code="2">Radiology dx of hip fx, but not on discharge summary</value><value code="3">Discharge, equiv. xray, unequiv. scan/MRI dx hip fx</value><value code="4">Hip fracture dx in discharge summary, but no radiology rprt</value><value code="5">Uncertain radiology report of hip fracture without add. doc</value></variable><variable id="phv00193595.v2"><name>HIPFPATH</name><description>Pathologic fracture (of hip)</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Pathologic hip fracture: (Fracture resulting from bone tumors or cysts, Paget's disease, bone or joint prostheses, or surgical manipulation.Osteoporotic fracture is not considered a pathologic fracture.)</comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value><value code="2">Possible</value></variable><variable id="phv00193596.v2"><name>FRACSIDE</name><description>F123 Side of fracture (non hip)</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Not collected after WHI closeout.</comment><value code="1">Right</value><value code="2">Left</value><value code="3">Both sides</value><value code="4">Not applicable (e.g. tailbone)</value><value code="9">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00193597.v2"><name>FRACCONF</name><description>F123 Fracture confirmed as (non hip)</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Not collected after WHI closeout.</comment><value code="1">Non vertebal: Radiology report new fracture</value><value code="2">Non vertebal: Radiology report healing fracture</value><value code="3">Non vertebal: Non radiology report new/healing fracture</value><value code="4">Non vertebal: Init. rad.report equiv., subs report dx fract.</value><value code="5">Vertebal: Radiology report based on AP/lateral thoracolumbar</value><value code="6">Vertebal: Radiology rprt not based AP/lateral thoracolumbar</value></variable><variable id="phv00193598.v2"><name>FRACPATH</name><description>F123 Pathologic fracture (non hip)</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>Pathologic fracture other than hip: (Fracture resulting from bone tumors or cysts, Paget's disease, bone and joint prostheses, or surgical manipulation. Osteoporotic fracture is not considered a pathologic fracture.)
		Not collected after WHI closeout.  Non vertebral fractures are not counted if they are pathologic. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value><value code="2">Possible</value></variable></data_table>
