<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht005173.v1" study_id="phs000007.v27" participant_set="10" date_created="Tue Jan 12 16:27:02 2016"><description>Medications Reported at Clinic Exam, Original Cohort Exams 29, 30 and 31. Medications were reported by study participants, coded with WHO ATC medication codes.</description><unique_key phv="00257912" version="1">shareid</unique_key><unique_key phv="00257914" version="1">exam</unique_key><unique_key phv="00257915" version="1">medname</unique_key><unique_key phv="00257916" version="1">medstren</unique_key><unique_key phv="00257918" version="1">mednum</unique_key><unique_key phv="00257919" version="1">medper</unique_key><unique_key phv="00257920" version="1">medprn</unique_key><variable id="phv00257912.v1"><name>shareid</name><description>Unique study participant identification number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00257913.v1"><name>idtype</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier (counts are observations, not participants)</description><type/><comment>1. IDTYPE and ID taken together form a unique study participant identification number. However, for this dataset a unique observation identifier includes more variables. Please see note #1 on the first page.</comment><value code="0">Original Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00257914.v1"><name>exam</name><description>Exam number (counts are observations, not participants)</description><type/><value code="29">Original Cohort Exam 29</value><value code="30">Original Cohort Exam 30</value><value code="31">Original Cohort Exam 31</value></variable><variable id="phv00257915.v1"><name>medname</name><description>Medication name (character variable)</description><type/><comment>1. "NO MEDS LISTED" = there were no medications listed on the form. However, it may not necessarily imply that the participant is not taking any medications.
		2. The same drug may be recorded in more than one record for an individual participant.  This is because the participant took the medication at more than one strength and/or dose. 
		3. The text written on the form was preserved "as is". There could be some misspellings, etc. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00257916.v1"><name>medstren</name><description>Medication strength (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = Unknown</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257917.v1"><name>route</name><description>Medication route</description><type/><comment>1. This variable was not present at the time of Exam 29.</comment><value code="1">Oral</value><value code="2">Topical</value><value code="3">Injection</value><value code="4">Inhaled</value><value code="5">Drops</value><value code="6">Other</value><value code="8">Variable not present at the time of exam 29</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00257918.v1"><name>mednum</name><description>Number taken for given period (MEDPER)</description><type/><comment>1. This variable should be used in conjunction with MEDPER.</comment><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00257919.v1"><name>medper</name><description>Period range</description><type/><comment>1. This variable should be used in conjunction with MEDNUM. 2. Value of '4=Year' was not available as an option for Exam 29.</comment><value code="1">Day</value><value code="2">Week</value><value code="3">Month</value><value code="4">Year</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00257920.v1"><name>medprn</name><description>Medication taken as needed</description><type/><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00257921.v1"><name>medbag</name><description>Medication bag with medications brought to exam or med bottles/pack used by examiner to complete form?</description><type/><comment>1. If MEDNAME = "NO MEDS LISTED" then MEDBAG set to 0=NO. 2. MEDBAG =0 means that participants did not bring medications to the exam. Medications can still be reported by the participant. 3. This variable was not present at the time of Exam 29.</comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value><value code="8">Variable not present at the time of exam 29</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00257922.v1"><name>atc_cod1</name><description>ATC code for medication or first drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>1. This dataset includes ALL participants who attended Exams 29, 30 and 31. If participant did not list any medications, MEDNAME was set to "NO MEDS LISTED" and ATC_COD1 set to "NO_MEDS". 2. Some medications were coded as "NO_CODE", which means that either there is no code for it (for example supplements, herbal preparations, homeopathic remedies, etc.) or  the medication's name did not have enough information for coding.
		ATC_COD1 modified - medications classified for the treatment of addiction, HIV infection and psychosis have been removed to preserve confidentiality. </comment><value code="NO_CODE">Medication not coded</value><value code="NO_MEDS">No medications listed</value></variable><variable id="phv00257923.v1"><name>atc_cod2</name><description>ATC code for second drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>ATC_COD2 modified - medications classified for the treatment of addiction, HIV infection and psychosis have been removed to preserve confidentiality.
		Blank = No meds, not coded or single drug. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00257924.v1"><name>atc_cod3</name><description>ATC code for third drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>ATC_COD3 modified - medications classified for the treatment of addiction, HIV infection and psychosis have been removed to preserve confidentiality.
		Blank = No meds, not coded or no third compound. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00257925.v1"><name>atc_cod4</name><description>ATC code for fourth drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>ATC_COD4 modified - medications classified for the treatment of addiction, HIV infection and psychosis have been removed to preserve confidentiality.
		Blank = No meds, not coded or no fourth compound. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00257926.v1"><name>system1</name><description>Description/label for anatomical main group - medication or first drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds or not coded</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257927.v1"><name>system2</name><description>Description/label for anatomical main group - second drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>Blank = No meds, not coded or single drug</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257928.v1"><name>system3</name><description>Description/label for anatomical main group - third drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>Blank = No meds, not coded or no third compound</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257929.v1"><name>system4</name><description>Description/label for anatomical main group - forth drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>Blank = No meds, not coded or no fourth compound</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257930.v1"><name>ther_gp1</name><description>Description/label for therapeutic subgroup - medication or first drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or first drug does not have therapeutic subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257931.v1"><name>ther_gp2</name><description>Description/label for therapeutic subgroup - second drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or second drug does not have therapeutic subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257932.v1"><name>ther_gp3</name><description>Description/label for therapeutic subgroup - third drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or third drug does not have therapeutic subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257933.v1"><name>ther_gp4</name><description>Description/label for therapeutic subgroup - forth drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or fourth drug does not have therapeutic subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257934.v1"><name>phrm_gp1</name><description>Description/label for pharmacological subgroup - medication or first drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or first drug does not have pharmacological subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257935.v1"><name>phrm_gp2</name><description>Description/label for pharmacological subgroup - second drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or second drug does not have pharmacological subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257936.v1"><name>phrm_gp3</name><description>Description/label for pharmacological subgroup - third drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or third drug does not have pharmacological subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257937.v1"><name>phrm_gp4</name><description>Description/label for pharmacological subgroup - forth drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or fourth drug does not have pharmacological subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257938.v1"><name>chem_gp1</name><description>Description/label for chemical subgroup - medication or first drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or first drug does not have chemical subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257939.v1"><name>chem_gp2</name><description>Description/label for chemical subgroup - second drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or second drug does not have chemical subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257940.v1"><name>chem_gp3</name><description>Description/label for chemical subgroup - third drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or third drug does not have chemical subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257941.v1"><name>chem_gp4</name><description>Description/label for chemical subgroup - forth drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or fourth drug does not have chemical subgroup specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257942.v1"><name>chem_nm1</name><description>Description/label for chemical substance - medication or first drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or first drug does not have chemical substance specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257943.v1"><name>chem_nm2</name><description>Description/label for chemical substance - second drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or second drug does not have chemical substance specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257944.v1"><name>chem_nm3</name><description>Description/label for chemical substance - third drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or third drug does not have chemical substance specified</comment></variable><variable id="phv00257945.v1"><name>chem_nm4</name><description>Description/label for chemical substance - forth drug in compound (character variable)</description><type/><comment>blank = No meds, not coded or fourth drug does not have chemical substance specified</comment></variable></data_table>
