<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht004118.v1" study_id="phs000280.v3" participant_set="1" date_created="Wed Dec 17 10:53:44 2014"><description>Cohort Surveillance Incident Atrial Fibrillation. Participants with or without atherosclerosis and cardiovascular disease and involved in the "Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) Cohort" project.</description><variable id="phv00207561.v1"><name>AFECGV1</name><description>Prevalent atrial fibrillation at visit 1</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>AFECGV1 is a numeric variable determined by ECG readings from ARIC cohort visit 1. If a Minnesota code of 831 or 832 is indicated at visit 1 then AFECGV1=1, otherwise AFECGV1=0.
		Purpose: to determine if a person had prevalent atrial fibrillation at visit 1. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00207562.v1"><name>LEADRJT</name><description>Unreadable ECG At Exam 1 [0=No, 1=Complete, 2=Partial, Missing]</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>In data set ECGRAW there are 12 variables, ECGRA034-ECGRA045 that correspond to 'lead reject' in each of the ECG leads, and take the value 'T' or 'F' depending on whether the lead was rejected ('T' if lead rejected, 'F' otherwise). Those with 'T' in all 12 leads were classified as LEADRJT=1, meaning their ECG was unreadable in all leads. Those with at least one 'T' in one of the 12 leads, but at least one 'F' were classified as LEADRJT=2, meaning some leads were unreadable, but others could be evaluated. Finally, those with 'F' in all leads were classified as LEADRJT=0.
		Purpose: to determine whether an unreadable ECG was obtained at cohort visit 1. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Complete</value><value code="2">Partial</value></variable><variable id="phv00207563.v1"><name>AFDTHBY05</name><description>Fatal atrial fibrillation event by 31DECYY as indicated by death certificate</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>AFDTHBYYY is a numeric variable determined by the underlying cause of death from a death certificate. If an ICD-9 code of 427.31 or 427.32 or an ICD-10 code of I48 is indicated as the underlying cause of death prior to 31DECYY then AFDTHBYYY=1, otherwise AFDTHBYYY=0.
		Purpose: to determine if a person has had an incident atrial fibrillation event at visit 2, 3, or 4. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00207564.v1"><name>AFECGBY05</name><description>Incident atrial fibrillation event at visit 2, 3, or 4</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>AFECGBYYY is a numeric variable determined by ECG readings from ARIC cohort visits 2, 3, and 4. If a Minnesota code of 831 or 832 is indicated at visits 2, 3, or 4 then AFECGBYYY=1, otherwise AFECGBYYY=0.
		Purpose: to determine if a person has had an fatal atrial fibrillation event by 31DECYY as indicated by death certificate. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00207565.v1"><name>FT05AFECG</name><description>Follow-up time (in days) for an incident atrial fibrillation event at visit 2, 3, or 4</description><type>string</type><comment>FTYYAFECG is the follow-up time for AFECGBYYY. FTYYAFECG is calculated as EDYYAFECG - V1DATE01.
		Purpose: to determine the follow-up time (in days) for an incident atrial fibrillation event at visit 2, 3, or 4. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00207566.v1"><name>AFHOSP1BY05</name><description>Incident atrial fibrillation event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL)</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>AFHOSP1BYYY is a numeric variable determined by ICD-9 discharge codes entered in question 10 of the CEL. If a discharge code of 427.31 is present and procedure codes of 35.X or 36.X are not present then AFHOSP1BYYY=1, otherwise AFHOSP1BYYY=0.
		Purpose: to determine if a person has had an incident atrial fibrillation event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL) </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00207567.v1"><name>FT05AFHOSP1</name><description>Follow-up time for AFHOSP1by05</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00207568.v1"><name>AFINCBY05</name><description>Incident atrial fibrillation event as determined by any source by 31DECYY.</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>AFINCBYYY is a numeric variable determined by either ECG readings from cohort visits, ICD-9 discharge codes from the CEL, or the underlying cause of death from the death certificate. If AFECGBYYY, or AFHOSP1BYYY, or AFDTHBYYY =1 then AFINCBYYY=1. Otherwise, AFINCBYYY=0.
		Purpose: to determine if a person has had an incident atrial fibrillation event as determined by any source by 31DECYY. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00207569.v1"><name>FT05AFINC</name><description>Follow-up time (in days) for an incident atrial fibrillation event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL)</description><type>string</type><comment>FTYYAFINC is the follow-up time for AFINCBYYY. FTYYAFINC is calculated as EDYYAFINC - V1DATE01.
		Purpose: to determine the follow-up time (in days) for an incident atrial fibrillation event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL) </comment></variable><variable id="phv00207570.v1"><name>AFLINCBY05</name><description>Incident atrial flutter event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL) or at cohort visits 2, 3, or 4</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>AFLINCBYYY is a numeric variable determined by ICD-9 discharge codes entered in question 10 of the CEL or Minnesota codes from ECG readings at cohort visits 2, 3, or 4. If a discharge code of 427.32 is present and procedure codes of 35.X or 36.X are not present then AFLINCBYYY =1, OR if a Minnesota code of 832 is indicated at visit 2, 3, or 4 then AFLINCBYYY =1.  otherwise, AFLINCBYYY =0.
		Purpose: to determine if a person has had an incident atrial flutter event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL) or at cohort visits 2, 3, or 4. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00207571.v1"><name>FT05AFLINC</name><description>Follow-up time for an incident atrial flutter event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL) or at cohort visits 2, 3, or 4</description><type>string</type><comment>FTYYAFLINC is the follow-up time for AFLINCBYYY. FTYYAFLINC is calculated as EDYYAFLINC - V1DATE01.
		Purpose: to determine the follow-up time for an incident atrial flutter event as determined by hospital discharge codes on the cohort eligibility form (CEL) or at cohort visits 2, 3, or 4. </comment></variable><variable id="phv00207572.v1"><name>MISSECGFLAG</name><description>Missing An ECG Reading Before End Date/Censoring Date</description><type>encoded value</type><comment>MISSECGFLAG defines missing ECG at a visit as anyone who is not in the ATRFIB data set for a particular visit (i.e. if an ID is missing from ATRFIB21 then that person is missing and ECG for visit 2). We then imputed the date of MISSECG as visit 1 date + 3 years (*365.25) if missing visit 2 ECG, visit 1 + 6 years (*365.25) if missing visit 3 ECG, and visit 1 date + 9 years (*365.25) if missing visit 4 ECG (name date variable MISSECGDT. If date of MISSECGDT is less than ED05ECG than ECGFLAG=1, else ECGFLAG=0. If there is more than one MISSECGDT than we used the earliest date to determine ECGFLAG.
		Purpose: to determine a person who is missing at least one ECG reading at cohort visits 2, 3, or 4. </comment><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00207573.v1"><name>GWAS_ID</name><description>ARIC subject ID</description><type/></variable></data_table>
