<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?>
<data_table id="pht000178.v1" study_id="phs000089.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Tue Aug 12 13:57:00 2008">

<variable id="phv00024004.v1">
	<name>Age</name>
	<description>Age, at sampling, of the subject</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<unit>Years</unit>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024002.v1">
	<name>Catalog_ID</name>
	<description>Subject ID number assigned by NINDS Repository</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024009.v1">
	<name>Clinical_Data_Source</name>
	<description>The source of the clinical data</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024010.v1">
	<name>Clinician_Type</name>
	<description>Type of clinician that collected the clinical data</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024011.v1">
	<name>Country_Origin</name>
	<description>Subject&#39;s country of birth</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024007.v1">
	<name>Ethnicity</name>
	<description>Ethnic category (as reported by subject) - check one:  Hispanic or Latino, Not Hispanic or Latino</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024013.v1">
	<name>Family History Family history of parkinsonism</name>
	<description>The subject does or does not endorse a family history of Parkinsonism on clinician&#39;s interview</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024005.v1">
	<name>Gender</name>
	<description>Gender of the subject</description>
	<type>string</type>
	<value code="F">Female</value>
	<value code="M">Male</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024003.v1">
	<name>In_Panel</name>
	<description>Indicates whether DNA from this subject is included in any panels available through the NINDS Repository catalog</description>
	<type>string</type>
	<value code="N">No</value>
	<value code="Y">Yes</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024014.v1">
	<name>Longitudinal Data Is this data Longitudinal (Follow-Up) Data?</name>
	<description>Is the data longitudinal or an initial assessment</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024008.v1">
	<name>Onset_Age</name>
	<description>The age at which the subject themselves first noted symptoms of Parkinsonism, based on clinician&#39;s interview</description>
	<type>string</type>
	<unit>Years</unit>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024015.v1">
	<name>Optional data Handedness</name>
	<description>The hand preference of the subject; the subject&#39;s dominant hand</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024016.v1">
	<name>Optional data Hoehn and Yahr</name>
	<description>The score on the Hoehn and Yahr scale</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024017.v1">
	<name>Optional data Mini-mental status score</name>
	<description>The score on the Folstein Mini-Mental Status Score</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024018.v1">
	<name>Optional data UPDRS total motor score</name>
	<description>The score on the Unified Parkinson&#39;s Disease Rating Scale</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024006.v1">
	<name>Race</name>
	<description>Race of the subject</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024019.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis axial rigidity</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates if rigidity exists axially on physical examination.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024020.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis cerebellar signs (other than activation tremor)</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has signs of cerebellar dysfunction, other than activation tremor on physical examination</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024021.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis dysautonomia</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has dysautonomia, including orthostatic hypotension.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024022.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis fluctuations</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has fluctuations in severity of Parkinsonism.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024023.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis gaze palsy</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has a supranuclear gaze palsy on physical examination.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024024.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis hallucinations</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has hallucinations either independent of or related to treatment for Parkinsonism.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024025.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis history of encephalitis</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates if the subject has a history of encephalitis (infection of the brain tissue, requiring hospitalization).</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024026.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis history of head injury with loss of consciousness</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates if the subject has a history of head injury (including due to boxing) leading to loss of conciousness lasting more than 4 minutes, or more than 3 times over the lifetime; present indicates that this has occurred, absent indicates</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024027.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis history of strokes or stepwise deterioration</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates if the subject has a history of stroke causing a stepwise course in progression of Parkinsonism; i.e., does the subject have vascular Parkinsonism.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024028.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis memory loss</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has history of memory loss.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024029.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis neuroleptic treatment at time of symptom onset</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject was treated with neuroleptics or related anti-emetics which cause Parkinsonism at the time of the onset of parkinsonian symptoms.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024030.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis Oculogyric crisis</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates if the subject has a history of oculogyric crisis spontaneously or secondary (for example due to illness such as encephalitis or medication induced phenomenae).</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024031.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis Other</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates, via comments, if they see other features suggestive of a diagnosis other than Parkinson&#39;s disease which is not delineated by the choices given.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024032.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of another diagnosis sustained remission</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has had a history of sustained remission of the Parkinsonism during longitudinal physical examination</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024033.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Activation tremor</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not activation tremor is present on examination of the subject.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024034.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Asymmetric onset</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates if the onset of Parkinsonism was asymmetric (started on one side, and/or was worse on one side than the other).  If so, then present is checked; if not, then absent is indicated.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024035.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Bradykinesis</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not bradykinesis is present , or if &quot;on&quot; from medication at time of evaluation, whether this has ever been observed as a part of the subject&#39;s clinical syndrome</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024036.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Gait difficulties</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not gait difficulties are present on examination of the subject.  If the subject cannot stand, then the clinician indicates whether this has ever been observed as part of the subject&#39;s clinical syndrome.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024037.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Postural Instability</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not postural instability is present on examination of the subject, on pull test.  If the subject cannot stand, then the clinician indicates whether this has ever been observed as part of the subject&#39;s clinical syndrome.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024038.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Response to Anti-Parkinsonism Therapy</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not the subject has had at least a 70% improvement in motor symptoms on dopaminergic therapy, including l-dopa, dopamine agonists, COMT and dopamine reuptake inhibitors or enhancers.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024039.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Resting Tremor</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not 4-6 Hz resting tremor is present on examination of the subject, or if &quot;on&quot; from medication at time of evaluation, whether this has ever been observed as a part of the subject&#39;s clinical syndrome.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024040.v1">
	<name>Signs suggestive of PD diagnosis Rigidity</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates whether or not rigidity is present on examination of the subject, or if &quot;on&quot; from medication at time of evaluation, whether this has ever been observed as a part of the subject&#39;s clinical syndrome.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024041.v1">
	<name>Smoking History smoking history</name>
	<description>A record of an individual&#39;s background in regard to smoking tobacco. This would include such factors as start date, end date (if applicable), number of cigarette smoked, attempts to quit, and others.</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024042.v1">
	<name>Smoking History years smoking</name>
	<description>How many years did the person smoke, if the person is a current or former smoker?</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<unit>Years</unit>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024044.v1">
	<name>Specific diagnosis Parkinsonism clinical diagnosis</name>
	<description>The clinician indicates which kind of Parkinsonism the subject has by choosing one of the offered diagnoses or writing in if best diagnosis not offered</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00024012.v1">
	<name>Zip_Abbrev</name>
	<description>First 3 digits of subject&#39;s zip code</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

</data_table>
