<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002236.v4" study_id="phs000007.v27" participant_set="10" date_created="Tue Jan 12 16:23:48 2016"><description>Foot Study, Original Cohort Exams 27 and 28 and Offspring Exam 8. The Framingham Foot Study, an ancillary study of the FHS, is an observational cohort study of adults to examine the role of foot disorders upon functional limitations and disability. Hallux valgus was measured as part of the Foot Assessment Clinical Tool, which is a validated foot exam with specific criteria to assess foot pain, foot symptoms and presence of foot disorders. Trained clinical examiners performed all foot exams. Hallux valgus was considered to be present if the angle of the hallux towards the lesser toes was observed to be greater than 15 degrees. Pes cavus was defined using a weight-bearing ratio of arch width to rear-foot width from a bipedal stance on a computerized pressure mat. We defined pes cavus for a person as having a ratio of arch width to rear-foot width of 0, on either foot, identified by the ratio of the arch of the foot.</description><variable id="phv00159553.v3"><name>shareid</name><description>Framingham Heart Study participant SHARe ID number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00159554.v3"><name>idtype</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type/><value code="0">Original Cohort</value><value code="1">Offspring Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00159556.v3"><name>exam</name><description>Closest Framingham exam cycle</description><type/><comment>The EXAM variable was assigned by comparing the foot study call back exam date (EXDATE) and the Framingham Heart Study exam date (data not in this dataset).  The EXAM variable is the FHS exam cycle that is the closest, by date, to the foot study call back exam date.</comment><value code="ex27">Original Cohort exam 27</value><value code="ex28">Original Cohort exam 28</value><value code="ex8">Offspring cohort exam 8</value></variable><variable id="phv00159558.v3"><name>exdate</name><description>Date of foot study call back exam</description><type/><unit>days</unit><logical_min>10002</logical_min><logical_max>20566</logical_max><comment>number of days since exam 1</comment></variable><variable id="phv00226990.v1"><name>FOOTPAIN</name><description>Presence of foot pain (on most days of the month, from foot study questionnaire)</description><type/><value code="0">No foot pain</value><value code="1">Yes foot pain</value></variable><variable id="phv00226991.v1"><name>HEELATRO</name><description>Presence of heel fat-pad atrophy</description><type/><comment>Data are missing when a participant attended the exam but did not obtain the foot exam by the foot study clinician for this data item.</comment><value code="0">No heel fat-pad atrophy</value><value code="1">Yes heel fat-pad atrophy</value><value code=".">unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00226992.v1"><name>FOREATRO</name><description>Presence of forefoot fat-pad atrophy</description><type/><comment>Data are missing when a participant attended the exam but did not obtain the foot exam by the foot study clinician for this data item.</comment><value code="0">No forefoot fat-pad atrophy</value><value code="1">Yes forefoot fat-pad atrophy</value><value code=".">unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00226993.v1"><name>lesstoe</name><description>Presence of lesser toe deformities</description><type/><comment>Data are missing when a participant attended the exam but did not obtain the foot exam by the foot study clinician for this data item.</comment><value code="0">No lesser toe deformities</value><value code="1">Yes lesser toe deformities</value><value code=".">unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00226994.v1"><name>pesplan</name><description>Presence of pes planus</description><type/><comment>Data are missing when a participant attended the exam but did not obtain the foot pressure scans (TekScan MatScan obtained on the right and left foot).  This data was not obtained because either the participant did not receive the foot pressure scan (63), or were seen on days when the foot pressure scan device was not working (49), or the data was poor quality (15).</comment><value code="0">No pes planus</value><value code="1">Yes pes planus</value><value code=".">unknown</value></variable></data_table>
