<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht000309.v9" study_id="phs000007.v25" participant_set="9" date_created="Fri Dec 12 15:51:20 2014"><description>Sequence of Cardiovascular Events (SOE) Endpoints (includes death), Original, Offspring, NOS, and Generation 3 Cohort reviewed through 12/2013. There is a more detailed coding manual at the bottom of the SOE protocol for this dataset. Each event is a separate record in this file. If a unique study participant has two or more events with the same date value, the order of events in the dataset does not necessarily reflect the natural order of events. This dataset is generated annually. Included are events reviewed on or before 12/2013. Events reviewed after 12/2013 will appear in the next annual update. Events can take up to two years to be reviewed after they become known. This file does not represent follow up through 12/2013. The corresponding survival file contains follow up information and lags one year behind.</description><unique_key phv="00036472" version="8">shareid</unique_key><unique_key phv="00036469" version="8">EVENT</unique_key><unique_key phv="00172155" version="3">pagenum</unique_key><unique_key phv="00172154" version="3">linenum</unique_key><unique_key phv="00036471" version="8">DATE</unique_key><variable id="phv00036472.v8"><name>shareid</name><description>Unique study participant identification number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00036469.v8"><name>EVENT</name><description>Event Number</description><type/><comment>For EVENT = 1 - 5. MI: Recognized means at time of MI occurrence, an MI was known to have taken place. Unrecognized means MI was not known to have taken place until later. Silent MI means at time of MI, there were no symptoms similar to MI symptoms. Not silent means that symptoms were present. Unrecognized MI's are dated using the midpoint between the dates of the diagnostic ECG's. Hierarchy for coding MI is based on strongest evidence: EVENT=01 &gt; EVENT=02 &gt; EVENT=03.
		For EVENT = 6. AP, First episode only:  If date of was unavailable, AP is dated as midpoint of the interval between medical encounters (FHS exams, hospitalizations or MD office visits). If AP occurred with MI or CI, then use same date as MI or CI. Before 1987, if AP occurred just before MI or CI, then AP date was assigned 3 months before MI or CI. If AP occurred just after MI or CI, then AP date was assigned 3 months after MI or CI. Beginning in 1987, if approximate or exact date of new angina was available, then that date was assigned as date of AP. 
		For EVENT = 8. Questionable MI at exam 1:  Date same date as Exam 1 for Original cohort and Offspring cohort. For the other cohort groups, a date other than the Exam 1 date is used if available. Any questionable MI episode at Exam 1, including definite history only without enzymes or ECG. Does not include questionable AP. 
		For EVENT = 9. Acute MI on autopsy, not a new event: This is coded when there has been a previously coded MI (1 or 2) and that MI shows on autopsy. 
		For EVENT = 19. Questionable CVA at exam 1: Date of Exam 1 (unless date available) 
		For EVENT = 39. Questionable IC at exam 1: Use Exam 1 date for Original cohort and Offspring cohort. For the other cohorts, a date other than the Exam 1 date is used if available. 
		For EVENT = 40. Not hospitalized, diagnosed on basis  of on exam or MD notes: If CHF found on FHS exam, use FHS exam date. 
		For EVENT = 49. Questionable CHF at exam 1: Use Exam 1 date for Original cohort and Offspring cohort. For the other cohorts, a date other than the Exam 1 date is used if available. </comment><value code="1">MI recognized, with diagnostic ECG</value><value code="2">MI recognized, without diagnostic ECG, with enzymes and history</value><value code="3">MI recognized, without diagnostic ECG, with autopsy evidence, new event (see also code 9)</value><value code="4">MI unrecognized, silent</value><value code="5">MI unrecognized, not silent</value><value code="6">AP, first episode only</value><value code="7">CI, definite by both history and ECG</value><value code="8">Questionable MI at exam 1</value><value code="9">Acute MI by autopsy, previously coded as 1 or 2</value><value code="10">Definite CVA at exam 1, but questionable type</value><value code="11">ABI (Atherothrombotic Infarction of brain)</value><value code="12">TIA (Transient Ischemic Attack) only the 1st TIA is coded</value><value code="13">Cerebral embolism</value><value code="14">Intracerebral hemorrhage</value><value code="15">Subarachnoid hemorrhage</value><value code="16">Other CVA</value><value code="17">CVA, definite CVA, type unknown</value><value code="19">Questionable CVA at exam 1</value><value code="21">Death, CHD sudden, within 1 hour</value><value code="22">Death, CHD, 1-23 hours, non sudden</value><value code="23">Death, CHD, 24-47 hours, non sudden</value><value code="24">Death, CHD, 48 hours or more, non sudden</value><value code="25">Death, CVA</value><value code="26">Death, other CVD</value><value code="27">Death, Cancer</value><value code="28">Death, other causes</value><value code="29">Death, cause unknown</value><value code="30">IC, first episode only</value><value code="39">IC, questionable IC at exam 1</value><value code="40">CHF, not hospitalized, diagnosed on basis of on exam or MD notes</value><value code="41">CHF, hospitalized</value><value code="49">CHF, questionable CHF at exam 1</value></variable><variable id="phv00036470.v8"><name>IDTYPE</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type/><value code="0">Original Cohort (Generation 1)</value><value code="1">Offspring Cohort (Generation 2)</value><value code="2">New Offspring Spouse Cohort (Generation 2)</value><value code="3">Generation 3 Cohort (Generation 3)</value><value code="7">Omni 1 Cohort</value><value code="72">Omni 2 Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00172155.v3"><name>pagenum</name><description>Page number of SOE log book</description><type/><logical_min>3</logical_min><logical_max>175</logical_max><comment>Used for administrative purposes. Can be used to separate multiple events per date.</comment><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00172154.v3"><name>linenum</name><description>Line number of page in SOE log book</description><type/><logical_min>1</logical_min><logical_max>25</logical_max><comment>Used for administrative purposes. Can be used to separate multiple events per date.</comment><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00036471.v8"><name>DATE</name><description>Date of Event</description><type/><unit>Number of days since Exam 1</unit><logical_min>-8824</logical_min><logical_max>23461</logical_max></variable></data_table>
