<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002998.v2" study_id="phs000145.v4" participant_set="2" date_created="Tue Apr 16 13:58:15 2013"><variable id="phv00173962.v2"><name>SUBJID</name><description>POPRES Subject ID</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00173963.v2"><name>EUROPEAN_LABEL</name><description>The geographic label for a sampled individual was based upon the self-reported labels attributed to 1) the four grandparents, 2) two grandparents and one parent, 3) the two parents, or 4) the individual, based upon data availability. Conflicting labels of ancestors resulted in an attribution to a higher level label.  Europe was divided the four regions UN Northern, UN Western, UN Southern and UN Eastern Europe as defined in the UN geo-scheme for Europe.  Those 4 groups were then further subdivided based on sampling of 500 individuals as follows:  UN Northern into North-Western Europe (Great Britain &amp; Ireland) and Northern Europe which includes all other UN Northern countries but Finland.  UN Western Europe was split into Western Europe (Belgium, France, Luxembourg, and the Netherlands) and Central Europe(Austria, Germany, and Switzerland). Finally, UN Southern Europe was split into South-WesternEurope (Spain, Portugal, and Andorra) and South-Eastern Europe (all others).</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00173964.v2"><name>WORLD_LABEL</name><description>Labels defined as follows:  African American: self identified as African ancestry from Jamaica or Grenada, European: self identified as European ancestry from UN Northern, UN Western, UN Southern, UN Eastern or a mixture of these  4 groups, Hispanic: self identified Hispanic from Colombia, Guyana, or  Uruguay, Southern Asia: self identified as origin from Afghanistan, India, Nepal, Pakistan or Sri Lanka, Western Asia: self identified as origin from Iraq, Jordan, Qatar, Turkey or Yemen and Other: Ancestry missing, incomplete or with small numbers from regions other than those specified</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00190413.v1"><name>ORIGIN_LABEL</name><description>Based on this information, we first attributed a best-guess geographic label to each of the family members based on the following rules: 1) missing data was ignored; 2) if ethnicity conflicted with birthplace or first language data, only ethnicity was considered; 3) if birthplace and first language disagreed, a higher level container label was chosen (e.g. an individual who was born in France but reported his first language to be Norwegian was labeled European); and 4) white individuals born in the US or Canada were attributed according to the first language information alone, if other than English.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00190414.v1"><name>COUNTRY_SELF</name><description>Indicates the country where the subject was born.</description><type/></variable></data_table>
