<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002391.v1" study_id="phs000297.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Fri Jul 27 13:48:23 2012"><variable id="phv00163146.v1"><name>SUBJID</name><description>Subject ID</description><type>integer</type></variable><variable id="phv00163147.v1"><name>CONSENT</name><description>Consent group as determined by DAC.</description><type>integer, encoded value</type><comment>For category 1, Health research: studies to learn about, prevent or treat health problems. For category 3, Limited to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process.  For example, studies of conditions like cataract, diabetes, and psoriasis might be appropriate, while conditions like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and neuroblastoma might not be appropriate.  Studies of conditions that are common in both children and the elderly, such as schizophrenia or depression, would not be appropriate if they focused on children and young adults.  Studies focused primarily on pediatric populations are not permitted.</comment><value code="1">Health Research - Group Health Seattle: These data will be used only for health related research, including research to improve methods for health related research.</value><value code="2">Dementia or Aging - Group Health Seattle: Limited to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. For example, studies of conditions like cataract, diabetes, and psoriasis might be appropriate, while conditions like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and neuroblastoma might not be appropriate. Studies of conditions that are common in both children and the elderly, such as schizophrenia or depression, would not be appropriate if they focused on children or young adults. Studies focused primarily on pediatric populations are not permitted.</value><value code="3">Health Research - Marshfield Clinic:May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.  No Permitted Use: Insurance companies.</value><value code="4">Health Research - Vanderbilt U: May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.</value><value code="5">Health Research - Mayo Clinic: Mayo Clinic Data may only be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.  Investigators must state in the Data Use Request their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from his or her study with the scientific community.</value><value code="6">Health Research - Northwestern U: May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.  No Permitted Use: Insurance companies.</value></variable><variable id="phv00163148.v1"><name>SUBJ_SOURCE</name><description>Source repository where subjects originate.</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00163149.v1"><name>SOURCE_SUBJID</name><description>Subject ID used in the Source Repository.</description><type>integer</type></variable><variable id="phv00163150.v1"><name>AFFECTION_STATUS</name><description>Affection Status</description><type>integer, encoded value</type><value code="1">Case type 1</value><value code="2">Case type 2</value><value code="3">Control type 1</value><value code="4">Control type 2</value></variable></data_table>
