<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?>
<data_table id="pht001196.v1" study_id="phs000218.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Tue Mar 30 11:20:45 2010">

<variable id="phv00089664.v1">
	<name>TARGETID</name>
	<description>Official non-identifying TARGET ID</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089665.v1">
	<name>AGE</name>
	<description>Age at diagnosis</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<unit>days</unit>
	<logical_min>5</logical_min>
	<logical_max>7446</logical_max>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089666.v1">
	<name>GENDER</name>
	<description>Gender</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>2</logical_max>
	<value code="1">Male</value>
	<value code="2">Female</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown,missing</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089667.v1">
	<name>NAACCR_ETHNICITY</name>
	<description>NAACCR Ethnicity</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="0">Non-Spanish, non-Hispanic</value>
	<value code="1">Mexican (incl Chicano)</value>
	<value code="2">Puerto Rican</value>
	<value code="3">Cuban</value>
	<value code="4">South or Central American (except Brazil)</value>
	<value code="5">Other specified Spanish/Hispanic origin (inlcudes European)</value>
	<value code="6">Spanish NOS, Hispanic NOS, Latino NOS (based on more than just surname)</value>
	<value code="7">Spanish surname only-no contrary evidence that the patient is not Hispanic</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown whether Spanish only</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089668.v1">
	<name>NAACCR_RACE</name>
	<description>NAACCR Race</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>99</logical_max>
	<value code="1">White</value>
	<value code="2">Black</value>
	<value code="3">American Indian, Aleutian, Eskimo</value>
	<value code="4">Chinese</value>
	<value code="5">Japanese</value>
	<value code="6">Filipino</value>
	<value code="7">Hawaiian</value>
	<value code="8">Korean</value>
	<value code="9">Asian Indian, Pakistani</value>
	<value code="10">Vietnamese</value>
	<value code="11">Laotian</value>
	<value code="12">Hmong</value>
	<value code="13">Kampuchean</value>
	<value code="14">Thai</value>
	<value code="20">Micronesian NOS</value>
	<value code="21">Chamorran</value>
	<value code="22">Guamanian, NOS</value>
	<value code="25">Polynesian, NOS</value>
	<value code="26">Tahitian</value>
	<value code="27">Samoan</value>
	<value code="28">Tongan</value>
	<value code="30">Melanesian, NOS</value>
	<value code="31">Fiji Islander</value>
	<value code="32">New Guinean</value>
	<value code="96">Other Asian, incl Asian NOS and Oriental NOS</value>
	<value code="97">Pacific Islander, NOS</value>
	<value code="98">Other</value>
	<value code="99">Unknown</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089669.v1">
	<name>inss_stage</name>
	<description>INSS Stage</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="1">Stage 1</value>
	<value code="2">Stage 2a</value>
	<value code="3">Stage 2b</value>
	<value code="4">Stage 3</value>
	<value code="5">Stage 4</value>
	<value code="6">Stage 4s</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089670.v1">
	<name>mycn</name>
	<description>MYCN Status</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="0">Not amplified</value>
	<value code="1">Amplified</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown, not done, unsatisfactory, in progress</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089671.v1">
	<name>ploidy</name>
	<description>Ploidy</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="0">DI &gt; 1 (hyperdipolid)</value>
	<value code="1">DI &lt;= 1 (hypodiploid, diploid)</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089672.v1">
	<name>hist</name>
	<description>Revised International Neuroblastoma Pathology Classification (INPC) prognostic group (Cancer 2003). If INPC is missing, this is the Shimada classification (JNCI 1984).</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="0">Favorable</value>
	<value code="1">Unfavorable</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown, slides not received, inadequate</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089673.v1">
	<name>grade</name>
	<description>Grade of Neuroblastic Differentiation (Revised International Neuroblastoma Pathology Classification (INPC)).  If INPC grade is missing, then this is Shimada grade.</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="0">Undifferentiated or Poorly Differentiated</value>
	<value code="1">Differentiating</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089674.v1">
	<name>mki</name>
	<description>Mitosis-Karyorrhexis Index (MKI) (Revised International Neuroblastoma Pathology Classification (INPC)).  If INPC MKI is missing, then this is Shimada MKI.  When multiple nodules present in a single Ganglioneuroblastoma, nodular tumor, the higher MKI value is reported.</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="1">Low (&lt;2% or &lt;100/5,000 cells)</value>
	<value code="2">Intermediate (2-4% or 100-&lt;200/5,000 cells)</value>
	<value code="3">High (&gt;4% or &gt;200/5,000 cells)</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089675.v1">
	<name>diag</name>
	<description>Diagnostic Category (Revised International Neuroblastoma Pathology Classification (INPC)).  If INPC diagnostic category is missing, then this is Shimada diagnostic category.</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>9</logical_max>
	<value code="1">Neuroblastoma (Schwannian stroma-poor)</value>
	<value code="2">Ganglioneuroblastoma, intermixed (Schwannian stroma-rich)</value>
	<value code="3">Ganglioneuroma (Schwannian stroma-dominant), maturing subtype OR Ganglioneuroblastoma, well differentiated (Schwannian stroma-rich)</value>
	<value code="4">Ganglioneuroblastoma, nodular (composite)</value>
	<value code="9">Unknown</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089676.v1">
	<name>icdo</name>
	<description>ICD-O Topography Code (International Classification of Disease Code)</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089677.v1">
	<name>snomed</name>
	<description>Older Topography Code (Systemized Nomenclature of Medicine-Clinical Terms)</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089678.v1">
	<name>icdo_snomed_description</name>
	<description>Either the ICDO code, or the SNOMED code (if ICDO=999 or Unknown) or a hard-coded value if both codes unknown but information available</description>
	<type>string</type>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089679.v1">
	<name>efscens</name>
	<description>Events are described as the first occurrence of relapse, progressive disease, secondary malignancy, or death.</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>1</logical_max>
	<value code="0">No event</value>
	<value code="1">Event</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089680.v1">
	<name>scens</name>
	<description>Events are described as the first occurrence of relapse, progressive disease, secondary malignancy, or death.</description>
	<type>encoded value</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>1</logical_max>
	<value code="0">Alive</value>
	<value code="1">Dead</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089681.v1">
	<name>efstime</name>
	<description>Number of days from diagnosis until the event, or until last contact if no event</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<unit>days</unit>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>5562</logical_max>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089682.v1">
	<name>stime</name>
	<description>Number of days from diagnosis until death, or until last contact if alive</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<unit>days</unit>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>5562</logical_max>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089683.v1">
	<name>COG Risk Group</name>
	<description>COG risk stratification criteria at the time the patient enrolled</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<logical_min>1</logical_min>
	<logical_max>3</logical_max>
	<value code="1">Low risk</value>
	<value code="2">Intermediate Risk</value>
	<value code="3">High Risk, per COG risk stratification criteria at the time the patient enrolled</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089684.v1">
	<name>Protocol(s)</name>
	<description>COG Protocol number on which the patient was enrolled</description>
	<type>string</type>
	<value code="901">Trial of Mouse Monoclonal Anti-GD-2 Antibody 14.G2A Plus IL-2 With or Without GM-CSF in Children With Refractory NBL or Melanoma</value>
	<value code="911">I-131-MIBG for Therapy of Advanced Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="914">A Dose Escalation Study of Cisplatin, Doxorubicin, VP-16, and Ifosfamide Followed by GM-CSF in Advanced NBL and Peripheral Neuroepithelioma</value>
	<value code="925">Study of Topotecan</value>
	<value code="935">Study of ch14.18 with GM-CSF in Children with Neuroblastoma (NBL) and Other GD2 Positive Malignancies Immediately Post ABMT or PBSC</value>
	<value code="937">Phase I Trial of ZD1694, an Inhibitor of Thymidylate Synthase, in Pediatric Patients with Advanced Neoplastic Disease</value>
	<value code="9709">A Phase I Study of Fenretinide in Children with High Risk Solid Tumors</value>
	<value code="321P2">New Intensive Chemotherapy for CCG Stage II (with N-myc amplification), Stage III and Stage IV Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="321P3">Treatment of Poor Prognosis Neuroblastoma Before Disease Progression With Intensive Multimodal Therapy and BMT</value>
	<value code="323P">Cyclic Combination Chemotherapy for Newly Diagnosed Stage III Neuroblastoma Age 2 and Older and Stage IV Neuroblastoma All Ages</value>
	<value code="3881">Biology and Therapy of Good, Intermediate, and Selected Poor Prognosis Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="3891">Conventional Dose Chemoradiotherapy vs Ablative Chemoradiotherapy With Autologous BMT for High-Risk Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="3951">Phase I Pilot Study of Multiple Cycles of High Dose Chemotherapy With Peripheral Blood Stem Cell Infusions In Advanced Stage Neuroblastoma.</value>
	<value code="4941">National Wilms Tumor Study V - Therapeutic Trial &amp; Biology Study</value>
	<value code="8605">Study of the Combination of Ifosfamide, Mesna, and VP-16 in Children and Young Adults With Recurrent Sarcomas, PNET and Other Tumors</value>
	<value code="8742">Phase III portion of 8741 for Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="9047">Neuroblastoma Biology Protocol</value>
	<value code="9082">Protocol for the Development of Intervention Strategies to Reduce the Time Between Symptom Onset and Diagnosis of Childhood Cancer - A Pediatric Oncology Group Cancer Control Study</value>
	<value code="9140">Therapy for Patients with Recurrent or Refractory Neuroblastoma - A Phase II Study</value>
	<value code="9262">A Phase II Study of Taxol in Children with Recurrent/Refractory Soft-Tissue Sarcoma, Rhabdomyosarcoma, Osteosarcoma, Ewing&#39;s Sarcoma, Neuroblastoma, Germ Cell Tumors, Wilms&#39; Tumor, Hepatoblastoma, and Hepatocellular Carcinoma, a POG Study</value>
	<value code="9280">Neuroblastoma Epidemiology Protocol - A Non-Therapeutic Study - A Joint Project of: The University of North Carolina, The Pediatric Oncology Group and The Children&#39;s Cancer Study Group</value>
	<value code="9340">Treatment of Patients &gt;365 Days at Diagnosis with Stage IV NBL: Upfront Phase II Window - A Phase II Study</value>
	<value code="9341">Treatment of Patients &gt;365 Days at Diagnosis with Stage IV and Stage IIB/III (N-myc) NBL - A Phase III Study</value>
	<value code="9342">Neuroblastoma #5, Bone Marrow Transplant - A Phase III Study</value>
	<value code="9343">Interleukin-6 in Children Receiving Autologous Bone Marrow Transplantation for Advanced Neuroblastoma - A Pediatric Oncology Group Phase I Trial</value>
	<value code="9361">Topotecan in Pediatric Patients with Recurrent or Progressive Solid Tumors - A Pediatric Oncology Group Phase II Study</value>
	<value code="9375">Topotecan Plus Cyclophosphamide in Children with Solid Tumors - A Pediatric Oncology Group Phase I Trial</value>
	<value code="9464">Cyclophosphamide Plus Topotecan in Children with Recurrent or Refractory Solid Tumors - A Pediatric Oncology Group Phase II Study</value>
	<value code="9640">Treatment of Patients with High Risk Neuroblastoma (A Feasibility Pilot) Using Two Cycles of Marrow Ablative Chemotherapy Followed By Rescue With Peripheral Blood Stem Cells (PBSC), Radiation Therapy</value>
	<value code="A3973">A Randomized Study of Purged vs. Unpurged PBSC Transplant Following Dose Intensive Induction Therapy for High Risk NBL</value>
	<value code="AADM01P1">Protocol for Registration and Consent to the Childhood Cancer Research Network: A limited Institution Pilot</value>
	<value code="AAML00P2">A Dose Finding Study of the Safety of Gemtuzumab Ozogamicin Combined with Conventional Chemotherapy for Patients with Relapsed or Refractory Acute Myeloid Leukemia</value>
	<value code="ACCL0331">A Randomized Double Blind Placebo Controlled Clinical Trial to Assess the Efficacy of Traumeel&#174; S (IND # 66649) for the Prevention and Treatment of Mucositis in Children Undergoing Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</value>
	<value code="ACCRN07">Protocol for the Enrollment on the Official COG Registry, The Childhood Cancer Research Network (CCRN)</value>
	<value code="ADVL0018">Phase I Study of hu14.18-IL2 Fusion Protein in Patients with Refractory Neuroblastoma and other Refractory GD2 Expressing Tumors</value>
	<value code="ADVL0212">A Phase I Study of Depsipeptide (NSC#630176, IND# 51810)  in Pediatric Patients with Refractory Solid Tumors and Leukemias</value>
	<value code="ADVL0214">A Phase I Study of Single Agent OSI-774 (Tarceva) (NSC # 718781, IND #63383) Followed by OSI-774 with Temozolomide for Patients with Selected Recurrent/Refractory Solid Tumors, Including Brain Tumors</value>
	<value code="ADVL0215">A Phase I Study of Decitabine in Combination with Doxorubicin and Cyclophosphamide in the Treatment of Relapsed or Refractory Solid Tumors</value>
	<value code="ADVL0421">A Phase II Study of Oxaliplatin in Children with Recurrent Solid Tumors</value>
	<value code="ADVL0524">Phase II Trial of Ixabepilone (BMS-247550), an Epothilone B Analog, in Children and Young Adults with Refractory Solid Tumors</value>
	<value code="ADVL0525">A Phase II Study of Pemetrexed in Children with Recurrent Malignancies</value>
	<value code="ADVL06B1">A Pharmacokinetic-Pharmacodynamic-Pharmacogenetic Study of Actinomycin-D and Vincristine in Children with Cancer</value>
	<value code="ADVL0714">A Phase I Study of VEGF Trap (NSC# 724770, IND# 100137) in Children with Refractory Solid Tumors</value>
	<value code="ALTE03N1">Key Adverse Events after Childhood Cancer</value>
	<value code="ALTE05N1">Umbrella Long-term Follow-up Protocol</value>
	<value code="ANBL0032">Phase III Randomized Study of Chimeric Antibody 14.18 (Ch14.18) in High Risk Neuroblastoma Following Myeloablative Therapy and Autologous Stem Cell Rescue</value>
	<value code="ANBL00B1">Neuroblastoma Biology Studies</value>
	<value code="ANBL00P1">A Pilot Study of Tandem High Dose Chemotherapy with Stem Cell Rescue Following Induction Therapy in Children with High Risk Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="ANBL02P1">A Pilot Induction Regimen Incorporating Dose-Intensive Topotecan and Cyclophosphamide for Treatment of Newly Diagnosed High Risk Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="ANBL0321">Phase II Study of Fenretinide in Pediatric Patients with Resistant or Recurrent Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="ANBL0322">A Phase II study of hu14.18-IL2 (BB-IND-9728) in Children with  Recurrent or Refractory Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="ANBL0532">Phase III Randomized Trial of Single vs. Tandem Myeloablative as Consolidation Therapy for High-Risk Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="ANBL0621">A Phase II Study of ABT-751, an Orally Bioavailable Tubulin Binding Agent, in Children with Relapsed or Refractory Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="B003">Diagnostic and prognostic studies in NBL</value>
	<value code="B903">Childhood Cancer Genetics</value>
	<value code="B947">Protocol for Collection of Biology Specimens for Research Studies</value>
	<value code="B954">Opsoclonus-Myoclonus-Ataxia Syndrome, Neuroblastoma and the Presence of Anti-neuronal Antibodies</value>
	<value code="B973">Laboratory-Clinical Studies of Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="E04">Self-Administered Epidemiology Questionnaire</value>
	<value code="E18">A Case-Control Study of Risk Factors for Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="I03">Neuroblastoma, Diagnostic/Prognostic</value>
	<value code="N891">Parents&#39; Perceptions of Randomization</value>
	<value code="P9462">Randomized Treatment of Recurrent Neuroblastoma with Topotecan Regimens following Desferrioxamine (POG only) in an Investigational Window</value>
	<value code="P9641">Primary Surgical Therapy for Biologically Defined Low-Risk Neuroblastoma</value>
	<value code="P9761">A Phase II Trial of Irinotecan in Children with Refractory Solid Tumors</value>
	<value code="P9963">A Phase II Trial of Rebeccamycin Analogue (NSC #655649) in Children with Solid Tumors</value>
	<value code="R9702">Prognostic Implications of MIBG Uptake in Patients with Neuroblastoma Previously Treated on CCG-3891</value>
	<value code="S31">Right Atrial Catheter Study</value>
	<value code="S921">Comparison of Urokinase vs Heparin in Preventing Infection in Central Venous Devices in Children with Malignancies</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089685.v1">
	<name>percent_tumor</name>
	<description>Proportion of specimen (tumor vs non-tumor), as estimated on specimen quality control review by the Biopathology Center in Columbus</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>0.98</logical_max>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00089686.v1">
	<name>percent_necrosis</name>
	<description>Proportion of tumor (necrotic vs viable), as estimated on specimen quality control review by the Biopathology Center in Columbus</description>
	<type>integer</type>
	<logical_min>0</logical_min>
	<logical_max>1</logical_max>
</variable>

</data_table>
