<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002431.v4" study_id="phs000007.v28" participant_set="10" date_created="Mon Apr 25 18:35:15 2016"><description>Physical Exam and Disorders of the Foot, Original and Offspring Cohorts December 2000 and June 2008. Participants are limited to those who attended Original Cohort Exams 27-28 and Offspring Exam 8. The Framingham Foot Study, an ancillary study of the FHS, is an observational cohort study of adults to examine the role of foot disorders upon functional limitations and disability. Foot disorders were assessed using a validated Foot Assessment Clinical Tool that captures the main features of common foot disorders. Reliability of this instrument has been shown to be excellent [Hannan et al., 2001; Hannan et al., 2003]. Briefly, trained clinical examiners conducted a physical examination of a participant's feet, collected data on medical history, plantar pressures using a computerized mat, and administered risk assessment questionnaires. Specific disorders of interest included hallux valgus, toe deformities other than hallux (lesser toe deformities of hammer toes, claw toes and overlapping toes), heel fat-pad atrophy, fore fat-pad atrophy, pes cavus, and pes planus. Information relevant to foot pain was also collected in the questionnaire. The structural foot disorders were indicated as present or absent based on an atlas of pictorial depictions of each foot disorder. For example, heel fat-pad atrophy, this condition was indicated as present or absent based on palpitation of the plantar heel of each foot. If bony prominences were noted at this area with minimal pressure then atrophy was considered present (to indicate decreased fat/muscle mass on the bottom of the heel).</description><variable id="phv00163500.v3"><name>shareid</name><description>Framingham Heart Study participant SHARe ID number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00163501.v3"><name>idtype</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type>encoded</type><value code="0">Original Cohort</value><value code="1">Offspring Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00163502.v3"><name>exam</name><description>Exam number</description><type>encoded,string</type><value code="ex27">Original Cohort exam 27</value><value code="ex28">Original Cohort exam 28</value><value code="ex8">Offspring cohort exam 8</value></variable><variable id="phv00163508.v3"><name>exdate</name><description>Foot study date</description><type>integer</type><unit>days</unit><logical_min>10002</logical_min><logical_max>20566</logical_max><comment>Number of days since exam 1</comment></variable><variable id="phv00226995.v1"><name>HVALGUS</name><description>Presence of hallux valgus</description><type>encoded</type><value code="0">No hallux valgus</value><value code="1">Yes hallux valgus</value><value code=".">unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00226996.v1"><name>pescav</name><description>Presence of pes cavus</description><type>encoded</type><value code="0">No pes cavus</value><value code="1">Yes pes cavus</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable></data_table>
