<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002998.v1" study_id="phs000145.v3" participant_set="2" date_created="Thu Oct 18 10:53:25 2012"><variable id="phv00173962.v1"><name>SUBJID</name><description>POPRES Subject ID</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00173963.v1"><name>EUROPEAN_LABEL</name><description>The geographic label for a sampled individual was based upon the self-reported labels attributed to 1) the four grandparents, 2) two grandparents and one parent, 3) the two parents, or 4) the individual, based upon data availability. Conflicting labels of ancestors resulted in an attribution to a higher level label.  Europe was divided the four regions UN Northern, UN Western, UN Southern and UN Eastern Europe as defined in the UN geo-scheme for Europe.  Those 4 groups were then further subdivided based on sampling of 500 individuals as follows:  UN Northern into North-Western Europe (Great Britain and Ireland) and Northern Europe which includes all other UN Northern countries but Finland.  UN Western Europe was split into Western Europe (Belgium, France, Luxembourg, and the Netherlands) and Central Europe (Austria, Germany, and Switzerland). Finally, UN Southern Europe was split into South-Western Europe (Spain, Portugal, and Andorra) and South-Eastern Europe (all others).</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00173964.v1"><name>WORLD_LABEL</name><description>Labels defined as follows:  African American: self identified as African ancestry from Jamaica or Grenada, European: self identified as European ancestry from UN Northern, UN Western, UN Southern, UN Eastern or a mixture of these  4 groups, Hispanic: self identified Hispanic from Colombia, Guyana, or  Uruguay, Southern Asia: self identified as origin from Afghanistan, India, Nepal, Pakistan or Sri Lanka, Western Asia: self identified as origin from Iraq, Jordan, Qatar, Turkey or Yemen and Other: Ancestry missing, incomplete or with small numbers from regions other than those specified</description><type>string</type></variable></data_table>
