<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht001891.v2" study_id="phs000007.v15" participant_set="6" date_created="Tue Aug 23 12:07:49 2011"><unique_key phv="00121928" version="1">of_fxsite</unique_key><unique_key phv="00121929" version="1">of_fxside</unique_key><unique_key phv="00121930" version="1">of_fxcircum</unique_key><unique_key phv="00121934" version="1">of_fxdate</unique_key><unique_key phv="00121935" version="1">shareid</unique_key><variable id="phv00121926.v1"><name>of_fxdt_imp</name><description>Date of fracture imputed (for both hip and non-hip fractures)?</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value></variable><variable id="phv00121927.v1"><name>of_imp_type</name><description>Which components of the date of fracture are imputed (for hip and non-hip fractures)?</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><value code="0">Fracture date NOT imputed because month, day and year were available.</value><value code="1">DAY of fracture imputed because day missing: 15 was assigned in cases like this</value><value code="2">MONTH of fracture imputed because month missing: 6 was assigned in cases like this</value><value code="3">DAY and MONTH of fracture imputed because both were missing</value><value code="4">DAY, MONTH, and YEAR of fracture imputed because all were missing: date was obtained from an x-ray report of an old fracture</value><value code="5">DAY, MONTH, and YEAR of fracture imputed because all were missing: date was obtained from a note in the medical history taken by nurse/MD in participant's medical records</value></variable><variable id="phv00121928.v1"><name>of_fxsite</name><description>Fracture location (for both hip and non-hip fractures).</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><comment>Hip and non-hip fractures were initially categorized into 60 detailed skeletal sites (see backof annotated form), but then collapsed into 21 locations for ease of analysis.</comment><value code="1">Hip</value><value code="2">All wrist and forearm fractures: includes wrist (unspecified), distal radius (Colles';Smith), distal ulna, both distal radius and ulna, other small bones in wrist and radius a/o ulna, proximal or mid shaft</value><value code="3">Skull</value><value code="4">Facial bones: includes jaw, nose, cheek</value><value code="5">Shoulder</value><value code="6">Clavicle or collar bone</value><value code="7">Scapula (shoulder blade)</value><value code="8">Upper arm: includes arm (unspecified), and humerus (upper arm)</value><value code="9">Elbow</value><value code="10">Hand</value><value code="11">Fingers</value><value code="12">Ribs</value><value code="13">Chest/sternum</value><value code="14">All vertebrae: includes neck, 1-7 or multiple cervical vertebra; 1-12, multiple or unspecified thoracic spine vertebra; 1-5, multiple or unspecified lumbar vertebra, multiple lumbar vertebra, and spine (unspecified)</value><value code="15">Pelvis</value><value code="16">Tailbone/coccyx/sacrum</value><value code="17">Leg: includes leg (unspecified), femur (not hip), tibia, fibula, both tibia/fibula</value><value code="18">Patella</value><value code="19">Ankle (includes distal tibia and fibula)</value><value code="20">Foot/metatarsal: includes foot/metatarsal and heel/os calcis</value><value code="21">Toes</value></variable><variable id="phv00121929.v1"><name>of_fxside</name><description>Fracture side (for both hip fractures and non-hip fractures).</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><value code="1">Right</value><value code="2">Left</value><value code="3">Axial (vertebral, pelvis, nasal, sacrum, sternum, skull)</value><value code="9">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00121930.v1"><name>of_fxcircum</name><description>Detailed circumstances of fracture (for both hip and non-hip fractures).</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><value code="1">Fall from standing height or less - includes most injuries due to tripping over something, slips in shower or tub, falling out of chair or bed, pt lands on the surface at the same height as the surface he/she was standing on</value><value code="2">Falls on stairs, steps or curbs - includes all falls during change in level, such as stepping up or down stairs, steps, curbs.</value><value code="3">Fall from more than standing height, but NOT on stairs - includes falls from heights such as off a ladder or while standing on a table or chair, off a porch, out of a window, etc.</value><value code="4">Minimal trauma other than a fall - includes vertebral fractures associated with coughing, stepping down a step, etc, and rib or other fractures associated with turning over in bed, etc.</value><value code="5">Moderate trauma other than a fall - includes collisions with objects during normal activities (stub toe, hit hand against door frame, walking into door), twisting or turning ankle (or ankle fractures).</value><value code="6">Severe trauma other than a fall - includes motor vehicle accidents, struck by a car, hit by rapidly moving projectile (golf ball, golf club), assault.</value><value code="7">Pathologic fracture - usually associated with cancer in bone.</value><value code="8">Unknown/Don't Know</value></variable><variable id="phv00121931.v1"><name>of_cnfrmfx</name><description>Fracture confirmed by medical record (for both hip and non-hip fractures)?</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><value code="0">No</value><value code="1">Yes</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00121932.v1"><name>of_hipfxtype</name><description>Hip Fracture Location</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><value code="1">Intertrochanteric</value><value code="2">Femoral neck</value><value code="3">Other</value><value code="9">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00121933.v1"><name>idtype</name><description>Framingham Cohort Identifier</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval><value code="1">Offspring Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00121934.v1"><name>of_fxdate</name><description>Date fracture occurred (for both hip and non-hip fractures)</description><type/><unit>number of days since exam 1</unit><logical_min>2165</logical_min><logical_max>13217</logical_max><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval></variable><variable id="phv00121935.v1"><name>shareid</name><description>Framingham Participant SHARe ID Number</description><type/><coll_interval>Reviewed through 2007</coll_interval></variable></data_table>
