<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002523.v2" study_id="phs000435.v2" participant_set="1" date_created="Wed May 29 12:37:25 2013"><variable id="phv00165093.v2"><name>SUBJID</name><description>Unique Participant Identifier</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00165096.v2"><name>Primary Disease</name><description>The main disease(s) for which the participant has been asked to donate a sample for study</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00165095.v2"><name>Gender</name><description>Participant's gender as Male or Female</description><type>string</type><comment>Note: A single gender discrepancy has been detected when comparing data of version 2 to version 1, please regard this current version (2) as the correct one.</comment><value>Female</value><value>Male</value></variable><variable id="phv00165094.v2"><name>Age</name><description>Participant's age</description><type>integer, string</type><unit>Years</unit></variable><variable id="phv00165098.v2"><name>IGHV</name><description>IGHV is mutation status  of the immunoglobulin heavy chain variable region. When the DNA sequence homology  of CLL tumor is less than 98% compared to reference, it is designated as "mutated". Homology &gt;98% is considered "unmutated."  IGHV mutation status is a CLL prognosis marker; IGHV mutated status is associated with good prognosis.</description><type/><value code="0">Unmutated</value><value code="1">Mutated</value><value>Not Reported</value></variable><variable id="phv00165099.v2"><name>ZAP70</name><description>ZAP70 is CLL prognosis marker and  positive expression is associated with poor prognosis. ZAP70 expression level is measured by flow cytometry and the cutoff score is 24%.</description><type/><value code="0">Negative</value><value code="1">Positive</value><value>Not Reported</value></variable><variable id="phv00165100.v2"><name>Trisomy 12</name><description>Trisomy 12 is measured by FISH cytogenetic analysis. Cutoff score is 2%. Trisomy 12 is a neutral prognosis marker.</description><type/><value code="0">Negative</value><value code="1">Positive</value></variable><variable id="phv00165101.v2"><name>Del13qhet</name><description>Del13qhet is measured by FISH cytogenetic analysis of CLL tumor. Del13qhet is a chromosome 13q deletion in one allele. Cutoff score is 7%. Del13q is one of the most common chromosomal abnormalities in CLL and is associated with  better prognosis.</description><type/><value code="0">Negative</value><value code="1">Positive</value></variable><variable id="phv00165102.v2"><name>Del13qhomo</name><description>Del13qhomo is measured by FISH cytogenetic analysis of CLL tumor.  Del13qhomo is a deletion of the 13q region in two alleles. Cutoff score is 7%. Del13q is one of the most common chromosomal abnormalities in CLL and is associated with  better prognosis.</description><type/><value code="0">Negative</value><value code="1">Positive</value></variable><variable id="phv00165103.v2"><name>Del11q</name><description>Del11q is measured by FISH cytogenetic analysis of CLL tumor, and is associated with poor prognosis. Cutoff score is 5%.</description><type/><value code="0">Negative</value><value code="1">Positive</value></variable><variable id="phv00165104.v2"><name>Del17p</name><description>Del17p is measured by FISH cytogenetic analysis of CLL tumor. The deleted region includes TP53, and is associated with poor prognosis. Cutoff score is 8%.</description><type/><value code="0">Negative</value><value code="1">Positive</value></variable></data_table>
