<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002188.v1" study_id="phs000250.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Wed Jul  6 12:53:41 2011"><variable id="phv00159010.v1"><name>SUBJID</name><description>De-identified subject ID.  This variable can be used to merge the phenotype data with the genomic data.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00159011.v1"><name>age_dec</name><description>Age decade. This variable quantifies the age of the patient (in decades) at the time of registration.  For example, a patient who is 40-49 years of age at the time of registration would have a value of 4, and a patient who is 50-59 years of age at the tim</description><type/><unit>Decades of years</unit></variable><variable id="phv00159012.v1"><name>dzext</name><description>Extent of disease. This variable is the absolute neutrophil count prior to treatment.  Units are 1000/micro liter.</description><type/><unit>1000/microliter</unit><value code="1">Metastatic</value><value code="2">Locally advanced</value></variable><variable id="phv00159013.v1"><name>sex</name><description>Gender. This variable indicates the self reported gender of the patient at the time of registration.</description><type/><value code="1">Male</value><value code="0">Female</value><value code="9">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00159014.v1"><name>race</name><description>Race. This variable is the self reported race of the patient at the time of registration.  Patients who report more than one race are categorized as having multiple races.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00159015.v1"><name>priorrt</name><description>Prior radio therapy. This variable indicates if the patient was administered radiotherapy prior to protocol therapy.</description><type/><value code="1">Yes</value><value code="0">No</value></variable><variable id="phv00159016.v1"><name>ps</name><description>The Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group [ECOG] performance status. This is the ECOG performance status of the patient prior to protocol therapy.</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00159017.v1"><name>arm</name><description>Treatment received. This variable indicates whether the patients receive placebo or bevacizumab.</description><type/><value code="1">Bevacizumab</value><value code="2">Placebo</value></variable><variable id="phv00159018.v1"><name>ostime</name><description>Overall survival (months). This variable quantifies time of death (due to any cause) starting from the time of registration.  It is measured in months. For patients who were still alive, at the time of the locking of the clinical database, this variable q</description><type/><unit>Months</unit></variable><variable id="phv00159019.v1"><name>osevent</name><description>Censor variable for overall survival. This is a censoring variable that can be used in a survival analysis to indicate death due to any cause.  It is paired with ostime. Patients who were dead when the clinical database was frozen are coded as 1. All othe</description><type/><value code="1">Dead</value><value code="0">Censored</value></variable><variable id="phv00159020.v1"><name>anc</name><description>Pre-study neutrophil count. This variable is the absolute neutrophil count prior to treatment.  Units are 1000/micro liter.</description><type/><unit>1000/microliter</unit></variable><variable id="phv00159021.v1"><name>urine24</name><description>Pre-study Protein from 24 hr urine collection - required is dipstick is &amp;ge;1+. This variable indicates the total protein from a 24 hour urine collection.  The test is administered prior to protocol therapy, but is only required for patients who had p</description><type/><unit>g of protein/24 hours</unit><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159022.v1"><name>urinedip</name><description>Pre-study urine dipstick result (lab test). This variable indicates the urine dipstick result of a patient prior to protocol therapy.  Acceptable values are 0, 1+, 2+, 3+, and 4+.</description><type/><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159023.v1"><name>maxanc</name><description>Max neutropenia grade. This variable is the maximum reported grade of "Neutrophils/granulocytes (ANC/AGC)" adverse events that were possibly, probably or definitely related to treatment. Events reported for all cycles and follow-up are included.</description><type/><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159024.v1"><name>maxhtn</name><description>Max hypertension. This variable is the maximum reported grade of "Hypertension" adverse events that were possibly, probably or definitely related to treatment. Events reported for all cycles and follow-up are included.</description><type/><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159025.v1"><name>maxprot</name><description>Max proteinuria. This variable is the maximum reported grade of "Proteinuria" adverse events that were possibly, probably or definitely related to treatment. Events reported for all cycles and follow-up are included.</description><type/><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159026.v1"><name>pd</name><description>Did patient Progress. This variable indicates if a patient has progressed. Patients who progressed prior to the time the clinical database was frozen are coded as 1. All other patients are coded as 0. This variable can be used with the variable osevent in</description><type/><value code="1">Yes</value><value code="0">No</value></variable><variable id="phv00159027.v1"><name>pfs</name><description>Progression free survival (months). This variable quantifies time of failure (death or progression) starting from the time of registration.  It is measured in months. For patients who were still alive and progression free at the time the clinical database</description><type/><unit>Months</unit></variable><variable id="phv00159028.v1"><name>response</name><description>Best objective response. This variable indicates the best overall response to protocol therapy either during treatment or in follow-up. Criteria for response, progression and relapse are consistent with Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors [RECIST</description><type/><comment>Complete Response (CR): Disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes (whether target non-target) must have reduction in short axis to &lt;10 mm. Partial Response (PR): At least a 30% decrease in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum diameters. Stable Disease (SD): Neither sufficient shrinkage to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for PD, taking as reference the smallest sum diameters while on study. Progressive Disease (PD): At least a 20% increase in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (this includes the baseline sum if that is the smallest on study). In addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. (Note: the appearance of one or more new lesions is also considered progression).</comment><value code="CR">Complete Response</value><value code="PR">Partial Response</value><value code="SD">Stable Disease</value><value code="PD">Progressive Disease</value><value code="Uneval">Undefined</value><value code=".">missing</value><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159029.v1"><name>cycles</name><description>Cycles of therapy. This is the total number of cycles the patient received protocol therapy.</description><type/><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159030.v1"><name>totalgem</name><description>Total dosage of gemcitabine over all cycles. This is the cumulative dose of gemcitabine over all cycles of therapy. Units are in mg.</description><type/><unit>mg</unit><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159031.v1"><name>totbev</name><description>Total dosage of bevacizumab over all cycles. This is the cumulative dose of bevacizamab over all cycles of therapy. Units are in mg.</description><type/><unit>mg</unit><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable><variable id="phv00159032.v1"><name>Analysis</name><description>Index of the samples for the association analysis. This variable indicates whether the sample is qualified for the association analysis</description><type/><value code="1">Yes</value><value code="0">No</value></variable><variable id="phv00159033.v1"><name>GeneticEuropean</name><description>Index of the genetic European samples. This variable indicates whether the sample is qualified for the association analysis</description><type/><value code="1">Yes</value><value code="0">No</value><value code="NA">Not available</value></variable></data_table>
