<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht001152.v1" study_id="phs000234.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Thu Apr 14 13:31:18 2011"><variable id="phv00088225.v1"><name>subjid</name><description>Subject ID</description><type>integer</type></variable><variable id="phv00088226.v1"><name>subj_source</name><description>Site providing the sample</description><type>string</type></variable><variable id="phv00088227.v1"><name>CASE_STATUS</name><description>Cases are defined as: Subjects meeting EMR criteria (5 dementia dx or 1 rx) from VU, Marshfield and Mayo cohorts OR Subjects enrolled in Group Health's ADPR (which required probable presence of Alzheimer's disease at study enrollment) OR Subjects </description><type>string</type><value>CASE</value><value>NOT CASE</value><value>UNKNOWN</value></variable><variable id="phv00088229.v1"><name>CONSENT</name><description>Consent Group</description><type>integer</type><value code="0">Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects</value><value code="1">May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems; no distribution to insurance companies (HR_MC).</value><value code="2">May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems (HR_VU).</value><value code="3">These data will be used only for health related research, including research to improve methods for health related research (HR_GHS).</value><value code="4">Limited to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. For </value><value code="5">Mayo Clinic Data may only be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems; investigators must state in the Data Use Request their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from his or her study with the sci</value></variable><variable id="phv00088230.v1"><name>source_subjid</name><description>Source ID</description><type>integer</type></variable></data_table>
