<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002570.v1" study_id="phs000007.v24" participant_set="9" date_created="Fri Sep  5 22:22:15 2014"><description>Vitamin B12, Folate and Vitamin B6 (PLP), Generation 3 Exam 1. This dataset represents a subset of those Generation 3 participants who came in for Exam 1. This subset represents those participants who also received a CT scan. The Framingham Osteoporosis Study, an ancillary study of the Framingham Heart Study, has contributed substantially to the understanding of risk factors for age-related bone loss and fractures in men and women. One of the study aims is to investigate the relationship between vitamin B12, B6, and folate status and volumetric trabecular bone mineral density measured on CT scans from participants enrolled in the "Framingham Heart Study Offspring and Third Generation Multidetector CT Study," (Framingham CT Study) and their interactions with candidate genes in common methylation pathways. Plasma EDT samples collected at Cycle 1 for the 3rd Generation participants. Vitamin B12/Folate were measured from October 2009 through May 2010. Pyridoxal phosphate (also known as PLP or B6) was analyzed from August through December 2010. Methyl malonic acid, (MMA) measurements will be added once completed.</description><variable id="phv00166967.v1"><name>shareid</name><description>Framingham Heart Study participant SHARe ID number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00166968.v1"><name>B12</name><description>Vitamin B12 (sample: EDTA plasma)</description><type>integer, encoded</type><unit>pg/mL</unit><logical_min>140</logical_min><logical_max>3010</logical_max><value code=".">Missing</value></variable><variable id="phv00166969.v1"><name>FOLATE</name><description>Folate (sample: EDTA plasma)</description><type>integer, encoded</type><unit>ng/mL</unit><logical_min>2.4</logical_min><logical_max>161</logical_max><value code=".">Missing</value></variable><variable id="phv00166970.v1"><name>IDTYPE</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type>integer, encoded</type><value code="3">Generation 3 Cohort</value></variable><variable id="phv00166971.v1"><name>PLP</name><description>Vitamin B6 (sample: EDTA plasma)</description><type>integer, encoded</type><unit>pmol/mL</unit><logical_min>12.64</logical_min><logical_max>1113.03</logical_max><value code=".">Missing</value></variable></data_table>
