<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?><data_table id="pht002569.v4" study_id="phs000007.v28" participant_set="10" date_created="Mon Apr 25 18:39:37 2016"><description>Human Stromal Cell-derived Factor 1 Alpha (SDF-1), Offspring Exam 6. This study includes immunoassay-generated data for plasma stromal cell derived factor-1a (SDF-1) from Exam 6 of Offspring cohort participants. Characterizing robust biomarkers associated with CVD is necessary for the discovery of disease mechanisms and development of diagnostics. Previous studies suggest that SDF-1 is a highly promising biomarker of CVD. SDF-1 is a CXC chemokine that mediates the immune response by regulating lymphocytes, monocytes, and B-cell proliferation. Variants in the SDF-1 gene CXCL12 are associated with plasma SDF-1 levels. We hypothesize that circulating SDF-1 levels are associated with atherosclerotic CVD. For these reasons, we measured plasma SDF-1 levels using an ELISA-based assay from R and D Systems, Inc., Minneapolis, MN, Part #DSA00, http://www.rndsystems.com/pdf/dsa00.pdf. The assay is a 4.5 hour solid-phase ELISA, which measures human SDF-1alpha in platelet-poor plasma. EDTA plasma samples from Exam 6 of Offspring cohort participants were stored at -80C and used immediately after thawing. 3532 Offspring participants completed Exam 6. After exclusion criteria were applied, 3336 measurements qualified for data analysis. These measurements are included in this dataset.</description><variable id="phv00166963.v4"><name>shareid</name><description>Framingham Heart Study participant SHARe ID number</description><type/></variable><variable id="phv00166964.v4"><name>IDTYPE</name><description>Framingham Heart Study cohort identifier</description><type>encoded</type><value code="1">Offspring Cohort</value><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00166965.v4"><name>sdf1</name><description>SDF-1 Human stromal cell-derived factor 1 alpha (sample: EDTA plasma)</description><type>decimal</type><unit>pg/mL</unit><logical_min>787.7</logical_min><logical_max>18503.9</logical_max><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable><variable id="phv00166966.v4"><name>Plate</name><description>Plate number</description><type>integer</type><logical_min>1</logical_min><logical_max>59</logical_max><value code=".">Unknown</value></variable></data_table>
