<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./datadict_v2.xsl"?>
<data_table id="pht000046.v1" study_id="phs000014.v1" participant_set="1" date_created="Tue Aug 12 14:03:29 2008">

<variable id="phv00011085.v1">
	<name>EVENT</name>
	<description>EVENT NUMBER ON SEQUENCE OF EVENTS</description>
	<value code="1">MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION RECOGNIZED, WITH DIAGNOSTIC ECG</value>
	<value code="10">DEFINITE CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT AT EXAM 1, BUT QUESTIONABLE TYPE.</value>
	<value code="11">ATHEROTHROMBOTIC INFARCTION</value>
	<value code="12">TRANSIENT ISCHEMIC ATTACK (ONLY THE 1ST TRANSIENT ISCHEMIC ATTACK IS CODED)</value>
	<value code="13">CEREBRAL EMBOLISM</value>
	<value code="14">INTRACEREBRAL HEMORRHAGE</value>
	<value code="15">SUBARACHNOID HEMORRHAGE</value>
	<value code="16">OTHER CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT</value>
	<value code="19">QUESTIONABLE CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT AT EXAM 1, DATE OF EXAM 1</value>
	<value code="2">MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION RECOGNIZED, WITHOUT DIAGNOSTIC ECG, WITH TRANSAMINASE AND HISTORY</value>
	<value code="21">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE   SUDDEN, WITHIN 1 HOUR</value>
	<value code="22">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE, 1-23 HOURS, NONSUDDEN</value>
	<value code="23">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE, 24-47 HOURS, NONSUDDEN</value>
	<value code="24">DEATH, CORONARY HEART DISEASE, 48 HOURS OR MORE, NONSUDDEN</value>
	<value code="25">DEATH, CEREBROVASCULAR ACCIDENT</value>
	<value code="26">DEATH, OTHER CARDIOVASCULAR DISEASE</value>
	<value code="27">DEATH, CANCER</value>
	<value code="28">DEATH, OTHER CAUSES</value>
	<value code="29">DEATH, CAUSE UNKNOWN</value>
	<value code="3">MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION RECOGNIZED, WITHOUT DIAGNOSTIC ECG, WITH AUTOPSY EVIDENCE, NEW EVENT (SEE ALSO CODE 09)</value>
	<value code="30">INTERMITTANT CLAUDICATION, DATE MIDPOINT OF INTERVAL AS ANGINA PECTORIS, ALSO DATE ONLY FIRST EVENT</value>
	<value code="39">QUESTIONABLE INTERMITTANT CLAUDICATION AT EXAM 1, USE EXAM 1 DATE</value>
	<value code="4">MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION UNRECOGNIZED, SILENT</value>
	<value code="40">CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE NOT HOSPITALIZED</value>
	<value code="41">CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE HOSPITALIZED</value>
	<value code="49">QUESTIONABLE CONGESTIVE HEART FAILURE AT EXAM 1, USE EXAM 1 DATE</value>
	<value code="5">MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION UNRECOGNIZED, NOT SILENT</value>
	<value code="6">ANGINA PECTORIS, FIRST EPISODE DATED ONLY. DATE AS MIDPOINT OF INTERVAL BETWEEN EXAMS OR BETWEEN HOSPITALIZATION AND EXAM.  IF ANGINA PECTORIS OCCURRED WITH MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, THEN USE SAME DATE AS MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY.  UNTIL 1987, IF ANGINA PECTORIS OCCURRED JUST BEFORE MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, THEN DATE 3 MONTHS BEFORE MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY. IF ANGINA PECTORIS OCCURRED JUST AFTER MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, THEN DATE 3 MONTHS AFTER MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION OR CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY.  BEGINNING IN 1987, IF INFORMATION ON THE DATE OF NEW ANGINA WAS AVAILABLE, THEN AN A DATE WAS ASSIGNED, EITHER APPROXIMATE OR EXACT, IF KNOWN.</value>
	<value code="7">CORONARY INSUFFICIENCY, BOTH ECG AND HISTORY DEFINITE</value>
	<value code="8">QUESTIONABLE MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION AT EXAM 1, DATE SAME DATE AS EXAM 1. ANY QUESTIONABLE MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION EPISODE AT EXAM 1:  DEFINITE MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION HISTORY   WITHOUT TRANSAMINASE OR AUTOPSY, OR POSSIBLE MYOCARDIAL INFARCTION-ECG.  DOES NOT INCLUDE QUESTIONABLE ANGINA PECTORIS.</value>
	<value code="9">MI AUTOPSY, NOT A NEW EVENT.  THIS IS SAME EVENT AS A PREVIOUSLY CODED MI (01-02).</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00011087.v1">
	<name>EVTIME</name>
	<description>TIME FROM EXAM 1 TO DATE OF EVENT IN DAYS</description>
	<unit>DAYS</unit>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00011086.v1">
	<name>IDTYPE</name>
	<description>COHORT IDENTIFIER</description>
	<value code="0">ORIGINAL COHORT GROUP</value>
	<value code="1">OFFSPRING GROUP</value>
	<value code="3">GENERATION 3</value>
</variable>

<variable id="phv00011088.v1">
	<name>shareid</name>
	<description>UNIQUE PARTICIPANT ID</description>
</variable>

</data_table>
