<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000127.v2.p1" parentStudy="phs000127.v2.p1" createDate="2010-09-03" modDate="2010-09-03">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Lead Principal Investigator</td><td>Orla Hardiman</td><td>Beaumont Hospital, Dublin, Ireland and Trinity College Institute of Neurosciences, Trinity College, Dublin, Ireland</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Brendan Loftus</td><td>Conway Institute, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin, Ireland</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Principal Investigators</td><td>Daniel G. Bradley</td><td>Smurfit Institute of Genetics, Trinity College, Dublin, Ireland</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Principal Investigators</td><td>Alex Evans</td><td>Conway Institute, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin, Ireland</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Lead Co-Investigators</td><td>Simon Cronin</td><td>Beaumont Hospital, Dublin, Ireland, and Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, Dublin, Ireland</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Study of Irish Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (SIALS)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>A Genome-Wide Association Study of Sporadic ALS in an Irish Population (SIALS) and Sequencing and Analysis of an Irish Human Genome</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) is a fatal neurodegenerative disease characterized by loss of motor neurons.      Epidemiological studies indicate that 2-5% of cases are familial, usually with an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance.      For a portion of these, causative genes have been identified.  The remaining 95% of ALS cases are described as sporadic,      and believed to result from a combination of genetic and environmental factors.</p>      <p>This study utilized samples from Irish patients with sporadic ALS and Irish control individuals.  The aim of the study  	was to identify susceptibility alleles for ALS in the Irish population.  Genome-wide, single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)  	genotyping was undertaken using Illumina 550K version 3 chips.  Genotyping data are available on 221 SALS patients  	and 211 controls.</p>  	<p>Future work will aim to examine ALS genetic risk at individual sequence level.  As an initial step, as of September 2010  	we have made available the human genome sequence from a single anonymous male control individual from the SIALS collection.</p>  	<p>Recent studies generating complete human sequences from Asian, African and European subgroupings have revealed population  	specific variation and illuminated disease susceptibility loci.  The Irish population is of interest because of its  	location at the periphery of Europe and also the impact its emigrants have had on the genetics of populations in a  	number of other countries.  We have identified sequence variants that may be specific to this population and have  	identified potentially novel disease associated variants.  We describe a novel method for improving SNP calling  	accuracy at low genome coverage using haplotype information.  Overall we demonstrate utility in generating whole genome  	sequences to test general principles and reveal specific instances of human biology.  With increasing access to low cost  	sequencing we would predict that similar studies will emerge.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p><b>Cases:</b><br/> All 221 cases were diagnosed by a Consultant neurologist in Ireland.  All included cases fulfilled the      criteria for probable or definite sporadic ALS, according to the El Escorial criteria (as per Brooks, B.R. (1994) El Escorial      World Federation of Neurology criteria for the diagnosis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. J Neurol Sci 124(suppl), 96-107).      Individuals with a family history of neurodegenerative disease, including ALS, were excluded.  All included participants self-reported      Irish Caucasian ethnicity for at least three generations.  Patients were drawn from across the island of Ireland.  Age at      onset was defined according to age at which the first symptom of weakness appeared.</p>      <p><b>Controls:</b><br/> Blood samples were ascertained from unrelated, neurologically normal control individuals drawn from      across the island of Ireland.  All participants self-reported Irish Caucasian ethnicity for at least three generations.  All      controls had no prior or current history of neurological disease, and no family history of neurodegenerative disease or ALS.      Age was defined by the age of the control subject at time of sample collection. Additionally, the whole genome sequence has now  	been made available for a single male control of fully Irish ancestry.  This individual was chosen based on typical clustering  	among the Irish population in population structure analyses.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18057069"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18689356"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19734901"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19265028"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Motor Neuron Disease"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Lead Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Orla Hardiman</AttName>
			<Institution>Beaumont Hospital, Dublin, Ireland and Trinity College Institute of Neurosciences, Trinity College, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Brendan Loftus</AttName>
			<Institution>Conway Institute, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Daniel G. Bradley</AttName>
			<Institution>Smurfit Institute of Genetics, Trinity College, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Alex Evans</AttName>
			<Institution>Conway Institute, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Lead Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Simon Cronin</AttName>
			<Institution>Beaumont Hospital, Dublin, Ireland, and Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Lead Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Pin Tong</AttName>
			<Institution>Conway Institute, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Lead Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>James Prendergast</AttName>
			<Institution>MRC Human Genetics Unit, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Lead Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Amanda Lohan</AttName>
			<Institution>Conway Institute, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Bryan J. Traynor</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute on Neurological Disorders and Stroke, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Matthew J. Greenway</AttName>
			<Institution>Beaumont Hospital, Dublin, Ireland, and Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Stephen Berger</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute on Aging, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Susan Farrington</AttName>
			<Institution>MRC Human Genetics Unit, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Nial Friel</AttName>
			<Institution>School of Mathematical Sciences, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Jim Wilson</AttName>
			<Institution>Centre for Population Health Sciences, University of Edinburgh, Teviot Place, Edinburgh, EH8 9AG, Scotland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Jinhui Ding</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Jennifer C. Schymick</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute on Aging, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Nicole Washecka</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute on Aging, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dena G. Hernandez</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute on Aging, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>Science Foundation Ireland</AttName>
			<Institution>Dublin, Ireland</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="NPU" longName="Non-Profit Use Only"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NINDS</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>ninds-dac@mail.nih.gov</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacFax>301-402-1501</DacFax>
      <DacUrl>http://grants.nih.gov/grants/gwas</DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000127.v2.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
               http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000127.v2.p1
            </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000127.v2.p1" FileName="Irish_ALS_study_NINDS_DUC_2008-09-25.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Non-Profit Use Only</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>NPU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The Irish ALS dataset is restricted for use by academic research institutions and/or non-profit organizations.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>

<Analyses>
	<Analysis pha="2851" genomeBuild="36.3" snpBuild="129" analysisType="">
		<Description>Genome-wide genotyping data was obtained using the Illumina Infinium II 550K SNP SNP for 221 ALS cases and 211 controls. SNPs having call rate below 98%, or Cluster seperaration (as reported by Illumina software) below 0.3, were excluded, resulting in 540553 analyzed SNPs reported here.</Description>
		<Method>Genome-wide association</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="572163" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>combination of two batches, if the alleles are different for the same rs#, please keep two separate lines (for different chips) as two markers .</VendorURL>
			<Platform>HumanHap550v1.1 and HumanHap550v3.0</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
</Analyses>

</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
