<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000421.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000421.v1.p1" createDate="2011-10-07" modDate="2013-05-21">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Natalie Afshari, MD</td><td>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>John Gottsch, MD</td><td>Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Sudha K. Iyengar, PhD</td><td>Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Nicholas Katsanis, PhD</td><td>Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Gordon Klintworth, MD, PhD</td><td>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>A Genome-Wide Association Study of Fuchs&#39; Endothelial Corneal Dystrophy (FECD)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>A Genome-Wide Association Study of Fuchs&#39; Endothelial Corneal Dystrophy (FECD)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Family</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Fuchs&#39; Endothelial Corneal Dystrophy (FECD) is a common disease that results in loss of vision associated with progressive corneal edema and loss of corneal transparency. In the initial stages of the disease, excrescences on Descemet&#39;s membrane with the appearance of an abnormal posterior collagenous layer, result in the clinical and pathologic appearance of guttae. Corneal edema ensues as endothelial function is compromised that may result in stromal edema, epithelial edema, and painful bullous keratopathy. Penetrating or endothelial keratoplasty is the only definitive treatment, with palliative care the only option prior to surgery. The pathophysiology underlying FECD, particularly in the common cases that affect older individuals, remains unknown, with a genetic predisposition being reported as the single best predictor of disease.</p> <p>Three independent groups funded by the National Eye Institute (NEI), with well-established programs in the genetics of FECD, conducted a genome-wide association study of FECD. The collaboration comprised investigators from Case Western University (CWRU), Duke University (DUEC), and Johns Hopkins University (JHU). CWRU and DUEC contributed samples that were genotyped at CIDR for the GWAS. Johns Hopkins University (JHU) provided samples for the replication phase of the study, where their data are not listed in dbGaP. Cohorts of FECD cases and controls were assembled. Synchronization of clinical and coded data was performed to unify the information across centers. The family history, clinical, demographic information, and genome-wide genotype data for samples from CWRU and DUEC were deposited in dbGaP.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>All three sites used a modified Krachmer scale for assessing disease severity in <i>cases</i>. Because each group modified Krachmer&#39;s grading scheme slightly differently, but otherwise had cornea fellowship trained observers using similar instrumentation (slit lamp biomicroscopy) to grade the corneal phenotype, the consortium was able to make adjustments to equalize grading across ascertainment sites. The following grading scheme was used:</p> <p> <table border="1"> <tr>FECD Consortium Grading Scheme</tr> <tr><td>Grade</td><td>Findings</td></tr> <tr><td>0</td><td>No central cornea guttae</td></tr> <tr><td>1</td><td>Scattered central cornea guttae</td></tr> <tr><td>2</td><td>1 or 2 mm of central cornea guttae</td></tr> <tr><td>3</td><td>&gt;2 to 5 mm of grouped central cornea guttae</td></tr> <tr><td>4</td><td>&gt;5 mm of grouped central cornea guttae</td></tr> <tr><td>5</td><td>Cornea guttae with corneal edema</td></tr> </table> </p> <p>There was no age restriction of cases.</p> <p>Based on discussions between investigators at all three centers, the following inclusion criteria for <i>controls</i> were established: <ol> <li>60 years of age or older</li> <li>Normal cornea with no epithelial, stromal, or endothelial abnormalities with the <u>exceptions</u> of: <ul> <li>Arcus senilis and Vogt&#39;s limbal girdle</li> <li>Cornea scar from subepithelial zone</li> <li>Previous cataract, glaucoma or retina-vitreous surgery, as long as the preoperative record indicated no evidence by slit lamp examination of guttae or FECD and postoperative exam also showed no evidence</li> <li>Previous intraocular surgery (such as iridotomy, trabeculoplasty, or pan retinal photocoagulation with same caveats as intraocular surgery)</li> </ul> </li> </ol> </p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22045388"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22045388"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16769829"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18502986"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20036349"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21533127"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Fuchs&#39; Endothelial Dystrophy"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Natalie Afshari, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>John Gottsch, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Sudha K. Iyengar, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Nicholas Katsanis, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Gordon Klintworth, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Jonathan Lass, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-investigator">
			<AttName>Simon Gregory, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-investigator">
			<AttName>Yi-Ju Li, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01EY016482 (CWRU, PI: Sudha Iyengar)</AttName>
			<Institution>National Eye Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01EY016514 (DUEC, PI: Gordon Klintworth)</AttName>
			<Institution>National Eye Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01EY016835 (JHU, PI: John Gottsch)</AttName>
			<Institution>National Eye Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping">
			<AttName>HHSN268200782096C. NIH contract &quot;High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&quot;</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping">
			<AttName>HHSN268201100011I. NIH contract &quot;High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&quot;</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>CWRU initiated its genetics studies on FECD with the commencement of the FECD Genetics Multi-center Study funded by the National Eye Institute in 2005. The study involved the recruitment of probands, family members and unrelated controls from 29 sites throughout United States from the practices of private practice or university based cornea fellowship trained specialists. All sites underwent rigorous training on acquiring phenotypic disease severity for FECD using a modified grading scale of Krachmer and also detailed personal and family history pertinent to the disease. The probands were defined not only by the severity of the phenotype clinically, but also either by pathologic confirmation of the excised corneal tissue following keratoplasty or by enrolling additional severely affected siblings or avuncular relatives. Recruitment began in March 2005 and was concluded in December 2010.</p> <p>Duke University initiated its study of FECD in 2002 and the team was granted an NIH award in 2007. The Duke dataset has over 1200 study subjects. Initially a linkage study was performed using 22 families (Afshari, et al., IOVS 2009). Since then the team has focused on both recruitment and genetic studies of FECD. A recent study with a combination of association and linkage studies (Li et al., 2011) was able to replicate TCF4 gene reported by Baratz et al. (2010). In our study, a set of 450 cases and 340 normal controls was used for association study, and revealed significant association with rs613872, the target marker of Baratz et al.(2010). In addition, the genome-wide linkage scan on 64 multiplex families composed primarily of affected sibling pairs (ASPs), a larger dataset than our first linkage scan, led to a promising linkage region localizing to chromosome 18 from 69.94cM to 85.29cM, with a peak multipoint HLOD = 2.5. The peak marker, rs1145315 (75.58cM) under the DOM model maps 1.5 Mb proximal to rs613872, which provides strong supporting evidence for the association finding at TCF4 marker. Both recruitment and genetic studies of FECD are still ongoing at Duke University Eye Center.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects."/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="FECD" longName="FECD Studies Only"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="5" shortName="EDO" longName="Eye Disease Research Only"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NEI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Eye Institute</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000421.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>9</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000421.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000421.v1.p1" FileName="FECD_DUC_v3.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>FECD Studies Only</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>FECD</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The use of this data is restricted to Fuch''s Endothelial Corneal Dystrophy only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The data can be used for research purposes.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="5">
        <ConsentName>Eye Disease Research Only</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>EDO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The data set is used only for eye disease .</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
