<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000564.v2.p1" parentStudy="phs000564.v2.p1" createDate="2014-11-17" modDate="2015-07-14">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Stephen Kingsmore, MB, ChB, BAO, DSc, FRCPath</td><td>Children&#39;s Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigator</td><td>Carol Saunders, PhD</td><td>Children&#39;s Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Rapid Whole Genome Sequencing for Genetic Disease Diagnosis in the NICU</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Rapid Whole Genome Sequencing for Genetic Disease Diagnosis in Neonatal Intensive Care Units</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case Set</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Parent-Offspring Trios</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Monogenic diseases are frequent causes of neonatal morbidity and mortality, and disease presentations are often undifferentiated at birth. More than 3,500 monogenic diseases have been characterized, but clinical testing is available for only some of them and many feature clinical and genetic heterogeneity. As such, an immense unmet need exists for improved molecular diagnosis in infants. Because disease progression is extremely rapid, albeit heterogeneous, in newborns, molecular diagnoses must occur quickly to be relevant for clinical decision-making. We describe 50-hour differential diagnosis of genetic disorders by whole-genome sequencing (WGS) that features automated bioinformatic analysis and is intended to be a prototype for use in neonatal intensive care units. Retrospective 50-hour WGS identified known molecular diagnoses in two children. Prospective WGS disclosed potential molecular diagnosis of a severe <i>GJB2</i>-related skin disease in one neonate; <i>BRAT1</i>-related lethal neonatal rigidity and multifocal seizure syndrome in another infant, identified <i>BCL9L</i> as a novel, recessive visceral heterotaxy gene (<i>HTX6</i>) in a pedigree, and ruled out known candidate genes in one infants. Sequencing of parents or affected siblings expedited the identification of disease gene in prospective cases. Thus, rapid WGS can potentially broaden and foreshorten differential diagnosis, resulting in fewer empirical treatments and faster progression to genetic and prognostic counseling.</p> <p>Reprinted from Saunders et. al, Rapid Whole-Genome Sequencing for Genetic Disease Diagnosis in Neonatal Intensive Care Units. Sci. Transl. Med. 4, 154ra135 (2012; <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?term=Rapid%20Whole-Genome%20Sequencing%20for%20Genetic%20Disease%20Diagnosis%20in%20Neonatal%20Intensive%20Care%20Units">PMID: 23035047</a>) with permission from AAAS.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>To assess the ability to recapitulate known results, whole genome sequencing was performed retrospectively on two infants with molecular diagnoses that had previously been identified by clinical testing. These samples (UDXXXX) were selected from a validation set of 384 samples with known molecular diagnoses for one or more genetic diseases.</p> <p>To assess the potential diagnostic use of WGS, sequencing was prospectively performed on four undiagnosed newborns with clinical presentations that strongly suggested a genetic disorder as well as one affected sibling and their unaffected parents. Seven prospective samples were selected from families with probands that presented in infancy, among 143 individuals without molecular diagnoses who were enrolled between November 2011 and April 2012 for exome or genome sequencing.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23035047"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Congenital, Hereditary, and Neonatal Diseases and Abnormalities"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Developmental Disabilities"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Cerebellar Ataxia"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Epidermolysis Bullosa"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Epilepsy"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Heterotaxy Syndrome"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Mitochondrial Diseases"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Growth and Development"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Malformations of Cortical Development"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Macrocephaly"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Menkes Kinky Hair Syndrome"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Microcephaly"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Myotonia"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Seizures"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Tay-Sachs Disease"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Stephen Kingsmore, MB, ChB, BAO, DSc, FRCPath</AttName>
			<Institution>Children&#39;s Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigator">
			<AttName>Carol Saunders, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Children&#39;s Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="Children&#39;s Mercy Hospitals and Clinics" url="http://www.childrensmercy.org/Health_Care_Professionals/Research/Pediatric_Genomic_Medicine/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>2012: The version 1 study release provided SNP data derived from whole genome sequences of n=9 subjects.</p> <p>2014: The version 2 study release provides SNP data derived from whole genome sequences of n=279 subjects.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU-IRB-PUB-COL-NPU-MDS-GSO" longName="General Research Use (IRB, PUB, COL, NPU, MDS, GSO)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NICHD</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NICHD-DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000564.v2.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000564.v2.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000564.v2.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use (IRB, PUB, COL, NPU, MDS, GSO)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU-IRB-PUB-COL-NPU-MDS-GSO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s).
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
