<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000733.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000733.v1.p1" createDate="2014-03-27" modDate="2014-06-05">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Lisa Cannon Albright, PhD</td><td>The University of Utah, UT, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>R01 CA089600</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>ICPCG Genome Wide Association Study of Familial Prostate Cancer</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>The International Consortium for Prostate Cancer Genetics Genome Wide Association Study of Familial Prostate Cancer</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Initially, the ICPCG focused largely on high-risk prostate cancer pedigrees using linkage analysis. However, association studies have also been informative to find prostate cancer susceptibility variants in the genome. We hypothesize that genome-wide (GW) association studies of familial cases of prostate cancer will have the power to identify rarer and perhaps less penetrant risk variants associated with prostate cancer than have been identified to date. Our approach will be to examine evidence for association in selected, independent cases from high-risk pedigrees; we hypothesize that they represent a more homogeneous set of cases with potentially different associations. Use of the 5M plus exome SNP platform will allow us to include in our search more rare variants in our search than have ever been investigated for prostate cancer.</p> <p><b>Aim 1. </b>Identify a set of independent prostate cancer cases selected from ICPCG high-risk prostate cancer pedigrees that have 3 or more related prostate cancer cases and have an average age at diagnosis &#8804; 75 years. Identify appropriate matched controls from participating ICPCG groups/ populations.</p> <p><b>Aim 2. </b>Perform GW SNP genotyping with the Illumina 5M plus exome SNP set on the set of independent prostate cancer cases and controls described in Aim 1.</p> <p><b>Aim 3. </b>Perform association analyses appropriately matching controls for different ICPCG populations and groups. There will be a two-stage design for confirmation.</p> <p><b>Aim 4. </b>Test reported associations using the extensive sample set available to us by collaboration with the PRACTICAL consortium that has access to 50 000 DNA samples from 34 groups internationally <i>(over 7,000 of whom are positive for prostate cancer family history).</i></p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p><b><u>Selection of cases:</u></b></p> <p>Ascertainment of 1 case from each pedigree that meets the ascertainment criteria: pedigree average age dx &#8804; 75 years and 3 or more related cases</p> <p>Case to select by pedigree:</p> <p>-Most aggressive case or Earliest age onset/dx if no, or more than one, most aggressive</p> <p><b><u>Selection of controls</u></b></p> <p>Must be male<br/> Must be unrelated to cases<br/> Must be unrelated to each other<br/> Controls not 1:1 matched to cases, but overall distribution by race/birth year is similar.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22712434"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21748754"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23064873"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Prostate cancer, familial"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Lisa Cannon Albright, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>The University of Utah, UT, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01 CA089600</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="International Consortium for Prostate Cancer Genetics" url="http://www.icpcg.org/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-PC" longName="Disease-Specific (Prostate Cancer)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>



</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
