<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000542.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000542.v1.p1" createDate="2012-08-29" modDate="2012-08-29">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Lydia Aguilar-Bryan, MD, PhD</td><td>Pacific Northwest Diabetes Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>Thrasher Fund Grant</td><td>Thrasher Research Fund, Salt Lake City, UT, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Sequencing Center</td><td>Northwest Genomics Center (NWGC; Director: Deborah Nickerson)</td><td>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source for Sequencing</td><td>HG005608</td><td>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Next Generation Mendelian Genetics: Neonatal Diabetes</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Next Generation Mendelian Genetics: Neonatal Diabetes</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case Set</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The NHGRI Next Generation Mendelian Genetics project uses exome resequencing to identify variants in unsolved Mendelian diseases.</p> <p>Neonatal diabetes mellitus (ND) is a rare form of monogenic diabetes (90,000-260,000 live births) that is diagnosed in the first 6 months of life. The disease has been classified as transient or permanent and although it can be inherited, more frequently is sporadic as a result of &#39;de novo&#39; mutations. Defects in 12 genes have been found as responsible for the disease (defects in the paternally imprinted chromosomal region 6q24, IPF1, SLCA2A, INS, EIF2AK3, GCK, FOXP3, GLIS3, PTF1A, HNF1Beta, KCNJ11 and ABCC8). The two subunits of the ATP-sensitive K channel (ABCC8 and KCNJ11) and the insulin gene (INS), account for almost half of the cases and similar to CHI, the other half, remains genetically unexplained.</p> <p>We became part of this study when we submitted 4 DNA samples for exome sequencing, from patients with NDM of Caucasian ancestry, which had no mutations identified in ABCC8 or KCNJ1, with the goal to identify new mutations in known genes or new mutations or genetic variants in new genes.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Only patients with neonatal diabetes were chosen and none of the 1st degree relatives were included. The patients were chosen from a multiethnic/racial group in accordance to the control sample available, which was Caucasian.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Pancreatic beta cell agenesis with neonatal diabetes mellitus"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Lydia Aguilar-Bryan, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Pacific Northwest Diabetes Research Institute, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>Thrasher Fund Grant</AttName>
			<Institution>Thrasher Research Fund, Salt Lake City, UT, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Sequencing Center">
			<AttName>Northwest Genomics Center (NWGC; Director: Deborah Nickerson)</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for Sequencing">
			<AttName>HG005608</AttName>
			<Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>DNA samples from patients with Neonatal Diabetes and their families were collected under an IRB approved consent form, after our laboratory (Aguilar-Bryan and Bryan) cloned and reconstituted KATP channel activity. This important channel links cell metabolism with electrical activity. Patients for this study are Caucasians from North American, and were chosen from a total population of ~135 cases, which included patients of Caucasian, Latino and a few of Asian and African American origin. We sequenced DNA from patients with several insulin secretory abnormalities, including Congenital Hyperinsulinism and Neonatal Diabetes. Understanding the mechanism by which mutations in the KATP channel subunits result in NDM, many of the patients have been treated with hypoglycemic agents instead of insulin injections. Four patients that had been sequenced for the frequent genes with no results were included in this study.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHGRI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Human Genome Research Institute</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000542.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000542.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000542.v1.p1" FileName="DUC_for_Neonatal_Diabetes.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>General Research Use</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
