<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000340.v3.p1" parentStudy="phs000340.v3.p1" createDate="2014-04-09" modDate="2014-04-09">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Charles Mullighan, MD</td><td>Department of Pathology, St. Jude Children&#39;s Research Hospital, Memphis, TN, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Sequencing of ETP T-ALL</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>The genomic complexity of early T-cell progenitor acute lymphoblastic leukemia</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Whole Genome Sequencing</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Tumor vs. Matched-Normal</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Case Set</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p><b>CREST</b></p> <p>The accurate identification of structural variations using whole-genome DNA sequencing data generated by next-generation sequencing technology is extremely difficult. To address this challenge, we have developed CREST, an algorithm that uses sequencing reads with partial alignments to the reference human genome (so-called soft-clipped reads) to directly map the breakpoints of somatic structural variations. We applied CREST to paired tumor/normal whole genome sequencing data from five cases of T-lineage acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL). A total of 110 somatic structural variants were identified, &gt;80% of which were validated by genomic PCR and Sanger sequencing. The validated structural variants included 31 inter-chromosomal translocations, 19 intra-chromosomal translocations, one inversion, 22 deletions and 16 insertions. A comparison of the results generated with CREST to those obtained using the traditional paired-end discordant mapping methods demonstrate CREST to have a much higher sensitivity and specificity. In addition, application of CREST to publicly available whole-genome sequencing data from the human melanoma cancer cell line COLO-829 demonstrated the identification of 50 novel structural variations not detected using the standard methods, 20 of which were selected for validation with a 90% success rate. These data demonstrate that direct mapping of soft-clipped reads offers an improved method for detecting structural variants at the nucleotide level of resolution.</p> <p><b>T-ALL</b></p> <p>Early T-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (ETP ALL) is an aggressive malignancy of unknown genetic basis. We performed whole-genome sequencing of 12 ETP ALL cases and assessed the frequency of the identified somatic mutations in 94 T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukaemia cases. ETP ALL was characterized by activating mutations in genes regulating cytokine receptor and RAS signalling (67% of cases; <i>NRAS</i>, <i>KRAS</i>, <i>FLT3</i>, <i>IL7R</i>, <i>JAK3</i>, <i>JAK1</i>, <i>SH2B3</i> and <i>BRAF</i>), inactivating lesions disrupting haematopoietic development (58%; <i>GATA3</i>, <i>ETV6</i>, <i>RUNX1</i>, <i>IKZF1</i> and <i>EP300</i>) and histone-modifying genes (48%; <i>EZH2</i>, <i>EED</i>, <i>SUZ12</i>, <i>SETD2</i> and <i>EP300</i>). We also identified new targets of recurrent mutation including <i>DNM2</i>, <i>ECT2L</i> and <i>RELN</i>. The mutational spectrum is similar to myeloid tumours, and moreover, the global transcriptional profile of ETP ALL was similar to that of normal and myeloid leukaemia haematopoietic stem cells. These findings suggest that addition of myeloid-directed therapies might improve the poor outcome of ETP ALL.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Cases of early T cell progenitor acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ETP T-ALL). The cases in this cohort have had whole genome sequencing of tumor and normal DNA performed. The definition of ETP T-ALL can be found in Lancet Oncol. 2009 Feb;10(2):147-56. PMID: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19147408" target="_blank">19147408</a>. Cases were selected that had appropriate consent for genetic studies, and suitable material for sequencing (high purity tumor populations and available normal DNA obtained at disease remission).</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21666668"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Jinghui Zhang, Li Ding, Linda Holmfeldt, Gang Wu, Sue L. Heatley, Debbie Payne-Turner, John Easton, Xiang Chen, 		Jianmin Wang, Michael Rusch, Charles Lu, Shann-Ching Chen, Lei Wei, J. Racquel Collins-Underwood, Jing Ma, Kathryn G. Roberts, 		Stanley B. Pounds, Anatoly Ulyanov, Jared Becksfort, Pankaj Gupta, Robert Huether, Richard W. Kriwacki, Matthew Parker, 		Daniel J. McGoldrick, David Zhao, Daniel Alford, Stephen Espy, Kiran Chand Bobba, Guangchun Song, Deqing Pei, Cheng Cheng, 		Stefan Roberts, Michael I. Barbato, Dario Campana, Elaine Coustan-Smith, Sheila A. Shurtleff, Susana C. Raimondi, Maria Kleppe, 		Jan Cools, Kristin A. Shimano, Michelle L. Hermiston, Sergei Doulatov, Kolja Eppert, Elisa Laurenti, Faiyaz Notta, John E. Dick, 		Giuseppe Basso, Stephen P. Hunger, Mignon L. Loh, Meenakshi Devidas, Brent Wood, Stuart Winter, Kimberley P. Dunsmore,  		Robert S. Fulton, Lucinda L. Fulton, Xin Hong, Christopher C. Harris, David J. Dooling, Kerri Ochoa, Kimberly J. Johnson, 		John C. Obenauer, William E. Evans, Ching-Hon Pui, Clayton W. Naeve, Timothy J. Ley, Elaine R. Mardis, Richard K. Wilson, 		James R. Downing, Charles G. Mullighan" title="The genetic basis of early T-cell precursor acute lymphoblastic leukaemia." journal="Nature, in press"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Leukemia, T-cell"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Charles Mullighan, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Pathology, St. Jude Children&#39;s Research Hospital, Memphis, TN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>Whole genome sequence data from twelve cases of ETP T-ALL and sequence from matched normal samples. Five samples were used to develop and validate a novel algorithm CREST for the identification of structural variations from whole genome sequence data.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU-MDS" longName="General Research Use (MDS)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000340.v3.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000340.v3.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000340.v3.p1" FileName="DUC-PCPG-Whole_Genome_Seq_of_ALL-5.3.11.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use (MDS)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU-MDS</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification. Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
