<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000415.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000415.v1.p1" createDate="2011-09-21" modDate="2015-05-22">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Jeremiah M. Scharf, MD, PhD</td><td>Psychiatric and Neurodevelopmental Genetics Unit, Center for Human Genetic Research, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Carol A. Mathews, MD</td><td>Langley Porter Psychiatric Institute, Department of Psychiatry, University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>David L. Pauls, PhD</td><td>Psychiatric and Neurodevelopmental Genetics Unit, Center for Human Genetic Research, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Nancy Cox, PhD</td><td>Section of Genetic Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Nelson Freimer, MD</td><td>Center for Neurobehavioral Genetics, Semel Institute for Neuroscience and Human Behavior, University of California at Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Whole Exome and Targeted Sequencing in Tourette Syndrome Multiplex Families</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Whole Exome and Targeted Sequencing in Tourette Syndrome Multiplex Families</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Extended Pedigrees</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>This study consists of 771 individuals from 15 extended, multi-generational Tourette Syndrome (TS) pedigrees collected by the Tourette Syndrome Association International Consortium for Genetics (TSAICG), 213 of whom are affected either with TS or its broader, genetically related phenotype, chronic tic disorder (CT). Prior microsatellite linkage analysis, including 624 individuals from these families, has identified a genome-wide significant TS/CT susceptibility locus on chromosome 2p21-24 with two additional loci meeting criteria for suggestive linkage on chromosomes 6p12-21 and 17p11-q11. Subsequent joint linkage and association analysis, incorporating genome-wide SNP genotyping on the Illumina Hap610 platform from 221 individuals, has strengthened the evidence for a major TS/CT locus on chromosome 2p but did not refine the locus further. In addition, haplotype analyses suggest that multiple TS/CT loci may exist on the short arm of chromosome 2.</p> <p>The goal of the current sequencing study is to use exon-focused sequencing, supplemented with targeted sequencing of additional known functional elements on chromosome 2p, to identify susceptibility variants contributing to the highly penetrant TS/CT phenotype in these families.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Each pedigree was selected based on the presence of multiple affected individuals either with TS or CT across at least two generations. Both affected individuals and unaffected relatives were recruited and assessed for the presence of TS and CT using a standardized, semi-structured interview, which has high clinical validity and reliability for the diagnosis of TS (&#954;=1.0) (TSAICG, Am J Hum Genet, 2007).</p> <p>For the current sequencing study, pedigrees with the strongest evidence for linkage on chromosome 2 were prioritized. Within pedigrees, individuals were chosen for sequencing based on the following criteria: <b>a)</b> affected individuals as distantly related as possible with the common haplotype(s) segregating in that pedigree; <b>b)</b> individuals with key recombination events. For branches of chromosome 2-linked families, where the chromosome 2 risk haplotype was not transmitted to an affected offspring, complete trios were selected with the goal of identifying TS causal variants elsewhere in the exome.</p> <p>For the large pedigrees with little-or-no evidence for linkage on chromosome 2, complete trios with an affected parent were selected, as well as multi-generational lineages with a chain of affected individuals.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17304708"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19913658"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Tourette Syndrome"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Tics"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Jeremiah M. Scharf, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Psychiatric and Neurodevelopmental Genetics Unit, Center for Human Genetic Research, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Carol A. Mathews, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Langley Porter Psychiatric Institute, Department of Psychiatry, University of California at San Francisco, San Francisco, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>David L. Pauls, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Psychiatric and Neurodevelopmental Genetics Unit, Center for Human Genetic Research, Massachusetts General Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Nancy Cox, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Section of Genetic Medicine, Department of Medicine, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Nelson Freimer, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Center for Neurobehavioral Genetics, Semel Institute for Neuroscience and Human Behavior, University of California at Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Ben Oostra, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Clinical Genetics, Erasmus University Medical Center, Rotterdam, Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Peter Heutink, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Section of Medical Genomics, Department of Clinical Genetics, Free University of Amsterdam Medical Center, Amsterdam, Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>William McMahon, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Child Psychiatry, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Cathy Barr, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Genetics and Development, Toronto Western Research Institute, University Health Network, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>X01 HG006253-01</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for CIDR Genotyping">
			<AttName>HHSN268200782096C. NIH contract &quot;High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&quot;</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for CIDR Genotyping">
			<AttName>HHSN268201100011I. NIH contract &quot;High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&quot;</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p> 1980s-1990s: Samples collected<br/> 2004-2006: Microsatellite linkage analyses performed on 624 individuals<br/> 2009-2010: High-density SNP genotyping performed on 221 individuals<br/> 2011: Current study with whole genome genotyping data. </p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-TS-NPU" longName="Disease-Specific (Tourette Syndrome, NPU)"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>



</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
