<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000842.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000842.v1.p1" createDate="2014-11-28" modDate="2014-12-04">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Craig Wong, MD, MPH</td><td>University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center and UNM Children&#39;s Hospital</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Principal Investigator</td><td>Franz Schaefer, MD</td><td>Center for Pediatrics and Adolescent Medicine, University of Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>R01DKO82394</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>PediGFR</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Pediatric Investigation of Genetic Factors Linked with Renal Progression (PediGFR)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Multicenter</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Prospective</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Observational</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The Pediatric Investigation for Genetic Factors Associated with Renal Progression (PediGFR) (RO1-DK082394) is an international collaborative study among three large prospective cohort studies of children with chronic kidney disease. The participating parent cohort studies are the "<i>Chronic Kidney Disease in Children (CKiD)</i>", the "<i>Effect of Strict Blood Pressure Control and ACE Inhibition on CRF Progression in Pediatric Patients (ESCAPE)</i>", and the "<i>Cardiovascular Comorbidity in Children with Chronic Kidney Disease (4C)</i>" study. In these cohorts, pediatric subjects with CKD have been prospectively followed with standardized measurements for renal progression. The dbGaP data upload will utilize the structure of sub-studies to include the genotype and baseline phenotype for the three cohorts, as well as the RBC trait and anemia data for a sub-study under PI Susan Furth: "<i>Role of Genetic Variation in the Anemia of Chronic Kidney Disease</i>" (K24DK078737).</p> <p>In brief PediGFR is a prospective study of children with chronic kidney disease (CKD) to determine genetic factors associated with kidney function measured by the estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) by Schwartz equation.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>The PediGFR utilized de-identified data from subjects who had consented for genetic testing, provided a sample of DNA, and who had data available for the renal trait phenotype as well and RBC trait and anemia phenotype. Exclusions are those who did not provide genetic consent, subject IDs whose genotyping did not pass quality control.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21841064"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22622496"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20576824"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19846849"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Kidney Diseases"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Renal Insufficiency"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Renal Insufficiency, Chronic"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Craig Wong, MD, MPH</AttName>
			<Institution>University of New Mexico Health Sciences Center and UNM Children&#39;s Hospital</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Franz Schaefer, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Center for Pediatrics and Adolescent Medicine, University of Heidelberg, Heidelberg, Germany</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01DKO82394</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The PediGFR study is an international collaborative study designed to determine the gene loci associated with renal disease progression in children. Genotyping of the US-based CKiD cohort occurred prior to the genotyping of the European cohorts (ESCAPE and 4C). Furthermore, the renal trait phenotype of cystatin C has been assayed for the European cohort.</p> <p>In November 2013, the genotyping and phenotyping data for the CKiD sub-study were released by dbGaP. Under PI Susan Furth, the ancillary study (K24DK078737) to utilize this genotyping data, "<i>The Role of Genetic Variation in the Anemia of Chronic Kidney Disease</i>", was included for the data utilized for CKiD.</p> <p>The genotyping and phenotyping data for the European cohorts (ESCAPE and 4C) are being uploaded to dbGaP as sub-studies. Subsequent uploads include the anemia trait data of the ancillary study (K24DK078737) for ESCAPE/4C cohorts.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-CKD-COMP-IRB" longName="Disease-Specific (Chronic Kidney Disease and Related Complications, IRB)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIDDK</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIDDK Central Repository GWAS Data Access Committee</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000842.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000842.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000842.v1.p1" FileName="ModeNIDDKdbGaPlDUC_2010April7_FINAL_edited_for_format_and_links_2-2011.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Chronic Kidney Disease and Related Complications, IRB)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-CKD-COMP-IRB</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Chronic Kidney Disease and Related Complications.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
