<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000948.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000948.v1.p1" createDate="2015-07-01" modDate="2015-08-04">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Eric B. Larson, MD</td><td>Group Health Cooperative  Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>U01 HG006375</td><td>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Genetic Discovery and Application in a Clinical Setting: Continuing a Partnership (eMERGE Phase II)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genetic Discovery and Application in a Clinical Setting: Continuing a Partnership (eMERGE Phase II)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The electronic Medical Records and Genomics (eMERGE) Network is a consortium of ten participating sites funded by the NHGRI to investigate the use of electronic medical record systems for genomic research. The goal of eMERGE is to conduct genome-wide association studies in approximately 19,000 individuals using EMR-derived phenotypes and DNA from linked Biorepositories. The eMERGE Network brings together researchers with a wide range of expertise in genomics, statistics, ethics, informatics, and clinical medicine from leading medical research institutions across the country. Each center participating in the consortium is uniquely situated to provide critical resources to this highly collaborative and productive network. Each site combines a biobank or study cohort with extensive genomic data and access to clinical data derived from electronic medical records. Sites are geographically dispersed and have diverse patient populations, including two sites focusing specifically on pediatrics. </p> <p>The eMERGE Network is comprised of 9 sites and one coordinating center. Each site maintains its own biorepository where DNA specimens are linked to phenotypic data contained within EMRs.</p> <p> <ul> <p><b>Children&#39;s Hospital of Pennsylvania</b>, PI: Hakon Hakonarson, MD, PhD </p> <p><b>Cincinnati Children&#39;s Medical Center with Boston Children&#39;s Hospital</b>, PI: John Harley, MD, PhD - CCHMC and Ingrid Holm, MD, MPH - BCH </p> <p><b>Geisinger Health System</b>, PI: David Carey, PhD and Marc Williams, MD </p> <p><b>Group Health Cooperative with University of Washington</b>, PI: Eric Larson, MD, MPH - GHC and Gail Jarvik, MD, PhD - UW </p> <p><b>Marshfield Clinic with Essentia Institute of Rural Health</b>, PI: Catherine McCarty, PhD, MPH - Essentia and Murray Brilliant, PhD - Marshfield </p> <p><b>Mayo Clinic</b>, PI: Christopher Chute, MD, DrPH and Iftikhar Kullo, MD </p> <p><b>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</b>, PI: Erwin Bottinger, MD </p> <p><b>Northwestern University</b>, PI: Rex Chisholm, PhD and Maureen Smith, MS </p> <p><b>Vanderbilt University</b>, PI: Dan Roden, MD </p> <p><b>eMERGE Coordinating Center</b> - Vanderbilt University, PI: Paul Harris, PhD </p> </ul> </p> <p>Using electronic phenotyping methods, the consortium used DNA samples from all participating sites to explore the genetic determinants of red cell indices, white blood count (WBC) differential, diabetic retinopathy, height, serum lipid levels, specifically total cholesterol, HDL (high density lipoprotein), LDL (low density lipoprotein), and triglycerides, and autoimmune hypothyroidism as well as using the phenome-wide association study (PheWAS) paradigm to replicate and discover relationships between targeted genotypes with multiple phenotypes.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Study participants:</p> <p><b>Inclusion Criteria</b></p> <ul> <li>50-65 years old Group Health members</li> <li>Enrolled in the integrated group practice</li> <li>Health Risk Assessment [HRA] completers</li> </ul> <p><b>Exclusion Criteria</b></p> <ul> <li>Actively receiving chemotherapy treatment (within last 2 weeks)</li> <li>Pregnant Women</li> <li>Opted out of research participation</li> <li>Unable to provide informed consent</li> </ul><p></p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="NA"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Eric B. Larson, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Group Health Cooperative  Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>U01 HG006375</AttName>
			<Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="eMERGE" url="https:emerge.mc.vanderbilt.edu/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="HMB" longName="Health/Medical/Biomedical"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHGRI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Human Genome Research Institute</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000948.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000948.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000948.v1.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Health/Medical/Biomedical</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HMB</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
