<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000206.v5.p3" parentStudy="phs000206.v5.p3" createDate="2015-07-10" modDate="2015-07-23">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Laufey Amundadottir</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Brian Wolpin</td><td>Department of Medical Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, Massachusetts,  Department of Medicine, Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Rachael Stolzenberg-Solomon</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Study Representatives</td><td>Laura Beane-Freeman</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Study Representatives</td><td>Nuria Malats</td><td>Genetic and Molecular Epidemiology Group, CNIO-Spanish National Cancer Research Centre, Madrid, Spain</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Pancreatic Cancer Cohort and Case-Control Consortium (PanScan)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Whole Genome Scan for Pancreatic Cancer Risk in the Pancreatic Cancer Cohort Consortium and Pancreatic Cancer Case-Control Consortium (PanScan)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Longitudinal Cohort</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Within the framework of the NCI-sponsored Cohort Consortium, investigators from 12 prospective epidemiologic cohorts formed the Pancreatic Cancer Cohort Consortium in 2006. This study, also known as &#34;PanScan&#34;, is funded by the National Cancer Institute (NCI) and involves conducting a genome-wide association study (GWAS) of common genetic variants to identify markers of susceptibility to pancreatic cancer. In 2007, the study was expanded to include 8 case-control studies. The study team includes scientists from the cohorts comprising the Consortium, the NCI and the Pancreatic Cancer Case Control Consortium (PanC4). PanScan I and II were conducted in 12 cohort studies and 8 case-control studies, leading to the discovery of four novel regions in the genome associated with risk for pancreatic adenocarcinoma.</p> <p>The third phase of PanScan (PanScan III) was conducted using recently identified incident pancreatic cancer cases drawn from fourteen cohorts from the cohort consortium, including nine prospective cohorts who participated in PanScan I, and five newly joined cohorts. The nine cohort studies that participated in PanScan I and had new genotyping of cases in PanScan III include ATBC, CPS-II, EPIC, HPFS, NHS, PHS, PLCO, SMWHS, and WHI; the five newly joined cohort studies include the Agricultural Health Study (AHS), the Multiethnic Cohort Study (MEC), the Melbourne Collaborative Cohort Study (MCCS), the Vitamins and Lifestyle Study (VITAL), and Selenium and Vitamin E Cancer Prevention Trial (SELECT). In addition to the cases from cohorts, we also included cases from the Gastrointestinal Cancer Clinic of Dana-Farber Cancer Institute Study (DFCI-GCC); from the University Hospital in Heidelberg, Germany, which is part of a larger European clinical case-control study (PANDoRA); and from clinic-based cases from eastern Spain (PANKRAS-II). </p> <p>The dbGaP datasets available include all subjects previously made available from PanScan I and II (phs000206.v4.p3), plus 1,582 new incident pancreatic cancer cases of European descent from prospective cohorts, case-control studies or case series (genotyped as part of PanScan III). Also included are 61 pancreatic cancer cases and 67 control subjects from PanScan I as well as 173 pancreatic cancer cases from PanScan III of Asian ancestry from the Shanghai Men&#39;s and Women&#39;s Health Study (Supplemental Table 10, Wolpin et al. (Nat Genet, 2014)). The control population used in the analysis for the Wolpin et al. manuscript included cancer-free individuals from the prospective cohorts that contributed pancreatic cancer cases to PanScan III and controls from the Spanish Bladder Cancer SBC/EPICURO study that were previously genotyped using the OmniExpress, Omni 1M or Omni 2.5M SNP arrays. The data from these control subjects were posted to dbGaP under the GWAS in which they were initially genotyped and will not be made available in duplicate under this dbGaP study.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Cases were defined as those individuals having primary adenocarcinoma of the exocrine pancreas (ICD-O-3 code C250-C259). Those with non-exocrine pancreatic tumors (histology types 8150, 8151, 8153, 8155 and 8240) were excluded.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20101243"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="25086665"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19648918"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Pancreatic Neoplasms"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Laufey Amundadottir</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Brian Wolpin</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Medical Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, Massachusetts,  Department of Medicine, Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Rachael Stolzenberg-Solomon</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Laura Beane-Freeman</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Nuria Malats</AttName>
			<Institution>Genetic and Molecular Epidemiology Group, CNIO-Spanish National Cancer Research Centre, Madrid, Spain</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Kala Visvanathan</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, Maryland, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Eric Jacobs</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Epidemiology and Surveillance Research, American Cancer Society, Atlanta, GA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Eric Duell</AttName>
			<Institution>Unit of Nutrition, Environment and Cancer, Cancer Epidemiology Research Program, Catalan Institute of Oncology (ICO), Bellvitge Biomedical Research Institute (IDIBELL), Barcelona, Spain</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Charlie Fuchs</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Medical Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute and Channing Laboratory, Department of Medicine, Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Larry Kolonel</AttName>
			<Institution>The Cancer Research Center of Hawaii (retired), Honolulu, Hawaii, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Graham Giles</AttName>
			<Institution>Centre for Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Melbourne School of Population and Global Health, The University of Melbourne, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Alan Arslan</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Department of Environmental Medicine, New York University School of Medicine and New York University Cancer Institute, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Myron Gross</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Laboratory Medicine/Pathology, School of Medicine, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Wei Zheng</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Medicine and Vanderbilt-Ingram Cancer Center, Vanderbilt University, Nashville, TN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Phyllis Goodman</AttName>
			<Institution>Southwest Oncology Group Statistical Center, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Emily White</AttName>
			<Institution>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, Department of Epidemiology, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Charles Kooperberg</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Public Health Sciences, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Melissa A Austin</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Epidemiology, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Allison Klein</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Oncology, Pathology and Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Gloria Petersen</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Health Sciences Research, College of Medicine, Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Donghui Li</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Gastrointestinal Medical Oncology, University of Texas M.D. Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Sara Olson</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Steve Gallinger</AttName>
			<Institution>Samuel Lunenfeld Research Institute, Mount Sinai Hospital, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Paige Bracci</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, University of California, San Francisco, San Francisco, California, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Harvey Risch</AttName>
			<Institution>Yale University School of Public Health, New Haven, CT, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Federico Canzian</AttName>
			<Institution>Genomic Epidemiology Group, German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Kouros Owzar</AttName>
			<Institution>Alliance Statistics and Data Center, Department of Biostatistics and Bioinformatics, Duke Cancer Institute, Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Gary Goodman</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Public Health Sciences, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, Washington, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Statistician">
			<AttName>Kai Yu</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Statistician">
			<AttName>Peter Kraft</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Epidemiology, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Bioinformatics">
			<AttName>Zhaoming Wang</AttName>
			<Institution>Cancer Genomics Research Laboratory, National Cancer Institute, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, Leidos Biomedical Research, Inc., Frederick National Laboratory 			for Cancer Research, Frederick, Maryland, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Coordination">
			<AttName>Patricia Hartge</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Coordination">
			<AttName>Robert Hoover</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Coordination">
			<AttName>Stephen Chanock</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Coordination">
			<AttName>Geoffrey Tobias</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Coordination">
			<AttName>Joanne Elena</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Control and Population Sciences, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>HHSN261200800001E</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>NIH/NCI K07 CA140790</AttName>
			<Institution>the American Society of Clinical Oncology Conquer Cancer Foundation, the Howard Hughes Medical Institute, the Lustgarten Foundation, the Robert T. and Judith B. Hale Fund for Pancreatic Cancer Research and Promises for Purple to B.M.W.</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="Pancreatic Cancer Cohort Consortium" url="http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/PanScan/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The Pancreatic Cancer Cohort Consortium</p> <p>Each of the 17 member studies of the Cohort Consortium participating in this GWAS is a prospective study of a defined population with blood or buccal cells collected prior to the occurrence of pancreatic cancer. Study characteristics vary but the common and standard prospective cohort design allows for rigorous pooled analysis. Additional information can be found at <a href="http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/Consortia/cohort.html/">http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/Consortia/cohort.html/</a>. The studies included in PanScan from the Pancreatic Cancer Cohort Consortium are:</p> <ul> <li><a href="http://www.cancer.org/research/researchtopreventcancer/currentcancerpreventionstudies/cancer-prevention-study">ACS Cancer Prevention Study-II (CPS II)</a></li> <li><a href="http://aghealth.nih.gov/">Agricultural Health Study (AHS)</a></li> <li><a href="http://atbcstudy.cancer.gov/">Alpha-Tocopherol Beta-Carotene Cancer Prevention Study (ATBC)</a></li> <li><a href="http://epic.iarc.fr/">European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition Study (EPIC)</a></li> <li><a href="http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/Consortia/members/clue.html">Give Us a Clue to Cancer and Heart Disease Study (Clue II)</a></li> <li><a href="http://www.hsph.harvard.edu/hpfs/">Health Professional&#39;s Follow-up Study (HPFS)</a></li> <li><a href="http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/Consortia/members/melbourne.html">The Melbourne Collaborative Cohort Study (MCCS)</a></li> <li><a href="http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/Consortia/members/mec.html">Multiethnic Cohort Study of Diet and Health (MEC)</a></li> <li><a href="http://nyuwhs.med.nyu.edu/">NYU Women&#39;s Health Study (NYUWHS)</a></li> <li><a href="http://www.channing.harvard.edu/nhs/">Nurses&#39; Health Study (NHS)</a></li> <li><a href="http://phs.bwh.harvard.edu/">Physicians&#39; Health Study (PHS)</a></li> <li><a href="http://www.cancer.gov/news-events/press-releases/2012/PLCOQandA">Prostate, Lung, Colorectal, and Ovarian (PLCO) Cancer Screening Trial</a></li> <li><a href="http://www.cancer.gov/types/prostate/research/select-trial-results-qa">Selenium and Vitamin E Cancer Prevention Trial (SELECT)</a></li> <li>Shanghai <a href="http://www.mc.vanderbilt.edu/swhs-smhs/index_smhs.html">Men&#39;s</a> and <a href="http://www.mc.vanderbilt.edu/swhs-smhs/">Women&#39;s</a> Health Study (SMWHS)</li> <li><a href="http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/Consortia/members/vital.html">Vitamins and Lifestyle Study (VITAL)</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/whi/">Women&#39;s Health Initiative (WHI)</a></li> <li><a href="http://epi.grants.cancer.gov/Consortia/members/whs.html">Women&#39;s Health Study (WHS) </a></li> </ul> <p>Ten case-control studies and one case series participating in this GWAS with blood or buccal cells collected from individuals with pancreatic cancer or healthy controls. Eight studies are part of the Pancreatic Cancer Case Control Consortium (PanC4). The PanC4 case-control consortium consists of a group of scientists from diverse biomedical disciplines (Epidemiology, Genetics, Biostatistics, Bioinformatics, Molecular Biology, Gastroenterology, Surgery) across the world who have joined together to improve understanding of the causes of pancreatic cancer through joint, or pooled analyses of our data. Additional information can be found at <a href="http://www.panc4.org/">www.panc4.org</a>. The studies included in PanScan (PanScan II) from PanC4 are:</p> <ul> <li>PACIFIC Study of Group Health and Northern California Kaiser Permanente</li> <li>Johns Hopkins University</li> <li>Mayo Clinic SPORE in Pancreatic Cancer</li> <li>MD Anderson Cancer Center</li> <li>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</li> <li>University of California San Francisco</li> <li>University of Toronto</li> <li>Yale University</li> </ul> <p>Three additional case-control studies or case-series were included in PanScan (PanScan III):</p> <ul> <li>Gastrointestinal Cancer Clinic of Dana-Farber Cancer Institute Study (DFCI-GCC)</li> <li>University Hospital in Heidelberg, Germany (part of the PANcreatic Disease ReseArch (PANDoRA) consortium)</li> <li>PANKRAS-II</li> </ul>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="CADM" longName="Cancer in all age groups, other diseases in adults only, and methods"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="DS-PACA-GSO" longName="Disease-Specific (Pancreatic Cancer, GSO)"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="4" shortName="O-DS-PACA-IRB-COL-GSO" longName="Disease-Specific (Pancreatic Cancer, IRB, COL, GSO)"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="5" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="6" shortName="HMB-PUB-NPU-MDS-GSO" longName="Health/Medical/Biomedical (PUB, NPU, MDS, GSO)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000206.v5.p3_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000206.v5.p3
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000206.v5.p3" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Cancer in all age groups, other diseases in adults only, and methods</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>CADM</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The informed consent document signed by the PanScan GWAS participants allows use of these data by investigators for discovery and hypothesis generation in the investigation of the genetic contributions to cancer in all age groups and other diseases in adults only, as well as development of novel analytical approaches for GWAS.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Pancreatic Cancer, GSO)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-PACA-GSO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Pancreatic Cancer.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="4">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Pancreatic Cancer, IRB, COL, GSO)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>O-DS-PACA-IRB-COL-GSO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Pancreatic Cancer.&amp;#x2028;
Requestor must provide documentation of JHU IRB approval.&amp;#x2028;
Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s).&amp;#x2028;
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.&amp;#x2028;
Requestor(s) should obtain the Johns Hopkins PanScan II Collaborator Agreement (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetPdf.cgi?document_name=PANScanCA.pdf). This agreement which governs access to, and use and disclosure of PanScan data maintained in the NIH dbGaP database, will need to be completed and submitted to the JHU IRB for review. For instruction on how to submit your completed Collaborative Agreement to JHU, please contact the iNCI DAC (iNCI_DAC@mail.nih.gov). Upon JHU IRB approval, the Requestor will receive a signed copy of this form which should be appended to the dbGaP application. Upon successful submission, the request will be reviewed by the iNCI DAC for completeness.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="5">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="6">
        <ConsentName>Health/Medical/Biomedical (PUB, NPU, MDS, GSO)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HMB-PUB-NPU-MDS-GSO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>
  <Documents>
    <Document phd="phd003209.1" type="protocol" createDate="2010-08-26" modDate="2010-10-01" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd003209.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000206.v5.p3&amp;phd=3209">
      <OrigName>CGEMS_Pancreatic_Cancer_II_GWAS_analysis_Methods (2).doc</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>Pancreatic Cancer Genome-Wide Association Scan: PanScan II</DisplayName>
      <Description>Pancreatic Cancer Genome-Wide Association Scan: PanScan II</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
  </Documents>


<Analyses>
	<Analysis pha="2874" genomeBuild="36.3" snpBuild="129" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
We have performed the first genome-wide association study (GWAS) of Pancreatic Cancer. Genotyping was performed at the National Cancer Institute&#39;s Core Genotyping Facility with the Illumina Hap500 Infinium genotyping assay in 1,896 pancreatic cancer patients and 1,939 controls. Logistic regression was employed to test for association between single SNPs and pancreatic cancer. Pancreatic cancer cases were drawn from twelve cohort studies and one case-control study: Alpha-Tocopherol Beta-Carotene, Cancer Prevention Study (ATBC), CLUE II, the American Cancer Society Cancer Prevention Study-II (CPS-II),  European Prospective Investigation into Cancer and Nutrition Study (EPIC), Health Professionals Follow-up Study (HPFS), Nurses&#8217; Health Study (NHS), New York University Women&#8217;s Health Study (NYUWHS), Physicians&#8217; Health Study I (PHS I), Prostate, Lung, Colorectal, and Ovarian Cancer Screening Trial (PLCO), Shanghai Men&#8217;s and Women&#8217;s Health Study (SMWHS), Women&#8217;s Health Initiative (WHI), and the Women&#39;s Health Study (WHS) and the Mayo Clinic Molecular Epidemiology of Pancreatic Cancer Study
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Logistic Regression</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="561466" snpBatchId="51468">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL> http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_viewBatch.cgi?sbid=51468</VendorURL>
			<Platform>HumanHap550v3</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="2889" genomeBuild="37.1" snpBuild="131" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
We performed a genome-wide association study (GWAS) of Pancreatic Cancer. Genotyping was performed at the National Cancer Institute&#8217;s Core Genotyping Facility with the Illumina 610Quad Infinium genotyping assay in 3,851 pancreatic cancer patients and 3,934 controls. Logistic regression was employed to test for association between single SNPs and pancreatic cancer. Pancreatic cancer cases were drawn from 12 cohort studies and eight case-control studies. Non-CEU individuals (315 cases and 279 controls which show &lt;85% similarity to the HapMap CEU population by STRUCTURE analysis) are not included in the model.
		]]></Description>
		<Method>categorical analysis on single SNP</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="561466" snpBatchId="51468">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL> http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_viewBatch.cgi?sbid=51468</VendorURL>
			<Platform>HumanHap550v3</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="599011" snpBatchId="1048904">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina Human610-Quadv1_B chip</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Human610-Quadv1_B</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
</Analyses>

</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
