<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000336.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000336.v1.p1" createDate="2010-12-27" modDate="2011-04-20">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Maria Teresa Landi</td><td>Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Neil E. Caporaso</td><td>Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Study Representatives</td><td>Michael Thun</td><td>American Cancer Society, Atlanta, GA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Study Representatives</td><td>Demetrius Albanes</td><td>Nutritional Epidemiology Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Study Representatives</td><td>Jarmo Vitamo</td><td>Department of Chronic Disease Prevention, National Institute for Health and Welfare, Helsinki, Finland</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>DCEG Lung Cancer Study</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>A Genome-Wide Association Study of Lung Cancer Risk</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Three genetic loci for lung cancer risk have been identified by genome-wide association studies (GWAS), but inherited 	susceptibility to specific histologic types of lung cancer is not well established. We conducted a GWAS of lung cancer 	and its major histologic types genotyping 515,922 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in 5,739 incident lung cancer cases 	and 5,848 controls from one population-based case-control study and three cohort studies. Results were combined with 	summary data from 10 additional studies for a total of 13,300 cases and 19,666 controls of European descent.  Four studies 	also provided histology data for replication resulting in 3,333 adenocarcinomas (AD), 2,589 squamous cell carcinomas (SQ), 	and 1,418 small cell carcinomas (SC).</p> 	<p>In analyses by histology, rs2736100 (<i>TERT</i>) on chromosome 5p15.33, was associated with risk of adenocarcinoma 	(OR=1.23, 95%CI=1.13-1.33, P=3.02x10<sup>-7</sup>), but not other histologic types (OR=1.01, P=0.84, and OR=1.00, P=0.93, for SQ 	and SC, respectively). This finding was confirmed in each replication study and overall meta-analysis 	(OR=1.24, 95%CI=1.17-1.31, P=3.74x10<sup>-14</sup> for AD and OR=0.99, P=0.69 and OR=0.97, P=0.48, for SQ and SC, respectively). 	Other previously reported association signals on 15q25 and 6p21 were also refined, but no additional loci reached genome-wide 	significance. In conclusion, a lung cancer GWAS identified a distinct hereditary contribution to adenocarcinoma.</p> 	<p><i>Note: The lung study dataset to be released to dbGaP and caBIG excludes 47 individuals from the PLCO cohort who consented 	to participate only in cancer research projects and 22 individuals because of updated QC. Thus, the released dataset is derived 	from 11517 subjects, 5699 cases and 5818 controls. After the updated QC, the dataset to be released to dbGaP and caBIG 	includes 506062 SNPs.</i></p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Lung cancer cases were included based on a lung cancer diagnosis established on clinical criteria and confirmed by pathology reports 	from surgery, biopsy, or cytology samples in approximately 95% of cases and on clinical history and imaging for the remaining 5%. 	Tumor histology was coded according to the International Classification of Diseases for Oncology.</p> 	<p>Of the eligible subjects, in the original analysis, 183 were excluded for issues related to genotyping quality control and 337 	subjects were excluded with incomplete phenotype data resulting in a final dataset of 5739 lung cancer cases and 5848 controls. 	After the further exclusion of 47 individuals because of informed consent issues and 22 individuals for QC reasons, the dataset 	released in dbGap and caBIG includes 5699 cases and 5818 controls.</p> 	<p>The subjects included in the original analysis as reported in Landi et al., AJHG 2009, by study: 	<table border="1"> 	<tr> 	<td></td> 	<td>Cases</td> 	<td>Controls</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>EAGLE</td> 	<td>1920</td> 	<td>1979</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>ATBC</td> 	<td>1732</td> 	<td>1271</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>PLCO</td> 	<td>1390</td> 	<td>1924</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>CSP-II</td> 	<td>697</td> 	<td>674</td> 	</tr> 	</table> 	</p> 	<p>The subjects included in the dataset to be released in dbGaP and caBIG, by study, after further exclusions for informed consent and QC reasons: 	<table border="1"> 	<tr> 	<td></td> 	<td>Cases</td> 	<td>Controls</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>EAGLE</td> 	<td>1917</td> 	<td>1978</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>ATBC</td> 	<td>1732</td> 	<td>1270</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>PLCO</td> 	<td>1355</td> 	<td>1896</td> 	</tr> 	<tr> 	<td>CSP-II</td> 	<td>695</td> 	<td>674</td> 	</tr> 	</table> 	</p> 	<p>Further details of genotyping exclusions are provided in Supplemental Table 2 of the AJHG Report (Landi et al.)</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19836008"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Lung Neoplasms"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Smoking"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Maria Teresa Landi</AttName>
			<Institution>Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Neil E. Caporaso</AttName>
			<Institution>Genetic Epidemiology Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Michael Thun</AttName>
			<Institution>American Cancer Society, Atlanta, GA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Demetrius Albanes</AttName>
			<Institution>Nutritional Epidemiology Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Jarmo Vitamo</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Chronic Disease Prevention, National Institute for Health and Welfare, Helsinki, Finland</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Pier Alberto Bertazzi</AttName>
			<Institution>Unit of Epidemiology, Dept. of Occupational and Environmental Health, University of Milan, Italy</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Statisticians">
			<AttName>Nilanjan Chatterjee</AttName>
			<Institution>Biostatistics Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Statisticians">
			<AttName>Zhaoming Ying</AttName>
			<Institution>Biostatistics Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Statisticians">
			<AttName>Kai Yu</AttName>
			<Institution>Biostatistics Branch, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Genomics">
			<AttName>Stephen Chanock</AttName>
			<Institution>Core Genotyping Facility, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Genomics">
			<AttName>Kevin Jacobs</AttName>
			<Institution>Core Genotyping Facility, Advanced Technology Program, SAIC-Frederick Inc., National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Frederick, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Genomics">
			<AttName>Meredith Yeager</AttName>
			<Institution>Core Genotyping Facility, Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Genomics">
			<AttName>Kimberly F. Doheny</AttName>
			<Institution>CIDR, Institute of Genetic Medicine, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Programmer">
			<AttName>William Wheeler</AttName>
			<Institution>Information Management Service, Inc.</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Coordination">
			<AttName>Margaret Tucker</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics,  National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="The Environment and Genetics in Lung Cancer Etiology (EAGLE)" url="http://eagle.cancer.gov"/>
		<Url name="The Alpha-Tocopherol, Beta-Carotene Cancer Prevention Study (ATBC)" url="http://atbcstudy.cancer.gov"/>
		<Url name="The Prostate, Lung, Colon, Ovary Screening Trial (PLCO)" url="http://prevention.cancer.gov/plco"/>
		<Url name="Cancer Prevention Study overview" url="http://www.cancer.org/docroot/RES/content/RES_6_2_Study_Overviews.asp"/>
		<Url name="Cancer Genetic Markers of Susceptibility (CGEMS) portal" url="http://cgems.cancer.gov/"/>
		<Url name="Core Genotyping Facility (CGF)" url="http://cgf.nci.nih.gov/"/>
		<Url name="CGF sample handling and quality control" url="http://cgf.nci.nih.gov/operations/sample-handling.html"/>
		<Url name="dbGaP" url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?Db=gap"/>
		<Url name="EIGENSTRAT" url="http://genepath.med.harvard.edu/~reich/EIGENSTRAT.htm"/>
		<Url name="ESPERR score" url="http://genome.ucsc.edu"/>
		<Url name="Genotype Library and Utilities (GLU)" url="http://code.google.com/p/glu-genetics/"/>
		<Url name="Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man (OMIM)" url="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Omim/"/>
		<Url name="SNP500Cancer" url="http://snp500cancer.nci.nih.gov/"/>
		<Url name="STRUCTURE" url="http://pritch.bsd.uchicago.edu/structure.html"/>
		<Url name="Tagzilla" url="http://code.google.com/p/glu-genetics"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>We conducted a GWAS in 5739 lung cancer cases and 5848 controls (National Cancer Institute [NCI] GWAS) to search for overall 	susceptibility variants and variants associated with specific histologic types and smoking status. We also conducted a 	meta-analysis of the NCI GWAS with summary data from ten additional studies, for a total of 13,300 primary lung cancer 	cases and 19,666 controls, all of European descent. Four of the ten studies provided information on histology for 	replication analyses; 3333 AD, 2589 SQ, and 1418 SC cases were analyzed overall.</p> 	<p>The 11,587 subjects in the NCI GWAS were drawn from one population-based case-control study and three cohort studies; 	specifically: the Environment and Genetics in Lung Cancer Etiology (EAGLE), a population-based case-control study 	including 2100 primary lung cancer cases and 2120 healthy controls enrolled in Italy between 2002 and 2005; the 	Alpha-Tocopherol, Beta-Carotene Cancer Prevention Study (ATBC), a randomized primary prevention trial 	including 29,133 male smokers enrolled in Finland between 1985 and 1993; the Prostate, Lung, Colon, Ovary Screening Trial (PLCO), 	a randomized trial including 150,000 individuals enrolled in ten U.S. study centers between 1992 and 2001; and the 	Cancer Prevention Study II Nutrition Cohort (CPS-II), including over 183,000 subjects enrolled by the 	American Cancer Society between 1992 and 2001 across all U.S. states. Analyses stratified by histology in the 	NCI GWAS included 1730 AD cases, 1400 SQ cases, 678 SC cases, and groups of other histological types or of mixed histologies. 	These studies were approved by the individual institutional review boards of each location, and each subject gave his or 	her informed consent for participation. In the PLCO study, 47 individuals gave permission to participate only in studies 	involving lung cancer, and thus have been excluded from the dataset released on dbGaP and caBIG.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="CADM" longName="Cancer in all age groups, other diseases in adults only, and methods"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="SLD" longName="Research related to lung disease or smoking"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>CGEMS</DacName>
      <DacFullName>Cancer Genetic Markers of Susceptibility (CGEMS) DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>NCI_CGEMS_DAC@mail.nih.gov </DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacFax>301-480-3915</DacFax>
      <DacUrl>http://grants.nih.gov/grants/gwas</DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000336.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
               http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000336.v1.p1
            </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000336.v1.p1" FileName="LungDUC_rev012110.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Cancer in all age groups, other diseases in adults only, and methods</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>CADM</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The informed consent document signed by the study participants included in the genome-wide association study (GWAS) of lung cancer risk allows use of these data by investigators for discovery and hypothesis generation in the investigation of the genetic contributions to cancer in all age groups and other diseases in adults only, as well as development of novel analytical approaches for GWAS.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>Research related to lung disease or smoking</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>SLD</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the dataset is limited to scientific genetic research related to the etiology, molecular basis, and outcome of lung disease and smoking.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>
  <Documents>
    <Document phd="phd003533.1" type="protocol" createDate="2011-04-20" modDate="2011-04-20" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd003533.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000336.v1.p1&amp;phd=3533">
      <OrigName>Methods Lung Cancer FINAL.docx</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>Lung Cancer Genome-Wide Association Scan Methods</DisplayName>
      <Description>Lung Cancer Genome-Wide Association Scan Methods</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
  </Documents>



</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
