<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000633.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000633.v1.p1" createDate="2013-06-27" modDate="2013-11-13">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Leopoldo Nicolas Segal, PhD</td><td>New York University, School of Medicine, New York, NY, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>UL1 TR000038</td><td>National Center for the Advancement of Translational Science, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Enrichment of Lung Microbiome Associated with Pulmonary Inflammation</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Enrichment of Lung Microbiome with Supraglottic Taxa which is Associated with Increased Pulmonary Inflammation</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Cross-Sectional</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p><b>Background</b>: The lung microbiome of healthy individuals frequently harbors oral organisms. Despite evidence that micro-aspiration is commonly associated with smoking-related lung diseases, the effects of lung microbiome enrichment with upper airway taxa on inflammation has not been studied. We hypothesize that the presence of oral microorganisms in the lung microbiome is associated with enhanced pulmonary inflammation.</p> <p><b>Methods</b>: We sampled bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) from the lower airways of 29 asymptomatic subjects (9 never-smokers, 14 former-smokers and 6 current-smokers). We quantified, amplified, and sequenced 16S rRNA genes from BAL samples by qPCR and 454 sequencing. Pulmonary inflammation was assessed by exhaled nitric oxide (eNO), BAL lymphocytes and neutrophils.</p> <p><b>Results</b>: BAL had lower total 16S than supraglottic samples and higher than saline background. Bacterial communities in the lower airway clustered in two distinct groups that we designated as pneumotypes. The rRNA gene concentration and microbial community of the first pneumotype was similar to that of the saline background. The second pneumotype had higher rRNA gene concentration and higher relative abundance of supraglottic-characteristic taxa (SCT), such as Veillonella and Prevotella, and we called it pneumotypeSCT. Smoking had no effect on pneumotype allocation, alpha or beta diversity. PneumotypeSCT was associated with higher BAL lymphocyte-count (p = 0.007), BAL neutrophil-count (p = 0.034) and eNO (p = 0.022).</p> <p><b>Conclusion</b>: A pneumotype with high relative abundance of supraglottic-characteristic taxa is associated with enhanced subclinical lung inflammation. </p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Pneumonia"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Leopoldo Nicolas Segal, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>New York University, School of Medicine, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>UL1 TR000038</AttName>
			<Institution>National Center for the Advancement of Translational Science, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="HMB-IRB" longName="Health/Medical/Biomedical (IRB)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000633.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000633.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000633.v1.p1" FileName="suid9682.draft_duc.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Health/Medical/Biomedical (IRB)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HMB-IRB</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Full or expedited IRB approval is required.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
