<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs001008.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs001008.v1.p1" createDate="2015-10-20" modDate="2016-02-24">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Lynne Wagenknecht</td><td>Wake Forest University School of Medicine, University of North Carolina, Winston-Salem, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>HL060944</td><td>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>GUARDIAN: IRAS FAMILY STUDY (IRASFS)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>GUARDIAN: The Insulin Resistance Atherosclerosis Family Study (IRASFS)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Family</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>TThe IRAS Family Study was a family study designed to examine the genetic and epidemiologic basis of glucose homeostasis traits and abdominal adiposity. Briefly, self-reported Mexican pedigrees were recruited in San Antonio, TX and San Luis Valley, CO. Probands with large families were recruited from the initial non-family-based IRAS Study, which was modestly enriched for impaired glucose tolerance and T2D. GUARDIAN includes 1,024 individuals in 88 pedigrees from the IRAS Family Study. Insulin sensitivity was obtained by FSIGT.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Probands for the IRAS Family Study were generally recruited from the parent IRAS study. Criteria for selection were based on reported family size but not on affection (diabetes) status. The minimum pedigree structure to be considered potentially eligible included four full siblings and five natural children. Individual family members were excluded if they were adopted or were less than 18 years of age. </p> <p>In addition, individuals were excluded from participation in particular components of the protocol if they were deemed to have conditions which would place the participant at undue risk, interfere with the measurement of insulin resistance, or jeopardize the validity of self-reported data. Presence of these conditions resulted in complete exclusion or partial exams. These conditions included:</p> <ol> <li>Current insulin treatment</li> <li>Heart failure</li> <li>Decompensated emphysema or chronic lung disease</li> <li>Current shortness of breath or pulmonary obstructive disease</li> <li>Crescendo angina</li> <li>Cancer, other than skin cancer, for which the person is currently being treated</li> <li>Seizure disorder or epilepsy</li> <li>Kidney dialysis, transplant, or renal failure</li> <li>A serious illness within the last 6 months (e.g., heart attack, stroke, or major surgery)</li> <li>Treatment with steroids in the past 6 months</li> <li>Pregnancy or breast feeding</li> <li>Breast cancer treated with surgery or radiation</li> <li>Obvious mental disability as noted in the screening interview.</li> </ol> <p>A subset of IRAS Family Study participants were included in the genotyping study: Hispanics only; without diabetes; with insulin sensitivity obtained by frequently sampled intravenous glucose tolerance test, and providing consent for genetic studies.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="12684185"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="25524916"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Insulin Resistance"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Lynne Wagenknecht</AttName>
			<Institution>Wake Forest University School of Medicine, University of North Carolina, Winston-Salem, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>HL060944</AttName>
			<Institution>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The IRAS Family Study was established in 1999 by the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute (NHLBI). The IRAS Family Study cohort of 1856 participants was initially recruited in 1999-2002 from three US communities. Hispanic families. A follow-up examination was conducted in 2005 - 2006 with a 79% response rate.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-DHD-IRB-NPU-MDS-RD" longName="Disease-Specific (Diabetes and Heart Disease, IRB, NPU, MDS, RD)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs001008.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs001008.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs001008.v1.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Diabetes and Heart Disease, IRB, NPU, MDS, RD)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-DHD-IRB-NPU-MDS-RD</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Diabetes and Heart Disease and related disorders.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).
Use of this data is limited to research that pertains to diabetes, obesity, heart disease and related conditions.  Examples of related conditions are sleep disorders or inflammation.  Examples of conditions not related are schizophrenia or motor vehicle accident.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
