<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000366.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000366.v1.p1" createDate="2011-06-02" modDate="2011-10-26">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Martin H. Steinberg</td><td>Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>R01 HL087681</td><td>National Heart, Lung, Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>NHLBI: Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease (CSSCD)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>NHLBI: Genetic modifiers of sickle cell anemia severity and fetal hemoglobin expression in the Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease (CSSCD)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Longitudinal</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Phenotypic heterogeneity is characteristic of sickle cell anemia, a Mendelian disorder caused by      homozygosity for the sickle HBB gene (glu6val). Patients have different rates of hemolysis/vasculopathy      and viscosity/vasoocclusion-related complications. These complications account for a substantial reduction      in life expectancy. In 1994, the median life expectancy for men and women with sickle cell anemia was 42      and 48 years, respectively, and despite many advances in care, the annual mortality still approaches 4%.      Fetal hemoglobin (HbF) is one of the most studied markers of severity of sickle cell anemia, and detailed      longitudinal measurements were taken on subjects enrolled in the Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell      Disease (CSSCD). Cubic root transformation of the median values from follow-up in 848 African American      subjects is the phenotype data used in the GWAS of fetal hemoglobin. The analysis was adjusted by sex.      Details are in Solovieff et al., Blood 2010 [PMID:      <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20018918" target="_blank">20018918</a>].</p>     <p>To integrate individual disease complications into a comprehensive measure of severity, we developed      a model of the associations among clinical and laboratory variables that scored disease severity as the      risk of death within 5 years. This network was developed using data obtained from more than 3,400 subjects      from the CSSCD, and its accuracy was validated in two unrelated sets of sickle cell patients. Recently,      the network was also validated in a small European cohort of patients with sickle cell anemia. We used      extreme values of disease severity as cases and control in the GWAS of severity of sickle cell anemia.      We conducted the GWAS in 1,265 patients with either "severe" (177) or "mild" disease (1088) based on      a network model of disease severity. Details are in Sebastiani et al. Am J Hematol, 2010 [PMID:      <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20029952" target="_blank">20029952</a>].</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Refer to original study</p>     <p>Full documentation of the study is available from:      <a href="https://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/csscd/" target="_blank">https://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/csscd/</a>.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21143920"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20872960"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20029952"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20018918"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19569043"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19151898"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19077279"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18729854"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18691915"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18544690"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18461136"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18194558"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17918249"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17600133"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17034027"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16886151"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16681647"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16567954"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15985542"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15877729"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15784727"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15778708"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15638863"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="12673837"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="11480781"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="10099145"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="7993409"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Sickle Cell Anemia"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Martin H. Steinberg</AttName>
			<Institution>Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01 HL087681</AttName>
			<Institution>National Heart, Lung, Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>no</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease (CSSCD)" url="https://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/csscd/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>A cooperative group for the study of sickle cell disease was formed in 1977 at the National Institutes      of Health (NIH) to organize a multicenter, prospective study of the clinical course of sickle cell disease      in patients from the newborn period through adulthood. The primary motivation for the study was the lack      of systematically obtained knowledge about this prevalent and costly hereditary disease. Although the      molecular and genetic features of sickle cell disease have been known for years and many of its      manifestations have been recognized, the clinical course from birth to death is not well understood.      This is largely due to the variable degree of severity, the variability of the many manifestations,      and the complexity of the interaction of the disease process with other health-related events. Therefore,      information obtained was largely anecdotal, retrospective in nature, and lacking statistical validity.      There were many unanswered questions about this disease.</p>     <p>In 1978, the Division of Blood Diseases and Resources established a multi-institutional study, the      Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease, to answer these questions. During the first 10 years of the      study (October 1978 through September 1988), 4,085 patients from 23 clinical centers within the      United States were enrolled in the study. Patient entry was completed in 1981 for all except patients      less than 6 months of age who continued to enter the study through September 1988. Protocol requirements      for patients during the original study varied depending on age, phenotype, and time period. In 1989,      a 5-year study (Phase 2) to continue follow-up of two patient groups (the infant cohort (patients      entered at &lt; 6 months of age in Phase 1) and adults 35 years of age and older) was initiated.      During Phase 2, the objectives for the original infant cohort were 1) to identify factors related to      overall disease severity, 2) to determine the onset of early organ damage, and 3) to examine risk      factors contributing to certain complications and outcomes. The primary areas of interest for this      cohort were the brain and lungs. A 5-year follow-up study (Phase 3) was initiated in 1994 to continue      collecting these data to allow for longer longitudinal evaluation of factors affecting overall disease      severity, brain abnormalities, neurocognitive and psychosocial functioning, and pulmonary dysfunction.</p>     <p>Full documentation of the study is available from:      <a href="https://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/csscd/" target="_blank">https://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/csscd/</a>.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="100" shortName="Analysis" longName="Analysis only"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>nhlbigeneticdata@nhlbi.nih.gov</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacFax>(301) 480-1455</DacFax>
      <DacUrl>http://grants.nih.gov/grants/gwas</DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000366.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
               http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000366.v1.p1
            </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000366.v1.p1" FileName="CSSCD_NHLBIDUC_2012-05-01.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The informed consent document signed by the Study Participants allows use of these data results by investigators employed by non-profit and for-profit organizations. This consent group does not require IRB approval.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>

<Analyses>
	<Analysis pha="3105" genomeBuild="37.1" snpBuild="132" analysisType="">
		<Description>The analysis describes a genome wide association study of fetal hemoglobin in 846 African Americans with sickle cell anemia from the Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease. Genotype data were generated with the microarray Illumina 610. Median values of repeated measures of fetal hemoglobin were analyzed after a cubic root transformation.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="599011" snpBatchId="1048904">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina Human610-Quadv1_B chip</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Human610-Quadv1_B</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
</Analyses>

</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
