<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000930.v3.p1" parentStudy="phs000930.v3.p1" createDate="2016-03-08" modDate="2016-03-08">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Bruce Psaty, PhD</td><td>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>5R01HL105756-03</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>CHARGE (Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>CHARGE (Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology) Consortium Summary Results from Genomic Studies</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Nested Case-Control</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Family</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Longitudinal</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>GWAS have successfully identified genetic loci associated with a variety of conditions such as type 2 diabetes and coronary disease. The large number of statistical tests required in GWAS has posed a special challenge because few studies that have DNA and high-quality phenotype data are sufficiently large to provide adequate statistical power for detecting small to modest effect sizes. Even before the era of GWAS, the requirement for large sample sizes and the importance of replication have served as powerful incentives for collaboration. Meta-analyses combining summary data from multiple sources have improved the ability to detect new loci. The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology (CHARGE) Consortium was formed to facilitate GWAS meta-analyses and replication among multiple large and well-phenotyped cohort studies. The design of the CHARGE Consortium was formed initially from 5 prospective cohort studies from the United States and Europe: the Age, Gene/Environment Susceptibility (AGES) - Reykjavik Study, the <a href="./study.cgi?study_id=phs000280">Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) Study</a>, the <a href="./study.cgi?study_id=phs000287">Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS)</a>, the <a href="./study.cgi?study_id=phs000007">Framingham Heart Study (FHS)</a>, and the Rotterdam Study (RS). Additional studies have expanded the CHARGE consortium based upon the phenotypes and willingness to share information across the research community.</p> <p>In order to facilitate investigators across the world to examine relationships between phenotypes and genetic markers within CHARGE published reports, an open site is made available on dbGaP that provides the rsID and the p-value for inspection. Access to detailed summary statistics (including minor allele frequency, odds ratio/effect size) requires approval of a Data Access Request (DAR).</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>To be included in a CHARGE study, a cohort has to provide summary statistics for meta-analyses according to the specifications of the CHARGE Working Group. The summary statistics are based upon an agreed-upon analytic plan that provides guidance for all protocols and software.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20031568"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19630823"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23874508"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Cardiovascular Diseases"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Cerebrovascular Disorders"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Risk Factors"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Bruce Psaty, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>5R01HL105756-03</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>no</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="CHARGE Consortium" url="http://www.chargeconsortium.com"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>A major goal of the CHARGE Consortium is to collaboratively produce a series of jointly coordinated, high-impact publications that describes the collaborative results of genome-wide association scans (GWAS) for a number of cardiovascular, lung, blood and aging phenotypes. The focal point of the design, analysis, interpretation and publication of research results for each specific phenotype is one of several collaborative phenotype Working Groups (WGs) that have been convened by the CHARGE Research Steering Committee (RSC). One analytic strategy that is being undertaken by many of the CHARGE WGs is to conduct a meta-analysis of GWAS results for single phenotypes common to multiple CHARGE cohorts. The actions of members of CHARGE WGs from each of the individual CHARGE cohorts and other collaborating cohorts should support this research goal. The principles are meant to encourage collaborating investigators to conduct their research in the spirit of collaboration and trust and with transparency regarding potentially sensitive issues about the use of shared data prior to publication.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="100" shortName="Analysis" longName="Analysis only"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000930.v3.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000930.v3.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000930.v3.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
The NHLBI DAC recognizes that the subject matter represents statistics from meta-analyses of multiple cohorts; the summary results should not be used to identify individuals or groups, and should be used only for the evaluation of SNP associations with the phenotypes provided.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>

<Analyses>
	<Analysis pha="3869" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. <p>Association analysis between genotype and alpha-linoleic acid (ALA) was done separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  All analyses  used robust standard errors. For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="934940" snpBatchId="52074">
			<Vendor>Affy</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_viewBatch.cgi?sbid=52074</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Affy1M</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3870" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. <p>Association analysis between genotype and docosahexaenoic acid  (DHA) was done separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  All analyses  used robust standard errors. For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="934940" snpBatchId="52074">
			<Vendor>Affy</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_viewBatch.cgi?sbid=52074</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Affy1M</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3871" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype.<p>Association analysis between genotype and docosahexaenoic acid  (DHA) was done separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  All analyses  used robust standard errors. For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.<p></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="934940" snpBatchId="52074">
			<Vendor>Affy</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_viewBatch.cgi?sbid=52074</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Affy1M</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3872" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype.<p>Association analysis between genotype and eicosapentaenoic acid  (EPA) was done separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  All analyses  used robust standard errors. For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="934940" snpBatchId="52074">
			<Vendor>Affy</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_viewBatch.cgi?sbid=52074</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Affy1M</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3873" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. 
<p>Association analysis between genotype and white blood cell (WBC) count was conducted separately within each participating  cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  Meta-analyses were performed using inverse-variance weighted fixed-effects models to combine beta coefficients and standard errors from study level regression results for each SNP to derive a combined p-value. Study level results were  corrected for genomic inflation factors (&#955;GC) by incorporating study specific &#955;GC estimates into the scaling of the standard errors (SE) of the regression coefficients. Meta-analyses were implemented using METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3874" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. 
<p>Association analysis between genotype and basophil count was conducted separately within each participating  cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  Meta-analyses were performed using inverse-variance weighted fixed-effects models to combine beta coefficients and standard errors from study level regression results for each SNP to derive a combined p-value. Study level results were  corrected for genomic inflation factors (&#955;GC) by incorporating study specific &#955;GC estimates into the scaling of the standard errors (SE) of the regression coefficients. Meta-analyses were implemented using METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3875" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. 
<p>Association analysis between genotype and eosinophil count was conducted separately within each participating  cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  Meta-analyses were performed using inverse-variance weighted fixed-effects models to combine beta coefficients and standard errors from study level regression results for each SNP to derive a combined p-value. Study level results were  corrected for genomic inflation factors (&#955;GC) by incorporating study specific &#955;GC estimates into the scaling of the standard errors (SE) of the regression coefficients. Meta-analyses were implemented using METAL.<p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3876" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. 
<p>Association analysis between genotype and lymphocyte count was conducted separately within each participating  cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  Meta-analyses were performed using inverse-variance weighted fixed-effects models to combine beta coefficients and standard errors from study level regression results for each SNP to derive a combined p-value. Study level results were  corrected for genomic inflation factors (&#955;GC) by incorporating study specific &#955;GC estimates into the scaling of the standard errors (SE) of the regression coefficients. Meta-analyses were implemented using METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3877" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. 
<p>Association analysis between genotype and monocyte count was conducted separately within each participating  cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  Meta-analyses were performed using inverse-variance weighted fixed-effects models to combine beta coefficients and standard errors from study level regression results for each SNP to derive a combined p-value. Study level results were  corrected for genomic inflation factors (&#955;GC) by incorporating study specific &#955;GC estimates into the scaling of the standard errors (SE) of the regression coefficients. Meta-analyses were implemented using METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3878" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. 
<p>Association analysis between genotype and neutrophil count was conducted separately within each participating  cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  Meta-analyses were performed using inverse-variance weighted fixed-effects models to combine beta coefficients and standard errors from study level regression results for each SNP to derive a combined p-value. Study level results were  corrected for genomic inflation factors (&#955;GC) by incorporating study specific &#955;GC estimates into the scaling of the standard errors (SE) of the regression coefficients. Meta-analyses were implemented using METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3879" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. <p>Association analysis between genotype and common carotid IMT was done separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3880" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. Although originally founded by five cohort studies (Age, Gene, Environment, Susceptibility Study - Reykjavik (AGES), Atherosclerosis Risk in Communities (ARIC) study, Cardiovascular Health Study (CHS), Framingham Heart Study, Rotterdam Study, CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype.<p> Association analysis between genotype and carotid plaque was done separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL</p>
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1069796" snpBatchId="52075">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 1</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_1</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="1062" snpBatchId="856524">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina 1M chip part 2</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ILMN1M_2</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3886" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of myocardial infarction (MI). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (ACE inhibitor) with respect to MI was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3887" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of myocardial infarction (MI). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (beta blocker) with respect to MI was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3888" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of myocardial infarction (MI). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (calcium channel blocker) with respect to MI was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3889" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of myocardial infarction (MI). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (thiazide diuretics) with respect to MI was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each </Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3890" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of cardiovascular disease (CVD). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (ACE inhibitor) with respect to CVD was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3891" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of cardiovascular disease (CVD). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (beta blocker) with respect to CVD was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3892" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of cardiovascular disease (CVD). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (calcium channel blocker) with respect to CVD was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3893" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of drug-gene interactions on the outcome of cardiovascular disease (CVD). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 9 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with treated hypertension. Association analysis between genotype and anti-hypertensive medication (thiazide diuretics) with respect to CVD was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3895" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of FEV1 as a mesasure of severity of obstructive lung disease. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 5 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with pulmonary function (FEV1, FVC) measures. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1 was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3896" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of FEV1 as a mesasure of severity of airflow obstruction  in those participants who reported as &#34;ever (current or former) smokers&#34;. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 5 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with pulmonary function (FEV1, FVC) measures. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1 was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3897" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on FEV1 as a mesasure of severity of airflow obstruction in those participants who reported as &#34;never smokers&#34;. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 5 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with pulmonary function (FEV1, FVC) measures. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1 was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3898" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of FEV1/FVC as a mesasure of airflow obstruction independent of lung size. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 5 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with pulmonary function (FEV1, FVC) measures. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1/FVC was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3899" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of FEV1/FVC as a mesasure of airflow obstruction independent of lung size in those participants who reported as  &#34;ever (current or former) smokers &#34;. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 5 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with pulmonary function (FEV1, FVC) measures. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1/FVC was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3900" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of FEV1/FVC as a mesasure of airflow obstruction independent of lung size in those participants who reported as &#34;never smokers &#34;. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 5 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with pulmonary function (FEV1, FVC) measures. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1/FVC was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3901" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP and SNP-smoking interaction effects on the outcome of FEV1 as a measure of severity of obstructive lung disease. Smoking in this analysis was defined as a dichotomy (ever/never). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 19 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with FEV1  and smoking data. Association analysis between genotype and genotype-smoking interaction with respect to FEV1 was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3902" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP and SNP-smoking interaction effects on the outcome of FEV1 as a measure of severity of obstructive lung disease. Smoking in this analysis was defined as a continuous variable (pack-years). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 19 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with FEV1 and smoking data. Association analysis between genotype and genotype-smoking interaction with respect to FEV1 was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL. </Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3903" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP and SNP-smoking interaction effects on the outcome of FEV1/FVC as a measure of obstructive lung disease independent of lung size. Smoking in this analysis was defined as a dichotomy (ever/never). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 19 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with FEV1/FVC  and smoking data. Association analysis between genotype and genotype-smoking interaction with respect to FEV1/FVC was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3904" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP and SNP-smoking interaction effects on the outcome of FEV1/FVC as a measure of obstructive lung disease independent of lung size. Smoking in this analysis was defined as a continuous variable (pack-years). The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 19 studies with GWAS data with European ancestry participants with FEV1/FVC  and smoking data. Association analysis between genotype and genotype-smoking interaction with respect to FEV1/FVC was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3905" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of forced expiratory volume at 1 second (FEV1) in cohorts of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 48,201 subjects from 23 studies with GWAS data. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1 was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>inverse variance weighted meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3906" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of forced vital capacity (FVC) in cohorts of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 48,201 subjects from 23 studies with GWAS data. Association analysis between genotype and FVC was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>inverse variance weighted meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3907" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the ratio of forced expiratory volume at 1 second to forced vital capacity (FEV1/FVC) in cohorts of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 48,201 subjects from 23 studies with GWAS data. Association analysis between genotype and FEV1/FVC was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>inverse variance weighted meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3910" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of incident CHD in the five prospective cohort studies of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 24,024 subjects with 2406 incident CHD cases  with GWAS data. Association analysis between genotype and CHD was conducted separately within each study according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3911" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of incident MI in the five prospective cohort studies of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 24,024 subjects with 1570 incident MI cases  with GWAS data. Association analysis between genotype and MI was conducted separately within each study according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3912" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of fibrinogen level in cohorts of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in 120,246 subjects from 34 studies with GWAS data. Association analysis between genotype and log-transformed fibrinogen levell was conducted separately within each study cohort according to a pre-specified plan.  For each SNP, GWAS-specific results were combined using inverse-variance weighted meta-analysis in METAL.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3913" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the continuous variable FEV1, taken at multiple time points within each of the 14 cohorts, with measurements in 27,249 adults  of European ancestry. The GWAS meta-analysis was conducted in those with repeated measurements using a mixed effects model. Each cohort performed GWAS using a linear mixed effects model with a random intercept and random slope, with fixed effects for time, SNP, SNPxtime interaction, and baseline age, sex, standing height, smoking pattern during follow-up, smokingxtime interaction, baseline smoking pack-years, study site (as needed) and principal components of ancestry (as needed).</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3914" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of airflow obstruction (a key pathophysiologic characteristic of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, COPD) in 15 population-based cohorts with 32,875 subjects of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in those with airflow obstruction defined as FEV1 and FEV1/FVC both less than the lower limit of normal, with unaffected  subjects defined as FEV1, FVC, and FEV1/FVC all above the lower limit of normal. Logistic regression models were adjusted for current and former smoking, pack-years of smoking, age, sex, standing height, center/cohort as needed, and principal components for genetic ancestry (as needed). Genome-wide imputation and analysis were performed by cohort investigators, and genome-wide and regional meta-analyses were performed using METAL software. FIve discovery analyses were performed - all cohorts (including ever and never smokers), ever smokers, never smokers, asthma-free participants, and those with FEV1 &#60; 65% predicted (more severe airflow obstruction).</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3915" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of airflow obstruction (a key pathophysiologic characteristic of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, COPD) in 15 population-based cohorts with 32,875 subjects of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in those with airflow obstruction defined as FEV1 and FEV1/FVC both less than the lower limit of normal, with unaffected  subjects defined as FEV1, FVC, and FEV1/FVC all above the lower limit of normal. Logistic regression models were adjusted for current and former smoking, pack-years of smoking, age, sex, standing height, center/cohort as needed, and principal components for genetic ancestry (as needed). Genome-wide imputation and analysis were performed by cohort investigators, and genome-wide and regional meta-analyses were performed using METAL software. FIve discovery analyses were performed - all cohorts (including ever and never smokers), ever smokers, never smokers, asthma-free participants, and those with FEV1 &#60; 65% predicted (more severe airflow obstruction).</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3916" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of airflow obstruction (a key pathophysiologic characteristic of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, COPD) in 15 population-based cohorts with 32,875 subjects of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in those with airflow obstruction defined as FEV1 and FEV1/FVC both less than the lower limit of normal, with unaffected  subjects defined as FEV1, FVC, and FEV1/FVC all above the lower limit of normal. Logistic regression models were adjusted for current and former smoking, pack-years of smoking, age, sex, standing height, center/cohort as needed, and principal components for genetic ancestry (as needed). Genome-wide imputation and analysis were performed by cohort investigators, and genome-wide and regional meta-analyses were performed using METAL software. FIve discovery analyses were performed - all cohorts (including ever and never smokers), ever smokers, never smokers, asthma-free participants, and those with FEV1 &#60; 65% predicted (more severe airflow obstruction).</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3917" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of airflow obstruction (a key pathophysiologic characteristic of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, COPD) in 15 population-based cohorts with 32,875 subjects of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in those with airflow obstruction defined as FEV1 and FEV1/FVC both less than the lower limit of normal, with unaffected  subjects defined as FEV1, FVC, and FEV1/FVC all above the lower limit of normal. Logistic regression models were adjusted for current and former smoking, pack-years of smoking, age, sex, standing height, center/cohort as needed, and principal components for genetic ancestry (as needed). Genome-wide imputation and analysis were performed by cohort investigators, and genome-wide and regional meta-analyses were performed using METAL software. FIve discovery analyses were performed - all cohorts (including ever and never smokers), ever smokers, never smokers, asthma-free participants, and those with FEV1 &#60; 65% predicted (more severe airflow obstruction).</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3918" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The Cohorts for Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epimiology (CHARGE) consortium was formed to facilitate genome-wide association study meta-analyses and replication among large, well-phenotyped cohort studies. CHARGE has incorporated many genomic and phenotypic data from other cohorts, depending on the phenotype. The basic design was estimation of SNP effects on the outcome of airflow obstruction (a key pathophysiologic characteristic of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, COPD) in 15 population-based cohorts with 32,875 subjects of European ancestry. The discovery meta-analysis was conducted in those with airflow obstruction defined as FEV1 and FEV1/FVC both less than the lower limit of normal, with unaffected  subjects defined as FEV1, FVC, and FEV1/FVC all above the lower limit of normal. Logistic regression models were adjusted for current and former smoking, pack-years of smoking, age, sex, standing height, center/cohort as needed, and principal components for genetic ancestry (as needed). Genome-wide imputation and analysis were performed by cohort investigators, and genome-wide and regional meta-analyses were performed using METAL software. FIve discovery analyses were performed - all cohorts (including ever and never smokers), ever smokers, never smokers, asthma-free participants, and those with FEV1 &#60; 65% predicted (more severe airflow obstruction).</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait meta-analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="2716412" snpBatchId="">
			<Vendor>multichip</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>marker set used by ICBP</VendorURL>
			<Platform>ICBP_Multichip_Imputation</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
</Analyses>

</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
