<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000587.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000587.v1.p1" createDate="2013-01-29" modDate="2013-09-16">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Sekar Kathiresan</td><td>Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA 02142, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>John J.P. Kastelein</td><td>Department of Vascular Medicine, Academic Medical Center, Amsterdam, 1105AZ, The Netherlands</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Sequencing Center</td><td>Stacey Gabriel, PhD</td><td>Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Sequencing Center</td><td>Deborah Nickerson, PhD</td><td>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>RC2 HL102925</td><td>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>NHLBI GO-ESP: Family Studies (Mendelian Lipid Disorders)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>NHLBI GO-ESP: Family Studies (Mendelian Lipid Disorders)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case Set</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The NHLBI "Grand Opportunity" Exome Sequencing Project (GO-ESP), a signature project of the NHLBI Recovery Act investment, was designed to identify genetic variants in coding regions (exons) of the human genome (the "exome") that are associated with heart, lung and blood diseases. These and related diseases that are of high impact to public health and individuals from diverse racial and ethnic groups will be studied. These data may help researchers understand the causes of disease, contributing to better ways to prevent, diagnose, and treat diseases, as well as determine whether to tailor prevention and treatments to specific populations. This could lead to more effective treatments and reduce the likelihood of side effects. GO-ESP is comprised of five collaborative components: 3 cohort consortia - HeartGO, LungGO, and WHISP - and 2 sequencing centers - BroadGO and SeattleGO.</p> <p>In this study, we seek to identify the genetic cause of two monogenic lipid disorders-severe hypercholesterolemia and familial hypoalphalipoproteinemia. Monogenic severe hypercholesterolemia is clinically characterized by elevated total and low-density lipoprotein (LDL) cholesterol levels in plasma. Elevated LDL-cholesterol levels lead to excessive deposition of cholesterol in arterial walls, which eventually results in accelerated atherosclerosis and premature cardiovascular disease (CVD). Monogenic hypercholesterolemia has a prevalence of approximately one in 500 individuals, making it one of the most common inherited disorders. To date, mutations in the LDL receptor (LDLR) ligand-binding domains of APOB and PCSK9 have been shown to cause hypercholesterolemia. While mutations in these genes can explain a large percentage of clinically diagnosed patients, the underlying molecular determinant in a substantial fraction of patients remains unknown.</p> <p>Familial hypoalphalipoproteinemia (low HDL-C) is defined by an HDL-C below the age- and sex- specific 10th percentile. ABCA1, LCAT, and APOA1 are known to cause familial hypoalphalipoproteinemia. We hypothesize that: (1) additional novel genes responsible for Mendelian forms of low HDL-C exist; and (2) the causal gene and mutation(s) in each family may be discovered with exome analysis of just a few affected individuals in each pedigree.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Inclusion criteria for high LDL-cholesterol case: LDL-cholesterol levels above 95th percentile matched for sex and age.</p> <p>Exclusion criteria were mutations in the genes APOB, LDLR, and PCSK9.</p> <p>Inclusion criteria for low HDL-cholesterol case: HDL-cholesterol below the age- and sex- specific 10th percentile</p> <p>Exclusion criteria were mutations in the genes ABCA1, LCAT, and APOA1.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Hyperlipoproteinemia Type II"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Hypoalphalipoproteinemias"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Sekar Kathiresan</AttName>
			<Institution>Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA 02142, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>John J.P. Kastelein</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Vascular Medicine, Academic Medical Center, Amsterdam, 1105AZ, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Sequencing Center">
			<AttName>Stacey Gabriel, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Broad Institute, Cambridge, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Sequencing Center">
			<AttName>Deborah Nickerson, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>RC2 HL102925</AttName>
			<Institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>RC2 HL102926</AttName>
			<Institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="NHLBI Grand Opportunity Exome Sequencing Project (ESP)" url="https://esp.gs.washington.edu/drupal/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p> <ol> <li>Autosomal Dominant Hypercholesterolemia</li> <p>In the Netherlands, patients with suspected Autosomal Dominant Hypercholesterolemia (ADH) are referred to 64 Lipid Clinics evenly distributed over the country. DNA samples of these patients are routinely analyzed for the presence of LDLR, APOB, and PCSK9 mutations in order to confirm the clinical diagnosis of ADH. Screening of the LDLR gene in clinically diagnosed ADH patients results in approximately 67% of the cases in a molecular diagnosis. Approximately 10% of high cholesterol levels can be explained by mutations in APOB. In less than 1% a mutation in PCSK9 explains the ADH phenotype in the Dutch population.</p> <li>Familial Hypoalphalipoproteinemia</li> <p>The criteria for the diagnosis of hypo-alphalipoproteinemia (OMIM #604091) or low HDL-C included a plasma level of HDL-C and APOA1 below 5th percentile of the distribution in the population. Family members were sampled after a 12-hour fast and discontinuation of lipid-modifying medications for 4 weeks. Demographic and clinical information, medications, and lipoprotein profiles were determined on all subjects. DNA was isolated and sequencing was attempted for ABCA1, LCAT, and APOA1.</p> </ol> </p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-CLA" longName="Disease-Specific (Cardiovascular disease, lipoprotein metabolism disorders/atherosclerosis)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000587.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>3</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000587.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000587.v1.p1" FileName="Kastelein_Kathiresan_NHLBIDUC_July_24_2012-3_df.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Cardiovascular disease, lipoprotein metabolism disorders/atherosclerosis)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-CLA</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Cardiovascular disease, lipoprotein metabolism disorders/atherosclerosis.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
