<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000218.v15.p5" parentStudy="phs000218.v15.p5" createDate="2016-02-10" modDate="2016-04-05">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator (ALL Project Team)</td><td>Stephen P. Hunger, MD</td><td>University of Colorado Cancer Center, Denver, CO, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators (AML Project Team)</td><td>Soheil Meshinchi, MD, PhD</td><td>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators (AML Project Team)</td><td>Robert Arceci, MD, PhD</td><td>Children&#39;s Hospital, Phoenix, AZ, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator (NBL Project Team)</td><td>John M. Maris, MD</td><td>Children&#39;s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator (NBL Project Team)</td><td>Robert Seeger, MD</td><td>Children&#39;s Hospital of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>NCI TARGET: Therapeutically Applicable Research to Generate Effective Treatments</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>National Cancer Institute (NCI) TARGET: Therapeutically Applicable Research to Generate Effective Treatments</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The Therapeutically Applicable Research to Generate Effective Treatments (TARGET) Initiative seeks to accelerate research in novel marker and drug development, along with understanding the molecular basis of pediatric malignancy, through identification of genomic changes associated with the following childhood cancers:</p> <p> <ul> <li>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia (ALL) - A fast-growing type of blood cancer in which too many immature white blood cells are found in the blood and bone marrow.</li> <li>Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) - Another type of blood cancer marked by too many myeloblasts, an alternate type of immature white blood cell, are found in the blood and bone marrow.</li> <li>Neuroblastoma (NBL) - Cancer of cells of the sympathetic nervous system.</li> <li>Osteosarcoma (OS) - A cancer of the bone that primarily affects children and adolescents.</li> <li>Wilms&#39; Tumor (WT) - A cancer of cells in the kidney that can spread to the liver, lung and lymph nodes.</li> </ul> </p> <p>*Additional renal and AML tumors are being added to the TARGET Initiative (clear cell sarcoma of the kidney - CCSK, rhabdoid tumor - RT, and AML cases that fail to respond to standard treatment called induction - AML-IF), along with some sequencing of cell lines and xenografts including some that are being sequenced in conjunction with the NCI PPTP project (model systems substudy - MDLS). <i><font color="red">More information can be found about each TARGET subproject by following the links on the righthand side of this page.</font></i></p> <p>Together these cancers account for the majority of the more than 10,000 childhood cancer cases diagnosed in the United States each year.</p> <p>TARGET is employing a set of advanced and complementary genome analysis technologies, including large scale 2nd and 3rd generation genome sequencing, to strategically characterize alterations in both gene expression and in genomic structure (such as deletions and amplification) that are involved in childhood cancers. The goal of this coordinated effort is a comprehensive genomic and transcriptomic profile of each cancer. Integrated analysis of the TARGET data will identify those genes that are either altered in their expression level or mapped to the chromosome regions of deletion/amplification/translocation, as these genes represent strong candidates for therapeutic targeting. To learn more about the TARGET project, visit the website at <a href="http://ocg.cancer.gov/programs/target" target="_blank">http://ocg.cancer.gov/programs/target</a>.</p> <p>TARGET primary genomic sequencing datasets (controlled-access) and limited phenotype data (open-access) are available from this site. TARGET characterization data will be deposited into the TARGET Data Coordinating Center (DCC) database, while the sequence data is deposited either into the NCBI&#39;s trace repository or the sequence read archive (SRA). Comprehensive access to TARGET datasets, including molecular characterization (e.g. gene expression, copy number variation and epigenetics), fully annotated clinical information, and targeted sequencing linking tables, is available via the TARGET <a href="http://target.nci.nih.gov/dataMatrix/" target="_blank">Data Matrix</a>. <b><font color="red">Please see the TARGET Publication Guidelines at the <a href="http://ocg.cancer.gov/programs/target/target-publication-guidelines" target="_blank">OCG website</a> for updated details on sharing of any TARGET substudy data.</font></b></p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>TARGET employs stringent criteria for inclusion while focusing on primary untreated pediatric tumors. All cases included for TARGET must include a matched normal sample with a tumor specimen from the same patient. All samples used within TARGET are reviewed by a pathologist who confirms the accuracy of cancer diagnosis, as well as the presence of at least 70-80% tumor nuclei with no more than 20-30% necrotic tissue.</p> <p>Each cancer being studied has disease-specific inclusion and exclusion criteria for the cohorts being characterized and sequenced. Additional details can be found on the TARGET website, particularly within the TARGET <a href="http://target.nci.nih.gov/dataMatrix/" target="_blank">Data Matrix</a>.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19129520"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19470474"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20139093"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19880498"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20699438"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21680795"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22897847"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23212523"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23334666"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Neoplasms"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Neuroblastoma"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Osteosarcoma"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Wilms Tumor"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Clear Cell Sarcomas"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Rhabdoid Tumor"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Xenografts"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Children&#39;s Oncology Group (COG; Tissues for TARGET are collected as part of COG clinical and biological protocols)">
			<AttName>Peter C. Adamson, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Children&#39;s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (ALL Project Team)">
			<AttName>Stephen P. Hunger, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Colorado Cancer Center, Denver, CO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators (AML Project Team)">
			<AttName>Soheil Meshinchi, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators (AML Project Team)">
			<AttName>Robert Arceci, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Children&#39;s Hospital, Phoenix, AZ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (NBL Project Team)">
			<AttName>John M. Maris, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Children&#39;s Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (NBL Project Team)">
			<AttName>Robert Seeger, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Children&#39;s Hospital of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (NBL Project Team)">
			<AttName>Javed Khan, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (OS Project Team)">
			<AttName>Ching Lau, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Texas Children&#39;s Hospital, Houston, TX, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (OS Project Team)">
			<AttName>Paul Meltzer, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (Kidney Project Teams - WT, CCSK, RT)">
			<AttName>Elizabeth J. Perlman, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Ann and Robert H. Lurie Children&#39;s Hospital of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator (Cell Lines and Xenografts - PPTP)">
			<AttName>Peter Houghton, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>The Research Institute at Nationwide Children&#39;s Hospital, Columbus, OH, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="TARGET Data Matrix" url="http://target.nci.nih.gov/dataMatrix/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>Pediatric ALL was the first disease to be piloted for the TARGET initiative, which is jointly managed by the NCI Office of Cancer Genomics (OCG) and Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (CTEP). The study is run as a cooperative collaboration between investigators and management staff at NCI, Children&#39;s Oncology Group, University of Colorado Cancer Center, University of New Mexico Cancer Center, and St. Jude Children&#39;s Research Hospital.</p> <p> <table border="1"> <tr> <td valign="top" width="120">May, 2005</td> <td>NCI and the American Cancer Society co-sponsor "Childhood Cancer Targeted Therapeutics Workshop" that ultimately served as a basis for the conception of TARGET.</td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top" width="120">October, 2006</td> <td>TARGET project officially initiated.</td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top" width="120">January, 2009</td> <td>First publication of characterization and analysis of 221 ALL patients.</td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top" width="120">May, 2009</td> <td>Follow-up publication of additional genes involved in ALL treatment response.</td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top" width="120">September, 2009</td> <td>ARRA funding allows for expansion of TARGET pilot project to include three additional cancers.</td> </tr> <tr> <td valign="top" width="120">October, 2009<br/> November, 2009<br/> February, 2010<br/> July, 2010<br/> December, 2010<br/> June, 2011<br/> August, 2012<br/> December, 2012<br/> January, 2013 </td> <td>Follow-up publications of additional genes involved in poor outcome in pediatric ALL.</td> </tr> </table> </p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="PCR" longName="Pediatric Cancer Research"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000218.v15.p5_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000218.v15.p5
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000218.v15.p5" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Pediatric Cancer Research</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>PCR</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of protected TARGET datasets should be for research projects that can only be conducted using pediatric data (i.e., the research objectives cannot be accomplished using data from adults) and that have likely relevance to developing more effective treatments, diagnostic tests, or prognostic markers for childhood cancers. Applications proposing methods, software, or other tool development would not be considered acceptable uses of the data.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
