<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000346.v2.p2" parentStudy="phs000346.v2.p2" createDate="2014-08-18" modDate="2015-06-10">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Nathaniel Rothman</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Montserrat Garcia-Closas</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Debra Silverman</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Stephen Chanock</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Statistician</td><td>Nilanjan Chatterjee</td><td>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Cancer Genetic Markers of Susceptibility for Bladder Cancer (CGEMS Bladder)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genome-wide association study for Bladder Cancer Risk</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>This study funded by the National Cancer Institute (NCI) involves conducting a genome-wide association study of common genetic variants to identify markers of susceptibility to bladder cancer.</p> <p>This bladder GWAS has led to the discovery of three novel regions in the genome associated with bladder cancer risk. Cases were defined as individuals having histologically confirmed primary carcinoma of the urinary bladder, including carcinoma in situ (ICD-0-2 topography codes C67.0-C67.9 or ICD9 codes 188.1-188.9). Scan data were obtained from two case-control studies carried out in Spain and the United States (specifically, those in the Maine and Vermont components of the New England Bladder Cancer Study) and three prospective cohort studies in Finland and the United States (specifically Alpha-Tocopherol, Beta-Carotene Cancer Prevention Study, Prostate, Lung, Colorectal and Ovarian Cancer Screening Trial, and The American Cancer Society Cancer Prevention Study II Nutrition Cohort).</p> <p>We used data from 591,637 single nucleotide polymorphisms 3,532 affected individuals (cases) and 5,119 controls of European descent and replication including 8382 cases and 48275 controls from 16 studies. In a combined analysis, we identified three new regions associated with bladder cancer on chromosomes 22q13.1, 19q12 and 2q37.1: rs1014971, (P &#8776; 8 x 10<sup>-12</sup>) maps to a non-genic region of chromosome 22q13.1, rs8102137 (P = 2 x 10<sup>-11</sup>) on maps to CCNE1 and rs11892031 (P = 1 x 10<sup>-7</sup>) maps to the UGT1A cluster on 2q37.1. We confirmed four previously identified genome-wide associations on chromosomes 3q28, 4p16.3, 8q24.21 and 8q24.3 (Rothman N et al., Nature Genetics, 2010, PMID: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20972438" target="_blank">20972438</a>). Through meta-analysis with the MD Anderson Texas Bladder Cancer Study (TXBCS), we also identified a novel susceptibility locus that mapped to a region of 18q12.3, marked by rs7238033 (P = 8.7 x 10(-9); allelic odds ratio 1.20 with 95% CI: 1.13-1.28) and two highly correlated SNPs, rs10775480/rs10853535 (r(2)= 1.00; P = 8.9 x 10(-9); allelic odds ratio 1.16 with 95% CI: 1.10-1.22) (Garcia-Closas M et al, Human Molecular Genetics, 2011) </p> <p>For NCI-GWAS2, we performed genotyping on cases and controls for the New Hampshire component of the New England Bladder Cancer Study (NEBCS-NH). For the majority of new bladder cancer cases, we genotyped only cases from four case-control studies, the Los Angeles Bladder Cancer Study (LABCS), the French Center for Research on Prostate Diseases (CeRePP), the French Bladder Study (FBCS) and the Brescia Bladder Cancer Study (BBCS). We used existing control data from four cohort studies already genotyped and subjected to rigorous quality control metrics: the European Prospective Investigation Into Cancer and Nutrition Study (EPIC), Womens Health Initiative (WHI), Health Professionals Follow-up Study (HPFS), Nurses Health Study (NHS), which have been a part of Cancer Genetic Markers of Susceptibility (CGEMS).</p> <p>Meta-analysis of NCI-GWAS1, NCI-GWAS2 and a previously reported GWAS TXBCS-GWAS along with taqman replication, identified two new loci: rs10936599 on 3q26.2 (P = 4.53 x 10(-9)) and rs907611 on 11p15.5 (P = 4.11 x 10(-8)). Two notable loci were also identified that approached genome-wide statistical significance: rs6104690 on 20p12.2 (P = 7.13 x 10(-7)) and rs4510656 on 6p22.3 (P = 6.98 X 10(-7)); these require further studies for confirmation (Figueroa J et al, Human Molecular Genetics, 2013).</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Histologically confirmed primary carcinoma of the urinary bladder, including carcinoma in situ (ICD-0-2 topography codes C67.0-C67.9 or ICD9 codes 188.1-188.9).</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20972438"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21824976"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="24163127"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Urinary Bladder Neoplasms"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Carcinoma"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Nathaniel Rothman</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Montserrat Garcia-Closas</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Debra Silverman</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Stephen Chanock</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Statistician">
			<AttName>Nilanjan Chatterjee</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Nuria Malats</AttName>
			<Institution>Spanish National Cancer Research Centre, Madrid, Spain</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Jonine Figueroa</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Francisco X. Real</AttName>
			<Institution>Departament de Ci&#232;ncies Experimentals i de la Salut, Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Barcelona, Spain</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Dalsu Baris</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Michael Thun</AttName>
			<Institution>Epidemiology Research Program, American Cancer Society, Atlanta, Georgia, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Demetrius Albanes</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Mark P. Purdue</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Cancer Epidemiology and Genetics, National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Manolis Kogevinas</AttName>
			<Institution>Centre for Research in Environmental Epidemiology (CREAL), Barcelona, Spain and Municipal Institute of Medical Research, Barcelona, Spain and CIBER Epidemiologa y Salud P&#250;blica (CIBERESP), Barcelona, Spain and National School of Public Health, Athens, Greece</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Malcolm Pike</AttName>
			<Institution>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Olivier Cussenot</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Urology, Assistance Publique-Hopitaux de Paris, Tenon Hospital, Paris, France, Centre de Recherche sur les Pathologies Prostatiques, Paris, France</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Simone Benhamou</AttName>
			<Institution>Institut national de la sante et de la recherche medicale, U946, Foundation Jean Dausset Centre d&#39;Etude du Polymorphisme Humain (CEPH), Paris, France</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Stefano Porru</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Medical and Surgical Specialties, Radiological Sciences and Public Health, University of  Brescia, Brescia, Italy</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Paolo Vineis</AttName>
			<Institution>Imperial College London, London, UK</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Charles Kooperberg</AttName>
			<Institution>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Division of Public Health Sciences, Seattle, Washington, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>David Hunter</AttName>
			<Institution>Channing Division of Network Medicine, Department of Medicine, Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, 			Boston, MA, USA, Program in Genetic Epidemiology and Statistical Genetics, Department of Epidemiology, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Study Representatives">
			<AttName>Immaculata Devivo</AttName>
			<Institution>Channing Division of Network Medicine, Department of Medicine, Brigham and Women&#39;s Hospital and Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA, 			Program in Genetic Epidemiology and Statistical Genetics, Department of Epidemiology, Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Genomics">
			<AttName>Kevin B. Jacobs</AttName>
			<Institution>Core Genotyping Facility, Advanced Technology Program, SAIC-Frederick Inc, NCI-Frederick, Frederick, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>Intramural program of NCI</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Department Health and Human Services, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>Bladder cancer is a major public health problem with high disease management costs because of high recurrence of tumors requiring frequent screening and interventions (of particular relevant for early stage tumors). There are well-known epidemiologic factors that are associated with increased risk for bladder cancer: smoking and occupational exposure to aromatic amines, important clues for environmental, medication use, and lifestyle risk factors, as well as fluid balance and urine pH. The portfolio of established risk factors should provide opportunities to evaluate risk factors stratified by genotype and genetic factors within distinct exposure subgroups. There is also good evidence for a genetic component, given that previous studies have demonstrated reproducible associations with NAT2 and GSTM1 genotypes. Further, gene-environment interactions have been shown for smoking and specific NAT2 genotypes. The modest familial association has not yet been adequately explained but supports the need to search for genetic markers associated with bladder cancer. Together these observations provide a strong case for investigation of multi-genic associations as well as gene-environment interactions. Excellent information on clinical outcomes including survival and tumor recurrence is available for exploration of the influence of genetic variants on these outcomes, which could have potentially important clinical implications. Results from a GWAS leading to the identification of genetic makers could provide major insights into novel regions that regulate new mechanisms underlying bladder cancer pathogenesis. Findings from the GWAS could also provide etiological clues leading to the identification of additional modifiable factors that increase bladder cancer risk, recurrence and survival. The potential is great for advancing the understanding of the genetic contribution to bladder cancer, which could establish the foundation for developing novel approaches towards prevention while decreasing the burden of bladder cancer.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="CADM" longName="Cancer in all age groups, adult diseases, and methods"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000346.v2.p2_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000346.v2.p2
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000346.v2.p2" FileName="BladderDUC-v2.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Cancer in all age groups, adult diseases, and methods</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>CADM</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The informed consent document signed by the participants allows use of these data by investigators for discovery and hypothesis generation in the investigation of the genetic contributions to cancer in all age groups and other diseases in adults only, as well as development of novel analytical approaches for GWAS.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>
  <Documents>
    <Document phd="phd003458.1" type="questionnaire" createDate="2011-03-10" modDate="2011-03-28" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd003458.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000346.v2.p2&amp;phd=3458">
      <OrigName>bladder_GWAS_supplementary_methods.docx</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION</DisplayName>
      <Description>SUPPLEMENTARY INFORMATION</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
  </Documents>



</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
