<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000254.v2.p1" parentStudy="phs000254.v2.p1" createDate="2012-10-04" modDate="2012-10-04">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Michael Bamshad, MD</td><td>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Kathleen Barnes, PhD</td><td>Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Michael Knowles, MD</td><td>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Ronald Gibson, MD</td><td>Seattle Children&#39;s Hospital, Seattle, WA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>1RC2HL102923-01</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>ARRA - NHLBI Lung Cohorts Sequencing Project</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>ARRA - NHLBI Lung Cohorts Sequencing Project: Genetic modifiers of <i>Pseudomonas aeruginosa (Pa)</i> lung infection acquisition in cystic fibrosis</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Exome Sequencing</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The major goal of this project is to apply second generation resequencing technology to identify disease causing variants influencing pediatric and adult lung diseases in a collection of two longitudinal population cohorts of cystic fibrosis patients that have been well characterized for a comprehensive set of clinical traits. In Phase I, exome sequencing was performed on 43 cystic fibrosis patients with early <i>Pa</i> infection and 48 cystic fibrosis patients with late <i>Pa</i> infection to identify variants influencing the time to onset of <i>Pa</i> infection. In Phase II, additional exomes were added to the study, to reach a total of 91 individuals with early <i>Pa</i> infection and 96 with late <i>Pa</i> infection. The majority of the 340 subjects of Phase II do not have a <i>Pa</i> infection phenotype, but instead have a pulmonary function phenotype (121 severe vs. 124 mild impairment) as determined by the survival corrected Kulich FEV percentile of Corey et al. A small minority have intermediate phenotypes and/or show severe decline in lung function during childhood.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Extreme phenotypes:</p> <p><ul><li>Youngest with <i>Pa</i> infection vs. oldest without <i>Pa</i> infection.</li></ul> <ul><li>Very poor lung function vs. near normal lung function, adjusted for CFTR genotype.</li></ul></p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22772370"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22863193"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21946919"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19915526"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Cystic Fibrosis"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Michael Bamshad, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Washington, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Kathleen Barnes, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Michael Knowles, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Ronald Gibson, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Seattle Children&#39;s Hospital, Seattle, WA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>1RC2HL102923-01</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="NHLBI GO ESP Project" url="http://esp.gs.washington.edu/drupal/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p><i>Pseudomonas aeruginosa (Pa)</i> is a ubiquitous environmental organism and the most significant pathogen in cystic fibrosis (CF) lung disease. Early <i>Pa</i> acquisition is a major concern for CF care providers given that chronic infection with this pathogen is associated with significant CF morbidity and mortality. Two longitudinal population cohorts of cystic fibrosis patients that have been well characterized for a comprehensive set of clinical traits for the study of <i>Pa</i> acquisition have contributed to this project. The first cohort, Early <i>Pseudomonas</i> Infection Control (CFES-CF1), the world&#39;s largest, multicenter, longitudinal, prospective cohort of early lung disease in young CF patients consists of 1,704 CF cases who were ages &#8804; 12 years old with no prior isolation of <i>Pa</i> or at least a two-year history of <i>Pa</i> negative cultures. The second cohort, the NHLBI-GWAS to identify CF modifiers (CFES-CF2), consists of 1,208 patients who are at the extremes of lung disease severity.</p> <p>Exome resequencing of phenotypic extremes represents a cost-effective and robust strategy for the sensitive and specific identification of variants causing protein-coding changes influencing risk for complex traits.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS" longName="Disease Specific (Cystic Fibrosis and Genetic Variation Discovery Research Related to Cystic Fibrosis)"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000254.v2.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>3</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000254.v2.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000254.v2.p1" FileName="Sequencing_DUC_CF_final_revised_2011_Jun_30.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The use of the data from the consent group of Universities of North Carolina is limited to the general research use (GRU).</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="999">
        <ConsentName>Exchange Area</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>EA</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The use of the data from the consent group of University of Washington is limited to genetic research that facilitates discovery of variation related to cystic fibrosis (CF). The use of the data from the consent group of Universities of North Carolina is limited to the general research use (GRU). Pre release exchange area for use by study investigators only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease Specific (Cystic Fibrosis and Genetic Variation Discovery Research Related to Cystic Fibrosis)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The use of the data from the consent group of University of Washington is limited to genetic research that facilitates discovery of variation related to cystic fibrosis (CF).</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
