<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000185.v3.p1" parentStudy="phs000185.v3.p1" createDate="2013-11-08" modDate="2013-11-08">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Carole Ober, PhD</td><td>University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>R01HL085197</td><td>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Genetic Studies in the Hutterites</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genetic Studies in the Hutterites</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Population</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Whole Genome Sequencing</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>We conducted genome wide association studies (GWAS) of disease-associated quantitative phenotypes in the Hutterites, a founder population of European descent. The Hutterites in our studies live on communal farms in South Dakota and are related to each other through multiple lines of descent in a 3,657-person, 13-generation pedigree with 64 founders. The small number of founding genomes reduces genetic heterogeneity whereas their communal lifestyle ensures that non-genetic factors are remarkably uniform between individuals. During our <u>Phase 1 studies</u>, between 1996 and 1997, we measured qualitative and quantitative phenotypes that are associated with common diseases in ~750 individuals living in 9 Hutterite colonies. These individuals were genotyped using the Affymetrix 500k array. The SNPs included in our GWAS had &gt;90% call rates, minor allele frequencies &gt;5%, Hardy-Weinberg p-values &gt;0.001 (corrected for Hutterite population structure), and fewer than 5 Mendelian errors. During our Phase 2 studies, between 2006 and 2009, we phenotyped ~900 individuals living in 9 Hutterite colonies (7 overlapping with Phase 1 colonies). The Phase 2 individuals were genotyped with the Affymetrix 5.0 or 6.0 array. The SNPs included in the GWAS had &gt;95% call rates, minor allele frequencies &gt;5%, Hardy-Weinberg p-values &gt;0.001 (corrected for Hutterite population structure), and fewer than 5 Mendelian errors. The combined Phase 1 and Phase 2 sample includes 1264 unique individuals; ~ 400 individuals participated in both Phase 1 and 2 studies. These 1264 individuals are the subjects of ongoing and future studies.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Individuals living in the Hutterite colonies we visited who are age 6 years and older are invited to participate.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="11590547"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="10677322"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="11880950"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15100713"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16429159"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17323368"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19697328"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Prospective"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Asthma"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Bronchial Hyperreactivity"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Carotid Artery Diseases"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Cardiovascular Diseases"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Carole Ober, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01HL085197</AttName>
			<Institution>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p><u>Phase 1 studies</u> (1996-1997) - measured qualitative and quantitative phenotypes that are associated with common diseases in ~750 individuals living in 9 Hutterite colonies. These individuals were genotyped using the Affymetrix 500k array.</p> <p><u>Phase 2 studies</u> (2006-2009) - studied ~900 individuals living in 9 Hutterite colonies (7 overlapping with Phase 1 colonies). The Phase 2 individuals were genotyped with the Affymetrix 5.0 or 6.0 array. Approximately 400 individuals participated in both Phase 1 and 2 studies.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU-NPU" longName="General Research Use (NPU)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000185.v3.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000185.v3.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000185.v3.p1" FileName="DUC_Hutterites_2013.01.02.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use (NPU)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU-NPU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
These data will be used only for research purposes.  They may not be used to determine the individual identity of any person or to investigate aspects of pedigree structure, or to study behavior, psychiatric conditions, addiction or any other phenotype that the population may be sensitive to.  In addition, the word &amp;#x201C;Hutterite&amp;#x201D; may not be used in any oral or written presentations, disclosures, or publications resulting from any analyses of these data. A more general term such as &amp;#x201C;religious isolate of European descent&amp;#x201D; may be used to describe the population, and papers by the PI may be cited.  The informed consent document signed by the Genetic Studies in the Hutterites participants allows use of these data by investigators employed by non-profit organizations only.  Direct use of these data by private companies to develop diagnostics or therapeutics is not allowed under the consent. This consent group does not require IRB approval.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
