<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000364.v2.p1" parentStudy="phs000364.v2.p1" createDate="2011-09-12" modDate="2013-11-13">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Riccardo Dalla-Favera</td><td>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Laura Pasqualucci</td><td>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>RO1CA37295</td><td>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>R01CA177319-01</td><td>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Genome-Wide Analysis of Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>High density copy number analysis and whole exome sequencing of unselected chronic lymphocytic leukemia cases and of paired chronic lymphocytic leukemia and Richter Syndrome cases</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Tumor vs. Matched-Normal</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p><b>Analysis of the chronic lymphocytic leukemia coding genome: role of NOTCH1 mutational activation</b></p> <p>The pathogenesis of chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), the most common leukemia in adults, is still largely unknown since the full spectrum of genetic lesions that are present in the CLL genome, and therefore the number and identity of dysregulated cellular pathways, have not been identified. By combining next-generation sequencing and copy number analysis, we show here that the typical CLL coding genome contains less than 20 clonally represented gene alterations/case, including predominantly non-silent mutations and fewer copy number aberrations. These analyses led to the discovery of several genes not previously known to be altered in CLL. While most of these genes were affected at low frequency in an expanded CLL screening cohort, mutational activation of NOTCH1, observed in 8.3% of CLL at diagnosis, was detected at significantly higher frequency during disease progression toward Richter transformation (31.0%) as well as in chemorefractory CLL (20.8%). Consistent with the association of NOTCH1 mutations with clinically aggressive forms of the disease, NOTCH1 activation at CLL diagnosis emerged as an independent predictor of poor survival. These results provide initial data on the complexity of the CLL coding genome and identify a dysregulated pathway of diagnostic and therapeutic relevance.</p> <p><b>Genetic Lesions associated with Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia transformation to Richter Syndrome</b></p> <p>Richter syndrome (RS) derives from the rare transformation of chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) into an aggressive lymphoma, most commonly of the diffuse large B cell type (DLBCL). The molecular pathogenesis of RS is only partially understood. By combining whole-exome sequencing and copy-number analysis of 9 CLL-RS pairs and of an extended panel of 43 RS cases, we show that this aggressive disease typically arises from the predominant CLL clone by acquiring an average of ~20 genetic lesions/case. RS lesions are heterogeneous in terms of load and spectrum among patients, and include those involved in CLL progression and chemorefractoriness (TP53 disruption and NOTCH1 activation) as well as some not previously implicated in CLL or RS pathogenesis. In particular, disruption of the CDKN2A/B cell cycle regulator locus is associated with ~30% of RS cases. Finally, we report that the genomic landscape of RS is significantly different from that of de novo DLBCL, suggesting that they represent distinct disease entities. These results provide insights into RS pathogenesis, and identify dysregulated pathways of potential diagnostic and therapeutic relevance.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>1. Previously untreated, diagnoses of Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia with paired normal DNA (Analysis of the chronic lymphocytic leukemia coding genome: role of NOTCH1 mutational activation).<br/> 2. Matched,clonally related Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia and Richter Syndrome cases (Genetic Lesions associated with Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia transformation to Richter Syndrome).</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21670202"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="24127483"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Richter Syndrome"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Riccardo Dalla-Favera</AttName>
			<Institution>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Laura Pasqualucci</AttName>
			<Institution>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>RO1CA37295</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01CA177319-01</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-CA-PUB-MDS" longName="Disease-Specific (Cancer, PUB, MDS)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000364.v2.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000364.v2.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000364.v2.p1" FileName="GWA_Chronic_Lymphocytic_Leukemia_V.2_10.5.2011.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Cancer, PUB, MDS)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-CA-PUB-MDS</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Cancer.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
