<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000297.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000297.v1.p1" createDate="2010-07-26" modDate="2011-11-14">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Dan Roden, MD</td><td>Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>1U01HG04603</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>1U01HG04610</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>1U01HG04599</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>1U01HG04608</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>eMERGE Network Study of Resistant Hypertension</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>eMERGE Network Study of the Genetic Determinants of Resistant Hypertension</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The <b><u>e</u></b>lectronic <b><u>M</u></b>edical <b><u>R</u></b>ecords and <b><u>Ge</u></b>nomics (eMERGE) Network is a 	consortium of five participating sites (Group Health Seattle, Marshfield Clinic, Mayo Clinic, Northwestern University, and 	Vanderbilt University) funded by the NHGRI to investigate the use of electronic medical record systems for genomic research. 	The goal of eMERGE is to conduct genome-wide association studies in approximately 19,000 individuals using EMR-derived 	phenotypes and DNA from linked Biorepositories.</p> 	<p>Using electronic phenotyping methods, the consortium used DNA samples from all participating sites to explore the 	genetic determinants of resistant hypertension.  Treatment resistant hypertension is a common health problem in the 	clinical setting.  A basic definition of resistant hypertension included subjects with uncontrolled blood pressure 	despite use of three antihypertensive medications or subjects requiring four or more medications to maintain control. 	Other conditions, such as secondary causes of hypertension, were exclusions.</p> 	<p>Site and participants include:</p> 	<p><b>Vanderbilt University</b>: BioVU, Vanderbilt&#39;s DNA databank, is an enabling resource for exploration of the 	relationships among genetic variation, disease susceptibility, and variable drug responses, and represents a key first 	step in moving the emerging sciences of genomics and pharmacogenomics from research tools to clinical practice.  BioVU 	acquires DNA from discarded blood samples collected from routine patient care. The biobank is linked to de-identified 	clinical data extracted from Vanderbilt&#39;s EMR, which forms the basis for phenotype definitions used in genotype-phenotype 	correlations.</p> 	<p><b>Marshfield Clinic</b>: The Marshfield Clinic Personalized Medicine Research Project is a population-based biobank in 	central Wisconsin with more than 20,000 adult subjects who provided written, informed consent to access their medical records 	and provided a blood sample from which DNA was extracted and plasma and serum stored.  In addition to an average of 30 years 	of medical history data, a questionnaire about environmental exposures, including a detailed food frequency questionnaire, 	is available to facilitate gene/environment studies.</p> 	<p><b>Northwestern University</b>: The NUgene Project is a repository with longitudinal medical information from 	participating patients at affiliated hospitals and outpatient clinics from the Northwestern University Medical Center. 	Participants&#39; DNA samples are coupled with data from a self-reported questionnaire and continuously updated data from 	our Electronic Medical Record (EMR) representing actual clinical care events. Northwestern has a state-of-the art, 	comprehensive inpatient and outpatient EMR system of over 2 million patients.  NUgene has broad access to participant 	data for all outpatient visits as well as inpatient data via a consolidated data warehouse. NUgene participants consent 	to distribution and use of their coded DNA samples and data for a broad range of genetic research by third-party investigators.</p> 	<p><b>Group Health(GH)/University of Washington (UW)</b>: Aging and Dementia eMERGE study biorepository leverages rich 	population-based longitudinal data from both electronic medical records and in-depth research data to explore genome wide associations. 	Participants include Seattle-area members of GH (a large integrated health care system in Washington State) consented and 	enrolled in 1) the UW Alzheimer&#39;s Disease Patient Registry (ADPR) and 2) the Adult Changes in Thought (ACT) study.  The 	ADPR (PI: Eric B. Larson; NIH/NIA U01 AG 006781) is a population-based registry of incident dementia cases designed to 	identify all new Alzheimer&#39;s Disease cases within GH from 1987 to 1996.   Medical history, physical, laboratory testing, 	and neuropsychological testing were performed on all consenting potential cases for determination of dementia status by a 	consensus conference.   The study base of the ADPR population was stable with an attrition rate of less than 1%/year.  The 	ACT study (PI: Eric B. Larson; NIH/NIA U01 AG 006781) is an ongoing community-based cohort study of aging and dementia. 	The original cohort of 2,581 randomly selected dementia-free members age 65 and older was enrolled in 1994-1996 and 	expanded by 811 in 2000-2002.  Continuous enrollment to maintain a cohort of 2,000 dementia free persons began 	in 2005.  Participants receive biennial assessment including cognitive status determination.  The ACT sub-sample 	is stable; for the original cohort, median enrollment in GH was 19 years prior to joining the ACT study, and 85% of 	the cohort has &#8805; 10 years of GH enrollment.  DNA for the ADPR participants were obtained through a companion 	study, Genetic Differences in Cases and Controls (PI: Walter Kukull; NIH/NIA R01 AG007584).  DNA obtained through both 	studies were extracted from blood using Gentra Systems Puregene methods.  DNA concentration is determined by UV optical 	density. All samples are checked for quality by 260/280 ratio.  For long-term storage, samples are aliquoted and stored at -70&#176;C.</p> 	<p><b>Mayo Clinic</b>: The Mayo biobank is a disease-specific biobank for vascular diseases including peripheral arterial 	disease (PAD).  PAD patients were identified from individuals referred to the non-invasive vascular laboratory for lower 	extremity arterial evaluation.  Since 1997, laboratory findings have been recorded into an electronic database 	employing an in-house software package for data archiving and retrieval; this data becomes part of the Mayo EMR. 	Patients referred to the center with suspected PAD undergo a comprehensive non-invasive evaluation including the 	ankle-brachial index (ABI) - the ratio of blood pressure measured in the upper arms divided by blood pressure measured at 	the ankles. Controls subjects are identified from patients referred to the Cardiovascular Health Clinic for stress ECG. 	The prevalence of PAD in patients with normal exercise capacity who do not have inducible ischemia on the stress ECG, 	was &lt;1%. Data regarding risk factors for atherosclerosis such as diabetes, dyslipidemia, hypertension, and smoking 	are ascertained from the EMR.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Subjects were determined using electronic algorithms deployed with an existing EMR.</p> 	<p><b>CASE DEFINITION</b>:<br/> 	Subject has &#8805; 4 meds simultaneous* med classes below mentioned on at least 2 occasions &#8805; 1 month apart (does 	not have to be the same med classes in each of the 2 occasions);<br/> 	OR<br/> 	Subject has <u>two</u> outpatient (if possible) measurements of SBP &gt; 140 or DBP &gt; 90 at least one month after meeting 	medication criteria while still on 3 simultaneous med classes<br/> 	AND<br/> 	has 3 simultaneous* med classes below (and does not meet Case Type 1) mentioned on at least 2 occasions &#8805; 1 month 	apart (does not have to be the same med classes in each of the 2 occasions). 	</p> 	<p>*Simultaneous is defined as evidence that they are taking the medications concurrently.  Such evidence could be presence of 	the medications in the same medication list (e.g., problem list, clinic note, or discharge summary) or via medication 	refill data.  If using the latter method, the algorithm should find evidence of at least repeated overlapping scripts for 	each drug if you are using this method.</p> 	<p>S: start<br/> 	R:refill<br/> 	X-axis: is time<br/> 	BP: 150/80-----------145/80---154/74<br/> 	Drug 1 : S----->R1------>R2---->R3---->R4<br/> 	Drug 2: -----S------>absent<br/> 	Drug 3:----------S------>R1---->R2---->R3--<br/> 	Drug 4:-------------------S---->R1----->R2----<br/>     <i>At R1 of Drug 4, patient qualifies for Case Type 2</i> 	</p> 	<p><b>Note</b>: For those using NLP to define medications, we require a dose, strength, route, or frequency present with the medication 	name to insure that the medication represents a prescribed medication.</p> 	<p>From the above, subjects with any of the following codes appearing in the record at any time were excluded:</p> 	<p> 	<table border="1"> 	<tr><th>ICD9 codes</th><th>Description</th></tr> 	<tr><td>194.0</td><td>MALIGN NEOPL ADRENAL</td></tr> 	<tr><td>227.0</td><td>BENIGN NEOPLASM ADRENAL</td></tr> 	<tr><td>255.0, 255.1, 255.2, 255.3, 255.6, 255.8, 255.9</td><td>Disorders of adrenal glands (excludes adrenal insufficiencies - 255.4 and 255.5)</td></tr> 	<tr><td>405.*</td><td>SECONDARY HYPERTENSION</td></tr> 	<tr><td>416.*</td><td>Chronic pulmonary heart disease</td></tr> 	<tr><td>581.*</td><td>Nephrotic syndrome</td></tr> 	<tr><td>582.*</td><td>Chronic glumerulonephritis</td></tr> 	<tr><td>745.*</td><td>Bulbus cordis anomalies</td></tr> 	<tr><td>747.1*</td><td>COARCTATION OF AORTA</td></tr> 	</table> 	</p> 	<p>From the cases above, all subjects with the following codes were excluded only if the resistant hypertension only exists within 	five years before or after one of the codes below.  For example, this means that one could ignore medications mentioned during 	a 5-year time frame before or after the below codes.</p> 	<p> 	<table border="1"> 	<tr><th>ICD9 codes</th><th>Description</th></tr> 	<tr><td>242.*</td><td>Thyrotoxicosis</td></tr> 	<tr><td>246</td><td>Disorder of thyrocalcitonin secretion</td></tr> 	<tr><td>246.8</td><td>DISORDERS OF THYROID NEC</td></tr> 	<tr><td>246.9</td><td>DISORDER OF THYROID NOS</td></tr> 	<tr><td>252.8</td><td>PARATHYROID DISORDER NEC</td></tr> 	<tr><td>252.9</td><td>PARATHYROID DISORDER NOS</td></tr> 	<tr><td>320.2</td><td>ORGANIC SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.21</td><td>PRIMARY CENTRAL SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.23</td><td>OBSTRUCTIVE SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.27</td><td>CEN SLEEP APNEA IN COND CLASS</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.29</td><td>OTHER ORGANIC SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>599.6*</td><td>OBSTRUCTIVE UROPATHY</td></tr> 	</table> 	</p> 	<p>From the cases above, exclude the subject if <b>GFR &lt; 30 ml/min</b> before the time of meeting the CASE 1 or 2 definitions 	or within 6 months after meeting the medication definition.</p> 	<p><i>GFR should be calculated using the Modification of Diet in Renal Disease (MDRD) formula:</i><br/> 	eGFR = 186 x Serum Creatinine<sup>-1.154</sup> x Age<sup>-0.203</sup> x [1.210 <i>if Black</i>] x [0.742 <i>if Female</i>]<br/> 	<i>(source: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renal_function#Estimated_GFR_.28eGFR.29_using_Modification_of_Diet_in_Renal_Disease_.28MDRD.29_formula" target="_blank">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Renal_function#Estimated_GFR_.28eGFR.29_using_Modification_of_Diet_in_Renal_Disease_.28MDRD.29_formula</a>)</i> 	</p> 	<p>Exclude all patients with an Ejection Fraction (EF or LVEF) &lt;35% within 1 year before or after meeting the CASE 1 definition.</p> 	<p><b>CONTROL DEFINITION</b>:</p> 	<p> 	Controls - Case 1: Subjects with controlled hypertension<br/> 	Has outpatient (if possible) measurement of SBP &gt; 140 or DBP &gt; 90 prior to meeting medication criteria OR ICD9 401.* code at any time<br/> 	AND<br/> 	has 1 med from med classes below (and never has more than 1 simultaneous med class, although the med class can change)<br/> 	AND<br/> 	Has all SBP &lt; 135 and DBP &lt; 90 one month AFTER BP meds (require at least 1 BP measurement) 	</p> 	<p> 	Controls - Case 2: Subjects without evidence of hypertension<br/> 	Has no outpatient (if possible) measurement of SBP &gt; 140 or DBP &gt; 90<br/> 	AND<br/> 	No mention of any anti-hypertensive from med classes below at any time<br/> 	AND<br/> 	Does not have any hypertension ICD9 code:  (401, 401.0, 401.9, 402.*, 403.*  404.*) 	</p> 	<p>For all controls:  Exclude all patients with EF &lt; 35% or with the following ICD9 codes:</p> 	<p> 	<table border="1"> 	<tr><th>ICD9 codes</th><th>Description</th></tr> 	<tr><td>194.0</td><td>MALIGN NEOPL ADRENAL</td></tr> 	<tr><td>227.0</td><td>BENIGN NEOPLASM ADRENAL</td></tr> 	<tr><td>255.0, 255.1, 255.2, 255.3, 255.6, 255.8, 255.9</td><td>Disorders of adrenal glands (excludes adrenal insufficiencies - 255.4 and 255.5)</td></tr> 	<tr><td>405.*</td><td>SECONDARY HYPERTENSION</td></tr> 	<tr><td>416.*</td><td>Chronic pulmonary heart disease</td></tr> 	<tr><td>581.*</td><td>Nephrotic syndrome</td></tr> 	<tr><td>582.*</td><td>Chronic glumerulonephritis</td></tr> 	<tr><td>745.*</td><td>Bulbus cordis anomalies</td></tr> 	<tr><td>747.1*</td><td>COARCTATION OF AORTA</td></tr> 	</table> 	</p> 	<p>Subjects with the following codes <b>are allowable</b> as controls (no matter when they occurred):</p> 	<p> 	<table border="1"> 	<tr><th>ICD9 codes</th><th>Description</th></tr> 	<tr><td>242.*</td><td>Thyrotoxicosis</td></tr> 	<tr><td>246</td><td>Disorder of thyrocalcitonin secretion</td></tr> 	<tr><td>246.8</td><td>DISORDERS OF THYROID NEC</td></tr> 	<tr><td>246.9</td><td>DISORDER OF THYROID NOS</td></tr> 	<tr><td>252.8</td><td>PARATHYROID DISORDER NEC</td></tr> 	<tr><td>252.9</td><td>PARATHYROID DISORDER NOS</td></tr> 	<tr><td>320.2</td><td>ORGANIC SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.21</td><td>PRIMARY CENTRAL SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.23</td><td>OBSTRUCTIVE SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.27</td><td>CEN SLEEP APNEA IN COND CLASS</td></tr> 	<tr><td>327.29</td><td>OTHER ORGANIC SLEEP APNEA</td></tr> 	<tr><td>599.6*</td><td>OBSTRUCTIVE UROPATHY</td></tr> 	</table> 	</p> 	<p><b><u>Medication Classes</u></b>:</p> 	<p><b><u>Hydralazine</u></b>: Hydralazine (Apresazide, bidil, apressoline)</p> 	<p><b><u>Minoxidil</u></b>: (Loniten)</p> 	<p><b><u>Renin antagonist</u></b>: aliskiren (Tekturna)</p> 	<p><b><u>Central alpha agonists</u></b>: clonidine (catapres) (catapress); guanabenz; methyldopa; methyldopate</p> 	<p><b><u>ACEI/ARB</u></b>: candesartan (Atacand); Irbesartan (avapro); lisinopril (prinivil, zestril); trandolapril (Mavik, gopten, odrik); 	Losartan (cozaar); enalapril (enalaprilat); valsartan (diovan); telmisartan (Micardis); moexipril; quinapril (accupril); 	ramipril (altace); fosinopril (monopril); eprosartan; olmesartan (benicar); perindopril (Aceon); captopril (Capoten); benazepril (lotensin);</p> 	<p><b><u>Aldosterone antagonists</u></b>: spironolactone (Aldactone); eplerenone (inspra)</p> 	<p><b><u>Diuretics (count each instance as part of the same class, even if on more than one concurrently)</u></b>: <b><u>Thiazide</u></b>: hydrochlorothiazide 	(Esidrix); indapamide (lozol, natrilix); cyclothiazide; chlorothiazide; chlorthalidone; bendroflumethiazide; benzothiazide; 	<b><u>K-sparing diuretics</u></b>: amiloride (midamor); triamterene (Dyrenium); <b><u>Loop diuretics</u></b>: furosemide (lasix), torsemide (demadex), 	ethacrynic acid (ethacrynate, edecrin); bumetanide (bumex)</p> 	<p><b>Note</b>: the Diuretic combination meds now count as a single class:  Dyazide, Moduretic, Maxzide</p> 	<p><b><u>Alpha antagonists</u></b>: prazosin (minipress); doxazosin (cardura)</p> 	<p><b><u>Non-dihydro CCBs</u></b>: verapamil (calan, covera, isoptin, verelan); diltiazem (dilt, tiazac, cardizem)</p> 	<p><b><u>Dihydro CCBs</u></b>: isradipine (Dynacirc); nicardipine; nifedipine (procardia); nisoldipine; felodipine (plendil); Amlodipine 	(norvasc, caduet); bepridil (vascor)</p> 	<p><b><u>Beta Blockers</u></b>: propranolol (inderal); metoprolol (toprol); labetalol (trandate); nadolol (corgard); esmolol (brevibloc); 	pindolol; penbutolol (levatol); Labetalol (Normodyne); atenolol (tenormin); carvedilol (coreg); bisoprolol (Zebeta);</p> 	<p><b><u>*Thiazide/BB</u></b>: corzide , Tenoretic, lopressor HCT</p> 	<p><b><u>*Thiazide/ACEI_ARB</u></b>: zestoretic, Avalide, hyzaar, uniretic, benicar HCT, accuretic, Teveten HCT, lotensin HCT; micardis 	HCT; atacand HCT; Diovan HCT; Monopril HCT</p> 	<p><b><u>*Thiazide/aldosterone antagonist</u></b>: aldactazide</p> 	<p><b><u>*Thiazide/Renin antagonist</u></b>: Tekturna HCT</p> 	<p>*A match of a combination medication counts as two med classes.  We have not included the generics for combination medications 	to avoid possible double counting of the medication classes during a search.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18500243"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="McCarty CA, Wilke RA, Giampietro PF, Wesbrook S, Caldwell MD" title="Marshfield Clinic Personalized Medicine Research Project (PMRP): design, methods and recruitment for a large, population-based biobank" journal="Personalized Medicine 2005;2:49-79"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Wolf W, Doyle M, Aufox S, Frezzo T, Smith M, Kibbe, W, Chisholm, R" title="DNA Banking Study in an Ethnically Diverse Urban University Hospital" journal="American Journal of Human Genetics 2003;73:423"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Hypertension"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Dan Roden, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Vanderbilt University Medical Center, Nashville, TN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>1U01HG04603</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>1U01HG04610</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>1U01HG04599</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>1U01HG04608</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>1U01HG04609</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping">
			<AttName>U01HG004424</AttName>
			<Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping">
			<AttName>U01HG004438-01</AttName>
			<Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="The eMERGE Network" url="https://www.mc.vanderbilt.edu/victr/dcc/projects/acc/index.php/Main_Page"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="HR_GHS" longName="Health Research - Group Health Seattle"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="AGING_GHS" longName="Dementia or Aging - Group Health Seattle"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="3" shortName="HR_MC" longName="Health Research - Marshfield Clinic"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="4" shortName="HR_VU" longName="Health Research - Vanderbilt U"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="5" shortName="HR_MYO" longName="Health Research - Mayo Clinic"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="6" shortName="HR_NWU" longName="Health Research - Northwestern U"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHGRI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Human Genome Research Institute</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000297.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000297.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000297.v1.p1" FileName="eMERGE_GWAS_DUC_09-23-2011.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Health Research - Group Health Seattle</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HR_GHS</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>These data will be used only for health related research, including research to improve methods for health related research.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="3">
        <ConsentName>Health Research - Marshfield Clinic</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HR_MC</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.
No Permitted Use: Insurance companies</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>Dementia or Aging - Group Health Seattle</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>AGING_GHS</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Limited to health research on dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. This includes research to improve methods for conducting research that could be applied to dementia or other adult conditions related to the aging process. For example, studies of conditions like cataract, diabetes, and psoriasis might be appropriate, while conditions like attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) and neuroblastoma might not be appropriate. Studies of conditions that are common in both children and the elderly, such as schizophrenia or depression, would not be appropriate if they focused on children or young adults. Studies focused primarily on pediatric populations are not permitted.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="4">
        <ConsentName>Health Research - Vanderbilt U</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HR_VU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="5">
        <ConsentName>Health Research - Mayo Clinic</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HR_MYO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Mayo Clinic Data may only be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems.
Investigators must state in the Data Use Request their intention to publish or otherwise broadly share any findings from his or her study with the scientific community.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="6">
        <ConsentName>Health Research - Northwestern U</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HR_NWU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>May be used for genetic studies to learn about, prevent, or treat health problems
No Permitted Use: Insurance companies</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
