<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000856.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000856.v1.p1" createDate="2015-01-12" modDate="2015-01-12">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Philip M. Murphy</td><td>Division of Intramural Research, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>Z01 AI000615</td><td>Division of Intramural Research, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Chromothripsis in Patient WHIM-09</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Chromothripsis in Patient WHIM-09</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Single Patient</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>We are studying the natural history, pathogenesis and treatment of patients with WHIM syndrome, an immunodeficiency disorder characterized by warts, hypogammaglobulinemia, recurrent infections and neutropenia usually due to autosomal dominant gain-of-function mutations in chemokine receptor <i>CXCR4</i>. We have identified a patient born with WHIM syndrome and the WHIM mutation <i>CXCR4<sup>R334X</sup></i> who has been disease-free for 20 years and who lacks <i>CXCR4<sup>R334X</sup></i> in myeloid cells, the cells that drive disease manifestations. She is a genetic and hematopoietic mosaic, since she still has the mutation in lymphoid cells and non-hematopoietic cells. Cytogenetics and microarray analysis revealed that the mechanism of loss of the mutation was deletion of the mutant allele from one copy of chromosome 2. Whole genome sequencing of patient neutrophil and skin fibroblast genomic DNA revealed that the mechanism of deletion was chromothripsis, a process of chromosome shattering resulting in deletions and rearrangements of the non-deleted chromosomal segments. In the patient, this process evidently occurred in a single hematopoietic stem cell (HSC), resulting in deletion of the disease allele <i>CXCR4<sup>R334X</sup></i> and one copy of 163 other genes on chromosome 2. This HSC evidently acquired a growth advantage and repopulated the HSC population and the myeloid lineage. Consistent with this, studies using gene targeted mice in competitive bone marrow transplantation experiments revealed that selective <i>Cxcr4</i> haploinsufficiency (inactivation of one copy of <i>Cxcr4</i> and not of any other genes) was sufficient to confer a strong engraftment advantage over bone marrow cells from wild type mice as well as bone marrow cells from a mouse model of WHIM syndrome. These results suggest that <i>CXCR4</i> knockdown may be a useful strategy to enhance bone marrow engraftment in the absence of toxic bone marrow conditioning regimens.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Inclusion criteria: patients with warts, hypogammaglobulinemia, recurrent infections and neutropenia with mutations in <i>CXCR4</i>.</p> <p>Exclusion criteria: none</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="David H. McDermott, Ji-Liang Gao, Qian Liu, Marie Siwicki, Craig Martens, Paejonette Jacobs, Daniel Velez, Erin Yim, Christine R. Bryke, Nancy Hsu, Zunyan Dai, Martha M. Marquesen, Elina Stregevsky, Nana Kwatemaa, Narda Theobald, Debra A. Long Priel, Stefania Pittaluga, Mark A. Raffeld, Katherine R. Calvo, Irina Maric, Ronan Desmond, Kevin L. Holmes, Douglas B. Kuhns, Karl Balabanian, Francoise Bachelerie, Stephen F. Porcella, Harry L. Malech, and Philip M. Murphy" title="Chromothriptic Cure of WHIM Syndrome" journal="Cell, 2015. In Press."/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="WHIM syndrome"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Warts"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Severe congenital neutropenia"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Hypogammaglobulinemia"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Warts, hypogammaglobulinemia, infections, and myelokathexis"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Philip M. Murphy</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Intramural Research, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>Z01 AI000615</AttName>
			<Institution>Division of Intramural Research, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The first patient ever described with WHIM syndrome, designated WHIM-09, came to the NIH requesting evaluation of two of her three daughters, both of whom have WHIM syndrome. We identified the WHIM mutation <i>CXCR4<sup>R334X</sup></i> in whole blood DNA from both daughters but not in the mother who indicated that ~20 years prior to the visit her warts had resolved and her recurrent infections had stopped. Analysis of the medical record indicated that the absolute neutrophil and monocyte counts in the blood of patient WHIM-09, were markedly deficient until ~20 years before coming to NIH, consistent with WHIM syndrome, then began to rise spontaneously reaching a plateau about twice the upper limit of normal. The lymphocyte levels rose minimally during this time. Accordingly, we found that WHIM-09 is a genetic and hematopoietic mosaic, since she still has the mutation <i>CXCR4<sup>R334X</sup></i> in lymphoid cells and non-hematopoietic cells. Cytogenetics and microarray analysis revealed that the mechanism of loss of the mutation was deletion of the mutant allele from one copy of chromosome 2. Whole genome sequencing of patient neutrophil and skin fibroblast genomic DNA revealed that the mechanism of deletion was chromothripsis, a process of chromosome shattering resulting in deletions and rearrangements of the non-deleted chromosomal segments. In the patient, this process evidently occurred in a single hematopoietic stem cell (HSC), resulting in deletion of the disease allele <i>CXCR4<sup>R334X</sup></i> and one copy of 163 other genes on chromosome 2. This HSC evidently acquired a growth advantage and repopulated the HSC population and the myeloid lineage, but not the lymphoid lineage. Consistent with this, studies using gene targeted mice in competitive bone marrow transplantation experiments revealed that selective <i>Cxcr4</i> haploinsufficiency (inactivation of one copy of <i>Cxcr4</i> and not of any other genes) was sufficient to confer a strong engraftment advantage over bone marrow cells from a mouse model of WHIM syndrome as well as bone marrow cells from wild type mice. These results suggest that <i>CXCR4</i> knockdown may be useful as a general strategy to enhance bone marrow engraftment in the absence of toxic bone marrow conditioning regimens.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU-IRB" longName="General Research Use (IRB)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIAID</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIAID DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000856.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>2</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000856.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000856.v1.p1" FileName="DUC-Murphy_010715.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use (IRB)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU-IRB</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
