<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs001112.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs001112.v1.p1" createDate="2016-05-03" modDate="2016-05-23">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Stephen Chanock</td><td>National Cancer Institute, National Health Institute, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Chromosome X Mosaicism Methylation Study</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Chromosome X Mosaicism Methylation Study</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case Set</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>This study investigates methylation patterns in promoter regions on the X chromosomes of females with X chromosome mosaicism in an effort to phase mosaic events to either the active or inactive X chromosome.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Females with genotyping array detected X mosaic events greater than 2 Mb in size and with available DNA</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Mitchell J. Machiela, Weiyin Zhou, Eric Karlins, Joshua N. Sampson, Neal D. Freedman, Qi Yang, Belynda Hicks, Casey Dagnall, 			Christopher Hautman, Kevin B. Jacobs, Christian C. Abnet, Melinda C. Aldrich, Christopher Amos, Laufey T. Amundadottir, Alan A. Arslan, 			Laura E. Beane-Freeman, Sonja I. Berndt, Amanda Black, William J. Blot, Cathryn H. Bock, Paige M. Bracci, Louise A. Brinton, H. Bas 			Bueno-de-Mesquita, Laurie Burdett, Julie E. Buring, Mary A. Butler, Federico Canzian, Tania Carreon, Kari G. Chaffee, I-Shou Chang, 			Nilanjan Chatterjee, Chu Chen, Constance Chen, Kexin Chen, Charles C. Chung, Linda S. Cook, Marta Crous Bou, Michael Cullen, 			Faith G. Davis, Immaculata De Vivo, Ti Ding, Jennifer Doherty, Eric J. Duell, Caroline G. Epstein, Jin-Hu Fan, Jonine D. Figueroa, 			Joseph F. Fraumeni, Jr., Christine M. Friedenreich, Charles S. Fuchs, Steven Gallinger, Yu-Tang Gao, Susan M. Gapstur, Montserrat 			Garcia-Closas, Mia M. Gaudet, J. Michael Gaziano, Graham G. Giles, Elizabeth M. Gillanders, Edward L. Giovannucci, Lynn Goldin, 			Alisa M. Goldstein, Christopher A. Haiman, Goran Hallmans, Susan E. Hankinson, Curtis C. Harris, Roger Henriksson, Elizabeth A. Holly, 			Yun-Chul Hong, Robert N. Hoover, Chao A. Hsiung, Nan Hu, Wei Hu, David J. Hunter, Amy Hutchinson, Mazda Jenab, Christoffer Johansen, 			Kay-Tee Khaw, Hee Nam Kim, Yeul Hong Kim, Young Tae Kim, Alison P. Klein, Robert Klein, Woon-Puay Koh, Laurence N. Kolonel, 			Charles Kooperberg, Peter Kraft, Vittorio Krogh, Robert C. Kurtz, Andrea LaCroix, Qing Lan, Maria Teresa Landi, Loic Le Marchand, 			Donghui Li, Xiaolin Liang, Linda M. Liao, Dongxin Lin, Jianjun Liu, Jolanta Lissowska, Lingeng Lu, Anthony M. Magliocco, Nuria Malats, 			Keitaro Matsuo, Lorna H. McNeill, Robert R. McWilliams, Beatrice S. Melin, Lisa Mirabello, Lee Moore, Sara H. Olson, Irene Orlow, 			Jae Yong Park, Ana Patino-Garcia, Beata Peplonska, Ulrike Peters, Gloria M. Petersen, Loreall Pooler, Jennifer Prescott, Ludmila 			Prokunina-Olsson, Mark P. Purdue, You-Lin Qiao, Preetha Rajaraman, Francisco X. Real,  Elio Riboli, Harvey A. Risch, Benjamin 			Rodriguez-Santiago, Avima M. Ruder, Sharon A. Savage, Fredrick Schumacher, Ann G. Schwartz, Kendra L. Schwartz, Adeline Seow, 			Veronica Wendy Setiawan, Gianluca Severi, Hongbing Shen, Xin Sheng, Min-Ho Shin, Xiao-Ou Shu, Debra T. Silverman, Margaret R. Spitz, 			Victoria L. Stevens, Rachael Stolzenberg-Solomon, Daniel Stram, Ze-Zhong Tang, Philip R. Taylor, Lauren R. Teras, Geoffrey S. Tobias, 			David Van Den Berg, Kala Visvanathan, Sholom Wacholder, Jiu-Cun Wang, Zhaoming Wang, Nicolas Wentzensen, William Wheeler, Emily White, 			John K. Wiencke, Brian M. Wolpin, Maria Pik Wong, Chen Wu, Tangchun Wu, Xifeng Wu, Yi-Long Wu, Jay S. Wunder, Lucy Xia, Hannah P. Yang, 			Pan-Chyr Yang, Kai Yu, Krista A. Zanetti, Anne Zeleniuch-Jacquotte, Wei Zheng, Baosen Zhou, Regina G. Ziegler, Luis A. Perez-Jurado, 			Neil E. Caporaso, Nathaniel Rothman, Margaret Tucker, Michael C. Dean, Meredith Yeager, Stephen J. Chanock" title="Female chromosome X mosaicism is age-related and preferentially affects the inactivated X chromosome" journal="Nature Communications, (in press)"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Neoplasm"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Stephen Chanock</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Health Institute, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="O-MDS_ONLY" longName="Methods Only"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs001112.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs001112.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs001112.v1.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Methods Only</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>O-MDS_ONLY</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>These data may be used for methods studies only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
