<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000327.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000327.v1.p1" createDate="2010-11-17" modDate="2013-01-24">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Stephen Rich, PhD</td><td>University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>RC2 HL103010</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>NHLBI GO-ESP: Heart Cohorts Exome Sequencing Project (SWISS)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>NHLBI GO-ESP: Heart Cohorts Exome Sequencing Project (Siblings with Ischemic Stroke Study, SWISS)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Affected Sib Pairs</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Exome Sequencing</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The NHLBI "Grand Opportunity" Exome Sequencing Project (GO-ESP), a signature project of the NHLBI Recovery Act investment, was designed to identify genetic variants in coding regions (exons) of the human genome (the "exome") that are associated with heart, lung and blood diseases. These and related diseases that are of high impact to public health and individuals from diverse racial and ethnic groups will be studied. These data may help researchers understand the causes of disease, contributing to better ways to prevent, diagnose, and treat diseases, as well as determine whether to tailor prevention and treatments to specific populations. This could lead to more effective treatments and reduce the likelihood of side effects. GO-ESP is comprised of five collaborative components: 3 cohort consortia - HeartGO, LungGO, and WHISP - and 2 sequencing centers - BroadGO and SeattleGO.</p> <p>The Siblings with Ischemic Stroke Study (SWISS) is an affected sibpair (ASP) study of patients and their brothers/sisters who have had similar strokes. The study was conducted to determine the genes that contribute to an individual&#39;s risk of developing an ischemic stroke (a stroke due to sudden interruption of blood flow to a part of the brain). Over 600 people have participated in SWISS, with the coordination of the recruitment and flow of the samples occurring at the Mayo Clinic, Jacksonville, FL, under the direction of James F. Meschia, MD. The University of Virginia (Stephen S. Rich, PhD) served as the analytic site for the genetic data. Participants were excluded from SWISS if they had stroke following an invasive cerebrovascular or cardiovascular procedure, if their stroke occurred shortly following an aneurismal subarachnoid hemorrhage, if the stroke occurred in the setting of a mechanical aortic or mitral valve, if the patient had definite CNS vasculitis or if the patient had a Mendelian mitochondrial stroke disorder, including CADASIL, MELAS, Fabry disease, sickle cell anemia or homocysteinemia.</p> <p>For the NHLBI ESP, the youngest 51 ASPs (102 individuals) from SWISS were selected to undergo exome sequencing. These ASPs were selected from among all SWISS participants, excluding those pedigrees with individuals who had TOAST subtypes of stroke of other etiology or of stroke with undetermined etiology. In addition, the affected siblings were required to have the same TOAST subtype (both small vessel (lacunar) or both large vessel (atherosclerotic)). Of those selected, 98 samples passed initial quality control metrics, and 94 completed exome sequencing and were deposited in dbGaP.</p> <p>An additional set of 590 samples from the SWISS collection has been genotyped on the ExomeChip that contained a subset of rare/infrequent variants identified by exome sequencing. These samples include 495 affected individuals (from multiple affected family members) as well as 95 unaffected family members. These genetic and phenotypic data also will reside in dbGaP.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Probands and affected siblings were required to have at least one stroke (WHO criteria) that was confirmed to be ischemic by head CT or brain MR. They were excluded from the study if they had stroke following an invasive cerebrovascular or cardiovascular procedure, if their stroke occurred shortly following an aneurismal subarachnoid hemorrhage, if the stroke occurred in the setting of a mechanical aortic or mitral valve, if the patient had definite CNS vasculitis or if the patient had a Mendelian or mitochondrial stroke disorder, including CADASIL, MELAS, Fabry disease, sickle cell anemia or homocysteinemia.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="11882254"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15728301"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="15781828"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16130105"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17283317"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17332449"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17534386"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17904086"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18755410"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21940970"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Stroke"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Stephen Rich, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>RC2 HL103010</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="NHLBI GO-ESP Project" url="https://esp.gs.washington.edu/drupal/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The <b>Siblings with Ischemic Stroke Study (SWISS)</b> is an affected sib pair study of adult men and women who have a diagnosis of at least one ischemic stroke confirmed by a study neurologist, report having at least one living full sibling with a history of stroke and are at least 18 years old at the time of enrollment in the study. To be enrolled as a concordant sibling, the subject must have a full sibling enrolled in SWISS. Both the case and concordant siblings must be at least 18 years old at enrollment and both must meet the same definition of ischemic stroke. A central, genotype-blinded committee of study-appointed neurologists makes the diagnosis of ischemic stroke on the basis of medical record review. Over 300 affected sib pairs concordant for ischemic stroke, categorized for stroke risk factors and subtyped using TOAST criteria have been collected.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects."/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-STK-IRB-RD" longName="Disease Specific (Stroke and Related Disorders)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000327.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>3</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000327.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000327.v1.p1" FileName="SWISS_GOESP_DUC_2010_07_15.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease Specific (Stroke and Related Disorders)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-STK-IRB-RD</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The informed consent document signed by SWISS participants allows use of these data by investigators employed by non-profit and for-profit organizations. These data may be used by private companies in the development of diagnostics and therapeutics under the current consent. For the SWISS participants, this consent group requires IRB approval.
SWISS data may only be used to investigate stroke and stroke-related disorders. The SWISS data may not be used to investigate individual pedigree structures, individual participant genotypes, phenotype-only analyses, or issues such as non-maternity and non-paternity; all research must be related to the etiology and prevention of morbidity and mortality of the U.S. population consistent with the demographic distribution in the SWISS cohort.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="999">
        <ConsentName>Exchange Area</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>EA</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>The informed consent document signed by SWISS participants allows use of these data by investigators employed by non-profit and for-profit organizations. These data may be used by private companies in the development of diagnostics and therapeutics under the current consent. For the SWISS participants, this consent group requires IRB approval.
SWISS data may only be used to investigate stroke and stroke-related disorders. The SWISS data may not be used to investigate individual pedigree structures, individual participant genotypes, phenotype-only analyses, or issues such as non-maternity and non-paternity; all research must be related to the etiology and prevention of morbidity and mortality of the U.S. population consistent with the demographic distribution in the SWISS cohort.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
