<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000640.v4.p1" parentStudy="phs000640.v4.p1" createDate="2016-02-19" modDate="2016-02-22">

<Configuration>
	<StudyNameEntrez>HeLa Cell Genome Sequencing Studies</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>HeLa Cell Genome Sequencing Studies</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Whole Genome Sequencing</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>This study contains all authorized whole genome sequence data of the HeLa cell line from datasets currently in dbGaP. These data have been approved for health, medical, and/or biomedical research purposes. Access to these data can be granted for one year. Accessible data will include the studies listed on this page and any additional authorized datasets that become available during this one-year period.</p> <p><a href="http://acd.od.nih.gov/hlgda.htm">The HeLa Genome Data Access Working Group of the Advisory Committee to the Director (ACD)</a> will review requests from the research community for access to these datasets and assess whether the requests align with the terms of use defined in the HeLa Genome Data Use Agreement. The Working Group&#39;s findings will be reported to the ACD, and the ACD will make recommendations to the NIH Director about whether a request should be approved or disapproved. The NIH Director will decide whether access to the data will be granted.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23550136"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Andrew Adey, Joshua N. Burton, Jacob O. Kitzman, Joseph B. Hiatt, Alexandra P. Lewis, Beth K. Martin, Ruolan Qiu, Choli Lee, Jay Shendure" title="The haplotype-resolved genome and epigenome of the aneuploid HeLa cancer cell line" journal="Nature, 2013, in press"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Uterine Cervical Neoplasms"/>
	</Diseases>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>HeLa is a human epithelial adenocarcinoma cell line that was derived from biopsy specimens of a 31-year old patient named Henrietta Lacks who was being treated for cervical cancer at The Johns Hopkins University Hospital in 1951. The specimens were obtained without her knowledge or consent just before her death in 1951. HeLa is the oldest and most widely used human cell line and has been an extraordinarily important resource for researchers throughout the world. HeLa cells have served as a standard for understanding many fundamental biological processes, such as testing the polio vaccine, establishing basic techniques for cloning and in vitro fertilization, identifying the cause of cervical cancer (HPV), and advancing the development of anti-cancer drugs.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="HMB" longName="Health/Medical/Biomedical"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>OD</DacName>
      <DacFullName>OD</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000640.v4.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000640.v4.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000640.v4.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Health/Medical/Biomedical</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HMB</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of this data is limited to health/medical/biomedical purposes, does not include the study of population origins or ancestry.
Approved Users agree not to attempt to contact family members of Henrietta Lacks. 
Users agree to acknowledge Henrietta Lacks and her family in any dissemination of research findings: 
The genomic sequence data used in this study were derived from a HeLa cell line. Henrietta Lacks, and the HeLa cell line that was established from her tumor cells, have made significant contributions to scientific progress and advances in human health. The HeLa genomic data were accessed through the NIH database of Genotypes and Phenotypes (dbGaP at http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/entrez?db=gap) through dbGaP accession number phs000640.
Users agree to include a statement about whether the research is intended or could be reasonably expected to result in a patent or commercial product or service.
The Requester and Approved Users agree to safeguard the data by not sharing with unapproved users, following all required security measures, and reporting any data security breaches to NIH.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
