<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000332.v3.p2" parentStudy="phs000332.v3.p2" createDate="2016-01-28" modDate="2016-01-28">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Xiaobin Wang, MD, MPH, ScD, Zanvyl Krieger Professor</td><td>Director, Center on the Early Life Origins of Disease, Department of Population, Family and Reproductive Health, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, and Professor of Pediatrics, John Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Barry Zuckerman, MD, Professor</td><td>Department of Pediatrics, Boston Medical Center, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Linda Heffner, MD, Professor</td><td>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Boston Medical Center, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Xin Liu, MD, PhD, Assistant Professor</td><td>Mary Ann and J. Milburn Smith Child Health Research Program, Department of Pediatrics, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Hui-Ju Tsai, PhD, Assistant Professor</td><td>Mary Ann and J. Milburn Smith Child Health Research Program, Department of Pediatrics, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>GWAS of Preterm Birth</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genome-Wide Association Study of Preterm Birth</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Preterm birth (PTB, born before 37 weeks of gestation) is a leading cause of neonatal mortality and post-natal morbidity. PTB affects one in nine all live births in the U.S. Notably, the highest rate of PTB occurs among African Americans (one in six). PTB is a complex trait, likely determined by multiple environmental and genetic factors and their interactions. We demonstrated strong familial aggregation of preterm and low birthweight in the US Blacks and Whites (Wang et al, NEJM, <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7491139">1995</a>) and conducted the largest candidate gene study of preterm birth at that time (Hao et al, HMG, <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?cmd=DetailsSearch&term=14976157">2004</a>). We showed that a subset of mothers with certain metabolic gene variants are particularly vulnerable to the adverse effects of cigarette smoking on low birthweight and preterm births (Wang et al, JAMA, <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed?cmd=DetailsSearch&term=11779261">2002</a>). We also published a number of papers that examined the effect of maternal pre-pregnancy BMI, micronutrient status, stress and environmental toxins on the risk of preterm birth and related conditions.</p> <p>This project, supported by a grant from the NICHD (2R01HD41702, PI, Xiaobin Wang), aimed to conduct a genome-wide association study (GWAS) and apply advanced statistical methods to identify susceptibility loci of PTB in a predominantly urban low-income African American sample, a subset of the Boston Birth Cohort.</p> <p>PUBLIC HEALTH REVELANCE: We anticipate that this study will lead to the identification of novel genetic loci of PTB and gene-environment interactions. Such findings not only will provide important insights into mechanisms leading to PTB, but also may help identify women at high-risk of PTB, which in turn, may lead to the development of early and targeted interventions that can prevent PTB or mitigate the severity and consequences of PTB.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p><b>Criteria for cases</b> <ul> <p><b>A. Inclusion:</b> All mothers who delivered preterm babies (&lt;37 weeks of gestation, regardless of birthweight) at Boston Medical Center (BMC) were eligible as cases for the study.</p> <p><b>B. Exclusion:</b> We excluded pregnancies as a result of <i>in vitro</i> fertilization or multiple gestation, and fetuses with chromosomal abnormalities or major birth defects. Additional exclusion criteria include mothers with congenital or acquired uterus lesions or with a known history of incompetent cervix, and preterm births due to maternal trauma (e.g., car accident).</p> </ul> </p> <p><b>Criteria for controls</b></p> <p>Those mothers who delivered term (&gt;37 weeks of gestation) babies at BMC and frequency matched with case mothers on race, age (&#177; 5 years), baby&#39;s gender and parity were eligible as controls for this GWAS.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="11779261"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="14976157"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16642433"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="16681991"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17437198"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18320229"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19020903"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19403498"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19446788"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19529994"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20308216"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21814537"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="25140923"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21576006"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22015876"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21847588"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23592670"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23850528"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="24779674"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="24519298"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="He H, Butz A,  Keet CA, Minkovitz CS, Hong X, Caruso DM, Pearson C, Cohen RT,  Wills-Karp M, Zuckerman B,  Hughes ME,  Wang X." title="Preterm Birth with Childhood Asthma: The Role of Degree of Prematurity and Asthma Definitions." journal="American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, 2015, <i>in press</i>."/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Infant, Premature"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Premature Birth"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Gestational Age"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Xiaobin Wang, MD, MPH, ScD, Zanvyl Krieger Professor</AttName>
			<Institution>Director, Center on the Early Life Origins of Disease, Department of Population, Family and Reproductive Health, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, and Professor of Pediatrics, John Hopkins University School of Medicine, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Barry Zuckerman, MD, Professor</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Pediatrics, Boston Medical Center, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Linda Heffner, MD, Professor</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Boston Medical Center, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Xin Liu, MD, PhD, Assistant Professor</AttName>
			<Institution>Mary Ann and J. Milburn Smith Child Health Research Program, Department of Pediatrics, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Hui-Ju Tsai, PhD, Assistant Professor</AttName>
			<Institution>Mary Ann and J. Milburn Smith Child Health Research Program, Department of Pediatrics, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine, Chicago, IL, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Xiumei Hong, MD, PhD, Assistant Scientist</AttName>
			<Institution>Center on the Early Life Origins of Disease, Department of Population, Family and Reproductive Health, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Guoying Wang, MD, PhD, Assistant Scientist</AttName>
			<Institution>Center on the Early Life Origins of Disease, Department of Population, Family and Reproductive Health, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Hongkai Ji, PhD, Associate Professor</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Biostatistics, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Project Coordinators">
			<AttName>Colleen Pearson</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Pediatrics, Boston Medical Center, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Project Coordinators">
			<AttName>Deanna Caruso</AttName>
			<Institution>Center on the Early Life Origins of Disease, Department of Population, Family and Reproductive Health, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Lab Manager">
			<AttName>Guoying Wang, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Center on the Early Life Origins of Disease, Department of Population, Family and Reproductive Health, Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>2R01HD041702</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Child Health and Human Development, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Genotyping Institute">
			<AttName>CIDR</AttName>
			<Institution>Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for CIDR Genotyping">
			<AttName>HHSN268200782096C. NIH contract &quot;High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&quot;</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for CIDR Genotyping">
			<AttName>HHSN268201100011I. NIH contract &quot;High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&quot;</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The parent population for this GWAS is the Boston Birth Cohort (BBC), which was initiated by Dr. Xiaobin Wang in 1998 at the Boston Medical Center with the support of Dr. Barry Zuckerman, the former Chairman of the Department of Pediatrics and the Joel Alpert faculty development award by the Department of Pediatrics, Boston Medical Center. Subsequently, the Boston Birth Cohort was supported by multiple sources of funding, the March of Dimes Birth Defects Foundation (20-FY98-0701, 20-FY02-56 and #21-FY07-605, PI: Xiaobin Wang); and the National Institutes of Environmental Health Sciences (R21 ES011666, PI: Xiaobin Wang), and Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (2R01HD41702, PI: Xiaobin Wang).</p> <p>We are indebted to many individuals who have contributed to the parent study and/or this GWAS of preterm birth, including Barry Zuckerman, Howard Bauchner, Colleen Pearson, Deanna Caruso, Xiumei Hong, Guoying Wang, Xin Liu, Hui-Ju Tsai, Nan Laird, L-J Wei, Louise Ryan, Jerry Klein, Phillip Stubblefield, Linda Heffner, Milton Kotelchuck, Michael Corwin, Paul Wise, Michael Kramer, Gary Kaufman, John Kasznica, Sandra Cerda, Daniel Weeks, Yunxian Yu, Shanchun Zhang, Fengxiu Ouyang, Lingling Fu, Natalie Cruz, Shannon Kiang, Katherin Ortiz, Maria Kroll, Monica Cintron, Xin Xu, Xiping Xu, Tim Niu, Ke Hao, Lin Wang, Xin Chen, Scott Venners, Lester Arguelles, Karen Mestan, Nana Matoba, Jessica L Schanta, Marie Jean, Max Paillaint, Kathleen Delmas, Emault Louis, Alison Little, Yohanna Mendez, Munish Gupta, Joel Sawadi, Claire Joseph, Anthony Bonzagni, Stephanie Apollon, Laurie Natale, Peters Otlans, Patricia Francisco, Jhenane Joseph, Jared Berkowitz, Maggie Francis, Rachel Sajous, Guang Li, Ang Li, Qing Wang, Schubert Bijous, Maria Eguez, Weili Chang, Ivan Villon, Roberto Beltran, Kimberlee Bulger, Nahomy Calixte, Ivette Martinez, Winnie Mei, Kristin McPhillips, Mathis Bauchner, Ann Ramsey, Douglas Rockwell, Zhu Chen, Yuelong Ji, Kristin Schwartz, Anastacia Wahl, Hilena Addis, Bolanle Ajao, Liliana Burdea, Elisabeth Carrigg, Ifta Choiriyyah, Mallory Clifford, Monica D&#39;Ambrogi, Jane Daniels, Christopher DeEspinosa, Rebeca Diaz-Reyes, Rajelin Escondo, Emily Frankis, Emily Hu, Sato Kakihara, Anna Kropornicka, Suegene Lee, Anne Lilly, Samantha Margaritas, Molly McGlone, Miriam Million, Kyla Mor, Christiana Obeng, Anita Patel, Samantha Pollack, Yaritza Rodriguez, Edna Romero, Larisa Smith, Xuan Zhang, Marcela Ziemianski. We are particularly indebted to the nursing staff of Labor and Delivery at the Boston Medical Center for their long-standing assistance in data collection. We are grateful for the generous help and support of all of the Boston Medical Center participating mothers.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-PTB-RD" longName="Disease-Specific (Preterm Birth, RD)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NICHD</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NICHD-DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000332.v3.p2_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000332.v3.p2
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000332.v3.p2" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Preterm Birth, RD)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-PTB-RD</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Preterm Birth and related disorders.
Use of data is limited to genetic and biomedical research on preterm birth, and related complications of pregnancy such as preeclampsia, fetal growth restriction, etc. and their consequences on the neonate.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
