<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000777.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000777.v1.p1" createDate="2014-07-11" modDate="2014-07-28">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Michelle Winn, MD</td><td>Department of Medicine, Division of Nephrology, Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>5R01DK094987</td><td>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>NIDDK Gene discovery in FSGS</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK) Gene Discovery in Autosomal Dominant Focal Segmental Glomerulosclerosis (FSGS)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case Set</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis (FSGS) is a frequent cause of end-stage renal disease. The pathogenesis of FSGS has not been precisely defined and there are no consistently effective treatments. Recent studies identifying causal genes in rare, inherited FSGS, including our own study, have associated mutations in at least six genes with familial FSGS, and each discovery has clarified molecular mechanisms of glomerular injury. To build on this productive line of inquiry, we have ascertained and carefully characterized 118 families with familial FSGS. We have screened the remainder of our families for mutations in genes known to cause FSGS and identified the causal mutations in an additional 6 kindreds; the genetic basis of disease in the remaining 111 families is unknown. The objective of this proposal is to use this valuable and unique family resource to systematically identify causal genes for familial FSGS. Limitations of current conventional linkage and positional cloning approaches include their requirement for large, multiplex families. In addition, narrowing candidate areas in traditional linkage analysis can be difficult due to large regions that lack recombination events and hence these regions have required cumbersome and lengthy screening for causative mutations. Powerful new genetic tools can facilitate this screening process and improve variant discovery in smaller families. In particular, efficient whole-exome sequencing, the targeted capture of protein-coding gene sequences, should be particularly useful in our studies since most Mendelian disorders are caused by mutations affecting exomes of the target gene. Thus, by combining genome-wide linkage analysis (GWLS) and whole-exome sequencing, we can maximize impact of our family data and accelerate identification of novel mutations in FSGS. In preliminary studies, we have used this combination to identify a novel variant in the WT1 (Wilms&#39; Tumor-1) gene in one FSGS family, and we have evidence suggesting it is the causal mutation. This success provides proof-of-concept and provides a roadmap of how genes will be identified and evaluated in the proposed studies. Our hypothesis is that causes of inherited FSGS in our cohort of families will be sequence variants in the coding region of genes not previously associated with familial FSGS. We aim to: 1) Use GWLS and whole-exome sequencing to identify genetic variants associated with familial FSGS. 2) Characterize functional consequences of candidate causative mutations and 3) Determine the prevalence in the Duke FSGS dataset of these new causative mutations identified in Aim 2. Any genes found to have causative mutations will be sequenced in the remaining families and take full advantage of our family resource. By combining genome-wide linkage analysis (GWLS), whole-exome sequencing, and characterization of variants&#39; functional consequences, we will significantly improve understanding of normal glomerular biology and of the pathogenesis of FSGS and related glomerular diseases. Moreover, our discoveries are likely to reveal new opportunities to improve therapy for a disease that currently has few effective treatments.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Inclusion criteria cases <ol> <li>At least two affected individuals in the family</li> <li>FSGS on renal biopsy without evidence of other systemic disease known to cause FSGS</li> <li>Family members with proteinuria and or chronic kidney disease</li> </ol> </p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Hall G, Gbadegesin R, Lavin P, et al." title="A Novel Missense Mutation of Wilms&#39; Tumor 1 causes Autosomal Dominant Focal Segmental Glomerulosclerosis" journal="Journal of the American Society of Nephrology. 2014. Accepted."/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Glomerulosclerosis, Focal Segmental"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Nephrotic Syndrome"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Kidney Failure, Chronic"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Michelle Winn, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Medicine, Division of Nephrology, Duke University, Durham, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>5R01DK094987</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU-IRB" longName="General Research Use (IRB)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIDDK</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIDDK Central Repository GWAS Data Access Committee</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000777.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000777.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000777.v1.p1" FileName="ModeNIDDKdbGaPlDUC_2010April7_FINAL_edited_for_format_and_links_2-2011.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use (IRB)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU-IRB</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>
  <Documents>
    <Document phd="phd004446.1" type="consent-form" createDate="2014-07-28" modDate="2014-07-28" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004446.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000777.v1.p1&amp;phd=4446">
      <OrigName>DUKECONSENTADULT2014.pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>Consent To Participate In A Research Study (Adults)</DisplayName>
      <Description>Consent To Participate In A Research Study (Adults)</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
    <Document phd="phd004447.1" type="consent-form" createDate="2014-07-28" modDate="2014-07-28" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004447.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000777.v1.p1&amp;phd=4447">
      <OrigName>DUKECONSENTMINOR2014.pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>Consent To Participate In A Research Study (Minors)</DisplayName>
      <Description>Consent To Participate In A Research Study (Minors)</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
    <Document phd="phd004448.1" type="questionnaire" createDate="2014-07-28" modDate="2014-07-28" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004448.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000777.v1.p1&amp;phd=4448">
      <OrigName>FSGS_clinical_hist_12648.pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>FSGS CLINICAL HISTORY</DisplayName>
      <Description>FSGS CLINICAL HISTORY</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
  </Documents>

  <Annotations>
    <DocumentPart phd="phd004446.1" sectionId="phd004446">
      <phvList>
        <phvRef variableId="202553"/>
      </phvList>
    </DocumentPart>
    <DocumentPart phd="phd004447.1" sectionId="phd004447">
      <phvList>
        <phvRef variableId="202553"/>
      </phvList>
    </DocumentPart>
    <DocumentPart phd="phd004448.1" sectionId="V8">
      <phvList>
        <phvRef variableId="202570"/>
      </phvList>
    </DocumentPart>
  </Annotations>



</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
