<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000272.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000272.v1.p1" createDate="2010-05-19" modDate="2010-09-20">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Elaine F. Remmers, PhD</td><td>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Ahmet Gul, MD</td><td>Faculty of Medicine-Division of Rheumatology, Istanbul University, Istanbul, Turkey</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Daniel L. Kastner, MD, PhD</td><td>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Genome-Wide Association Study of Beh&#231;et&#39;s Disease (Turkish)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases and Istanbul Faculty of Medicine Genome-wide Association Study of Beh&#231;et&#39;s Disease (Turkish)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p><b>Introduction</b><br/>Beh&#231;et&#39;s disease (BD) is a genetically complex multisystem disease of unknown etiology,  	characterized by recurrent inflammatory attacks affecting orogenital mucosa, eyes, skin, joints, blood vessels, and less  	frequently, the central nervous system and gastrointestinal tract.  Family studies suggest a genetically complex contribution  	to BD.  With the exception of HLA-B51, which explains less than 20% of the genetic risk, the identities of alleles that are  	responsible for the complex inheritance of this disease have remained unclear.</p>  	<p><b>Aim</b><br/>To identify genes that contribute to BD susceptibility.</p>  	<p><b>Methods</b><br/>A genome-wide association study was undertaken with 311,459 informative and high quality SNPs in a  	collection of 1215 BD patients and 1278 healthy controls from Turkey using a beadchip microarray assay (Infinium SNP  	genotype assay, Illumina).  HLA-B types were determined with a reverse sequence-specific oligonucleotide method (One Lambda).  	Regions with evidence for association were fine-mapped using Sequenom iPLEX gold assays.  Disease-associated SNPs were  	genotyped in additional ethnically matched case/control collections from diverse genetic backgrounds, including a total  	of 2430 cases and 2660 controls, using TaqMan SNP genotype assays.  Association data were combined in a meta-analysis  	of all the collections.</p>  	<p><b>Results</b><br/>We confirmed the known association with HLA-B51 and found evidence for a second, independent  	susceptibility locus in the Class I region of the MHC. In addition, we identified one SNP with genome-wide evidence for  	disease association (P &lt; 5.0 x 10<sup>-8</sup>) within the gene encoding the immunoregulatory cytokine, interleukin-10 (IL10). A  	meta-analysis of the data from all the collections established associations with the IL10 variant (rs1518111,  	P = 3.54 x 10<sup>-18</sup>, odds ratio 1.45 with 95% confidence interval 1.34 to 1.58) and with a variant located between the  	interleukin-23 receptor (IL23R) and interleukin 12 receptor &#946;2 (IL12RB2) genes (rs924080, P = 6.69 x 10<sup>-9</sup>, odds  	ratio 1.28 with 95% confidence interval 1.18 to 1.39). The disease-associated IL10 variant was associated with diminished  	mRNA expression and low protein production by cells obtained from healthy blood donors.</p>  	<p><b>Conclusions</b><br/>These data suggest that genetically encoded low production of IL-10 increases risk of BD and  	suggest novel interventional targets in the IL-10 and IL-23 pathways.</p>  	<p>Note: The submitted data are the genotypes of the 311,459 SNPs in 1215 cases and 1278 controls.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>All cases fulfilled International Study Group Criteria (International Study Group for Beh&#231;et&#39;s disease. 1990.  	Lancet 335:1078-1080, PMID: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/1970380" target="_blank">1970380</a>).</p>  	<p>Excluded individuals with a diagnosis of Familial Mediterranean Fever.</p>  	<p>Excluded all first, second, and third degree relatives (identified by genetic relatedness).</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="1970380"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20622878"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Behcet Syndrome"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Elaine F. Remmers, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Ahmet Gul, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Faculty of Medicine-Division of Rheumatology, Istanbul University, Istanbul, Turkey</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Daniel L. Kastner, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>JARDE</DacName>
      <DacFullName>Joint NIAMS-NIDCR Data Access Committee</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>jardedac@mail.nih.gov</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl>http://grants.nih.gov/grants/gwas</DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000272.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
               http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000272.v1.p1
            </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000272.v1.p1" FileName="Behcets_Kastner_DUC.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>This dataset may be used for any type of biomedical research.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>

<Analyses>
	<Analysis pha="2888" genomeBuild="37.1" snpBuild="131" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
A genome-wide association study of Beh&#231;et&#8217;s disease was undertaken in the Turkish population because of the high disease prevalence (approximately 4 per 1000) in that population.  The cases were consecutive consenting patients from the Beh&#231;et&#8217;s Disease Clinic of Istanbul Faculty of Medicine, Division of Rheumatology, that met the Beh&#231;et&#8217;s Disease International Study Group Criteria (recurrent oral ulcers plus 2 or more of the following: genital ulcers, typical defined eye lesions, typical defined skin lesions, or a positive pathergy test).  Healthy controls were selected among blood bank donors or healthy volunteers to match by geographic location the place of birth of the patients.  All healthy controls were questioned for the absence of recurrent oral aphthous ulcers or other Beh&#231;et&#8217;s disease-related manifestations, or a family history for Beh&#231;ets disease.  After applying quality control metrics, the analysis included 1215 patients with Beh&#231;et&#8217;s disease and 1278 healthy controls.
		]]></Description>
		<Method>categorical analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="373339" snpBatchId="1049349">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/SNP/snp_viewBatch.cgi?sbid=1049349</VendorURL>
			<Platform>HumanCNV370-Quadv3</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
</Analyses>

</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
