<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000217.v2.p1" parentStudy="phs000217.v2.p1" createDate="2013-07-25" modDate="2013-07-29">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Fu-Ren Zhang, PhD</td><td>Shandong Provincial Institute of Dermatology and Venereology, Shandong Academy of Medical Science, Shandong, China</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Jianjun Liu, PhD</td><td>Genome Institute of Singapore, Singapore</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Genome-Wide Association Study of Leprosy and Dapsone Hypersensitivity Syndrome (DHS)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genome-Wide Association Study of Leprosy and Dapsone Hypersensitivity Syndrome (DHS) in Chinese population</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p><b>Leprosy GWAS</b></p> <p>Leprosy is a chronic infectious disease caused by <i>Mycobacterium leprae</i> (<i>M. leprae</i>). Due to <i>M. leprae&#39;s</i> narrow host range and an inability to be cultured <i>in vitro</i>, the biological investigation of this disease has been difficult. Host genetic factors have been suggested to play an important role in disease development, but few have been identified.</p> <p>In this study, we attempted to identify the host genetic factors by performing a two-stage genome-wide association study (GWAS) in Chinese population. The initial genome-wide scan was done by genotyping 706 patients and 1225 controls using the Illumina HumanHap610 BeadChip, and the follow-up study was performed by genotyping 93 SNPs in three independent samples consisting of 3254 cases and 5955 controls. We identified significant association (P&lt;10-10) within six genes CCDC122 (13q14), C13orf31 (13q14), NOD2(16q12), TNFSF15 (9q32), HLA-DR (6p21) and RIPK2 (8q21), and suggestive association (P=5.68x10-6) within LRRK2 (12q12). We also revealed suggestive evidence for C13orf31, LRRK2, NOD2 and RIPK2 to show stronger association in the multibacillary form than the paucibacillary form of leprosy. Our findings highlight the importance of the innate immune response, particularly NOD2-mediated signaling, in leprosy and suggests a new therapeutic target for leprosy.</p> <p><b>DHS GWAS</b></p> <p>Dapsone (DDS), as both an antibiotic and an anti-inflammatory agent, has been widely used for preventing and treating pathogen-caused infectious diseases and chronic inflammatory diseases. Currently, about 0.5-3.6% of individuals treated with DDS develop severe dapsone hypersensitivity syndrome (DHS) and the mortality rate is up to about 11-13%. However, until now, no tests are available to predict the risk of DHS.</p> <p>To identify the genetic risk factors of DHS, we performed a two-stage GWAS in Chinese population. In this study, the initial genome-wide scan was done by genotyping 39 DHS cases and 833 controls using Illumina Human 660W-Quad Beadchips and imputed human leukocyte antigen (HLA) molecules. Validation was performed by genotyping 24 SNPs using the Sequenom MassARRAY platform in additional 31 DHS cases and 1,089 controls through genotyping and 32 four-digit HLA-B alleles in an independent series of 37 DHS cases and 201 controls through Roche 454 sequencing. We identified significant association (OR =6.18, P=3.84x10-13) with SNP rs2844573, which located between the HLA-B and MICA loci. <i>HLA-B*13:01</i> was confirmed to be a strong risk factor for DHS (OR =20.53, P=6.84x10-25) and responsible for the association at rs2844573. The presence of <i>HLA-B*13:01</i> had a sensitivity of 85.5% and specificity of 85.7% as a predictor for DHS, and its absence can reduce the risk by 7 fold (from 1.4% to 0.2%). <i>HLA-B*13:01</i> is strongly associated with the development of DHS and can be used as a risk predictor of DHS in the individuals of Chinese and other Asian populations.</p> <p>Here, the summary statistics from the two genome-wide association analyses were published.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p><b>Leprosy GWAS</b></p> <p>The GWAS sample consisted of 738 persons affected by leprosy and 1276 controls of Chinese Han. All the subjects were recruited from Central China (Anhui, Shandong and Jiangsu provinces) in 2005 to 2008. The diagnosis of leprosy was based on medical records stored in local leprosy control institutions and clinical assessments at the time of blood taken (looking for evidence of leprosy such as claw hand, lagophthalmos or foot drop, etc). The controls were healthy individuals without leprosy, autoimmune and systemic disorders and family history of leprosy (including first-, second- and third-degree relatives). Demographic characteristics were also collected. All the cases and controls were recruited using the uniform criteria and matched regarding to ethnic origin and geographic area. The ethnicity of all the subjects was determined based on self-reported ancestry. All the subjects were recruited with written informed consent, and the study was approved by the institutional IRB committees at the Shandong Provincial Institute of Dermatology and Venereology, Shandong Academy of Medical Science and the Anhui Medical University.</p> <p><b>DHS GWAS</b></p> <p>There were 39 DHS cases used in the discovery stage analysis, and all the cases received DDS as a part of MDT and were diagnosed to meet the diagnostic criteria of DHS. The controls included 955 surviving leprosy patients who were also treated with DDS as a part of MDT for at least 6 months, but whose DHS status could not be determined due to insufficient medical information. The study was performed in 2010-2012.</p> <p>All the cases and controls were recruited using the uniform criteria and matched regarding to ethnic origin and geographic area. All the subjects were recruited with written informed consent, and the study was approved by the institutional IRB committees at the Shandong Provincial Institute of Dermatology and Venereology, Shandong Academy of Medical Science.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20018961"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Fu-Ren Zhang, et al." title="Identification of HLA-B*13:01 as a Risk Predictor for Dapsone-induced Hypersensitivity Syndrome" journal="N Engl J Med. Accepted."/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Leprosy"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Dapsone"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Drug Hypersensitivity"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Fu-Ren Zhang, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Shandong Provincial Institute of Dermatology and Venereology, Shandong Academy of Medical Science, Shandong, China</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Jianjun Liu, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Genome Institute of Singapore, Singapore</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>no</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="100" shortName="Analysis" longName="Analysis only"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIAID</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIAID DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000217.v2.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000217.v2.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000217.v2.p1" FileName="LeprosydbGAP-final-myg.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Leprosy Studies Only</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>LSO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Aggregate level data to be used for the study of leprosy only</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>

<Analyses>
	<Analysis pha="2872" genomeBuild="36.3" snpBuild="129" analysisType="">
		<Description><![CDATA[
A GWAS of leprosy was performed by genotyping 738 patients and 1276 controls.  As quality control, 85056 SNPs were removed due to low genotype call rate (&#60;90%), or low minor allele frequency (MAF &#60;1%) in either cases or controls, or showing significant deviation from Hardy-Weinberg Equilibrium in the controls (p-value &#8804; 10-7).  In addition, all the intensity-only SNPs and the SNPs on the X, Y and mitochondria chromosomes were also excluded.  After removing 30 samples due to their low call rates (&#60;0.98), we examined potential genetic relatedness among the remaining 724 cases and 1260 controls, leading to the removal of additional 32 controls and 18 cases as &#8242;potential&#8242; familial relatives (up to second-degree relatives).  The remaining 1934 samples (706 cases and 1228 controls) were subsequently assessed for population stratification using a principal component analysis (PCA).  PCA analysis was performed in two steps. First, the analysis was performed by combining the 1934 samples with 206 reference HapMap samples (Yoruba in Ibadan, Nigeria (YRI) (57), Japanese in Tokyo, Japan (JPT) (44), Chinese Han in Beijing, China (CHB) (45) and CEPH (CEU) (45)). 3 population outliers were identified and removed.  Afterwards, the second PCA analysis was performed on the 1931 samples of GWA study (706 cases, 1225 controls), which suggested some genetic mismatch between the 706 cases and 1225 controls.  To minimize the adverse impact of population stratification, we removed 711 control samples that did not match well with the cases, leaving a matched sample of 706 cases and 514 controls. All the patients and controls were self-reported Han Chinese and recruited from Eastern China. The leprosy cases were diagnosed based on consensus by at least two dermatologists. Clinical subtypes and age at onset of disease were collected from medical records. The controls were healthy individuals without leprosy, autoimmune and systemic disorders and family history of leprosy (including first-, second- and third-degree relatives). Demographic characteristics were collected from both the cases and the controls through questionnaires. All the cases and controls were recruited using uniform criteria and matched regarding to ethnic origin and geographic region of recruitment.
		]]></Description>
		<Method>Genome-wide association</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="599011" snpBatchId="1048904">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina Human610-Quadv1_B chip</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Human610-Quadv1_B</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
	<Analysis pha="3828" genomeBuild="37.1" snpBuild="132" analysisType="">
		<Description> A GWAS of dapsone hypersensitivity syndrome (DHS) was performed by genotyping 39 DHS cases and 955 controls using Illumina Human 660W-Quad BeadChips. After quality control filtering, there were 39 DHS cases, 833 controls and 430,276 SNPs remaining for association analysis. All the DHS cases received DDS as a part of Multi Drug Treatment (MDT) and were diagnosed based on the criteria of DHS.  The controls were also treated with DHS as a part of MDT for at least 6 months, but whose DHS status could not be determined due to insufficient medical information. Demographic characteristics were collected from both the cases and the controls through questionnaires. The DHS cases and controls were matched in terms of geographic origin and ethnicity.</Description>
		<Method>categorical analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="599011" snpBatchId="1048904">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>Illumina Human610-Quadv1_B chip</VendorURL>
			<Platform>Human610-Quadv1_B</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
</Analyses>

</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
