<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000547.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000547.v1.p1" createDate="2012-09-12" modDate="2013-03-08">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Weinshilboum, Richard, MD</td><td>Mayo Clinics, Rochester, Minnesota, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>U01 HG005160</td><td>GARNET: Genomics and Randomized Trials Network, National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source for Genotyping</td><td>U01HG004438-01</td><td>NIH GEI Grant &#39;JH/CIDR Genotyping for Genome-Wide Association Studies&#39;, National 			Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>A Genome-Wide Association Study in Breast Cancer Patients from the SUCCESS Trial</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>A Genome-Wide Association Study in Breast Cancer Patients from the Prospectively Randomized SUCCESS Trial</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Prospective</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Randomized</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Phase III</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The SUCCESS-A Study (<a href="http://www.success-studie.de">http://www.success-studie.de</a>) is a randomized Phase III study of response to treatment of early primary breast cancer with adjuvant therapy after surgical resection. The primary outcome is disease-free survival and secondary outcomes are overall survival and toxicity. The study design includes comparison of two pairs of treatment regimes performed in sequence. The first randomization contrasts treatment with and without Gemcitabine (3 cycles of Epirubicin-Fluorouracil-Cyclophosphamide(FEC)-chemotherapy, followed by 3 cycles of Docetaxel(D)-chemotherapy versus 3 cycles of Epirubicin-Fluorouracil-Cyclophosphamide(FEC), followed by 3 cycles of Gemcitabine-Docetaxel(DG)-chemotherapy). The second randomization contrasts treatment with Zoledronate for two versus five years. Patients were recruited from 2005 to 2007 and a total of 3754 patients were included from 250 study sites across Germany. Genome-wide SNP microarray data and phenotype outcomes for the first phase of the study (treatment with and without Gemcitabine) are included in the GARNET (Genomics and Randomized Trials Network) pharmacogenomic study in this dbGaP submission. (The Zoledronate treatments are still underway).</p> <p>SUCCESS-A is a an open-label, multicenter, 2x2 factorial design, randomized controlled, Phase III study comparing the disease free survival after randomization in patients treated with 3 cycles of Epirubicin-Fluorouracil-Cyclophosphamide(FEC)-chemotherapy, followed by 3 cycles of Docetaxel(D)-chemotherapy versus 3 cycles of Epirubicin-Fluorouracil-Cyclophosphamide(FEC), followed by 3 cycles of Gemcitabine-Docetaxel(DG)-chemotherapy, and to compare the disease free survival after randomization in patients treated with 2 years of Zoledronate versus 5 years of Zoledronate in patients with early primary breast cancer. Patients were required to have histopathological proof of axillary lymph node metastases (pN1-3) or high risk node negative, defined as: pT&#62;2 or histopathological grade 3, or age , &#8804; 35 or negative hormone receptor, but were not allowed to have evidence of distant disease. Patients were entered into the study no later than 6 weeks after complete resection of the primary tumor. No antineoplastic treatment other than surgical treatment, the defined cytotoxic and endocrine treatment, and radiotherapy was allowed prior to study entry and during the course of the study. After surgery, leading to complete resection of the invasive and intraductal components of the primary tumor, patients were randomized to one of the following two treatments for the first phase of the project (which is included in this GARNET pharmacogenomics study):</p> <p><b>AA</b>: 3 cycles of 5-Fluorouracil 500 mg/m&#178; i.v. body surface area and Epirubicin 100 mg/m&#178; i.v. and Cyclophosphamide 500 mg/m&#178; i.v., (FEC100), each administered on day 1, repeated on day 22, subsequently followed by 3 cycles of Docetaxel 75 mg/m&#178; body surface area i.v. (D), and Gemcitabine 1000 mg/m&#178; i.v. (30 min infusion) (G), administered on day 1, followed by Gemcitabine 1000 mg/m&#178; i.v. (30 min infusion) on day 8, repeated on day22</p> <p><b>AB</b>: 3 cycles of 5-Fluorouracil 500 mg/m&#178; i.v. body surface area and Epirubicin 100 mg/m&#178; i.v. and Cyclophosphamide 500 mg/m&#178; i.v., (FEC100), each administered on day 1, repeated on day 22, subsequently followed by 3 cycles of Docetaxel 100 mg/m&#178; body surface area i.v. (D), administered on day 1, repeated on day 22</p> <p>A second randomization was made for assigning patients to one of the following two subsequent treatments for the second phase of the project (NOT included in the pharmacogenetic study in this dbGaP submission):</p> <p><b>BA</b>: Zoledronic acid 4 mg i.v., every 3 months for the duration of two years, subsequently followed by zoledronic acid 4 mg i.v., every 6 months for the duration of additional three years</p> <p><b>BB</b>: Zoledronic acid 4 mg i.v., every 3 months for the duration of two years</p> <p>Patients with positive hormone receptor status (&#8805;10% positively stained cells for estrogen and/or progesterone) of the primary tumor were recommended to receive Tamoxifen treatment 20 mg p.o. per day for 2 years, after the end of chemotherapy . Subsequent to chemotherapy, postmenopausal patients with positive hormone receptor status were recommended to be treated with Anastrozole (Arimidex&#174;) 1 mg p.o. for additional 3 years, premenopausal patients will continue Tamoxifen treatment for those additional 3 years. In addition to tamoxifen, all patients with positive hormone receptor status of the primary tumor and under the age of 40 or restart of menstrual bleeding within 6 months after the completion of cytostatic treatment or with premenopausal hormone levels as defined below were recommended to receive Goserelin (Zoladex&#174;) 3.6 mg subcutaneously every 4 weeks over a period of 2 years following chemotherapy. Premenopausal endocrine status will be assumed, if the following serum levels are met: LH &#60; 20 mIE/ml, FSH &#60; 20 mIE/ml and E2 &#62; 20 pg/ml. Endocrine therapy will start after the end of chemotherapy.</p> <p>All patients with breast conserving therapy or more than 3 axillary lymph node metastases or in the following cases after mastectomy will receive adjuvant radiotherapy: T3/T4-carcinoma, T2-carcinoma &#62; 3 cm, multicentric tumor growth, lymphangiosis carcinomatosa or vessel involvement, involvement of the pectoralis fascia or a safety margin &#60; 5 mm. Radiotherapy was usually performed after the chemotherapy and parallel to the beginning of the zoledronic acid therapy.</p> <p>Initially, DNA was extracted for performing SNP microarray assays using blood collected at baseline prior to the first randomization. However, the first set of SNP microarray results indicated a quality problem with approximately 50% of the DNA samples. A majority of the problematic samples were replaced with DNA extracted from redrawn blood. The remaining problematic samples were &#39;restored&#39; using an Illumina FFPE Restoration procedure. A total of 3322 subjects (1638 from arm AA and 1684 from arm AB) were successfully genotyped. Among those, 1771 were from original blood samples, 1092 from redrawn blood samples and 459 from restored blood samples.</p> <p>The SUCCESS-A study is part of the Genomics and Randomized Trials Network (GARNET, <a href="http://www.garnetstudy.org">http://www.garnetstudy.org</a>) funded by the National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI). The overarching goal is to identify novel genetic factors that contribute to disease-free survival for breast cancer patients using different forms of chemotherapy through large-scale genome-wide association studies of treatment response in randomized clinical trials. The study was conducted at the University Hospital Erlangen, Friedrich-Alexander University Erlangen-Nuremberg, Germany. Genotyping was performed at the Johns Hopkins University Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR). Data cleaning and harmonization were performed at the GARNET Coordinating Center at the University of Washington.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Patients may be <b>included</b> in the study only if they meet <b>all</b> the following criteria: <ol> <li>Primary epithelial invasive carcinoma of the breast pT1-4, pM0</li> <li>Histopathological proof of axillary lymph node metastases (pN1-3) <b>or</b> high risk pN0/NX, defined as: pT &#8805; 2 <b><i>or</i></b> histopathological grade 3 <b><i>or</i></b> age &#8804; 35 <b><i>or</i></b> negative hormone receptor status</li> <li>Complete resection the primary tumor with margins of resection free of invasive carcinoma not more than 6 weeks ago</li> <li>Females &#8805; 18 years of age</li> <li>Performance Status &#8804; 2 on ECOG-Scale</li> <li>Adequate bone marrow reserve: leucocytes &#8805; 3.0 x 109/l and platelets &#8805; 100 x109/l</li> <li>Bilirubin within one fold of the reference laboratory normal range, ASAT (SGOT), ALAT (SGPT) and AP within 1,5 fold of the reference laboratory normal range for patients t</li> <li>Intention of regular follow-up visits for the duration of the study</li> <li>Ability to understand the nature of the study and to give written informed Consent</li> </ol> <ol start="10"> <p>Patients will be <b>excluded</b> from the study for <b>any</b> of the following reasons:</p> <li>Inflammatory breast cancer</li> <li>Previous or concomitant cytotoxic or other systemic antineoplastic treatment which is not part of or allowed within this study</li> <li>History of treatment or disease affecting bone metabolism (e.g. Paget disease, primary hyperparathyroidism)</li> <li>Prior treatment with bisphosphonates within the last 6 months</li> <li>Severe renal insufficiency as evidenced by creatinine clearance &#60; 30 ml/min as calculated using the Cockcroft-Gault formula:</li> <li>Second primary malignancy (except in situ carcinoma of the cervix or adequately treated basal cell carcinoma of the skin)</li> <li>Cardiomyopathy with impaired ventricular function (NYHA &#62; II), cardiac arrythmias influencing LVEF and requiring medication, history of myocardial infarction or angina pectoris within the last 6 months, or arterial hypertension not being controlled by medication</li> <li>infarction or angina pectoris within the last 6 months, or arterial hypertension not being controlled by medication</li> <li>Use of any investigational agent within 3 weeks prior to inclusion</li> <li>Patients in pregnancy or breast feeding (in premenopausal women anticonception has to be assured: intra uterine devices, surgical methods of sterilization, or, in hormone unsensitive tumors only, oral, subcutaneous or transvaginal hormonal, non estrogen containing contraceptives)</li> <li>Current active dental problems including infection of the teeth or jawbone (maxilla or mandibular); dental or fixture trauma, or a current or prior diagnosis of osteonecrosis of the jaw (ONJ), of exposed bone in the mouth, or of slow healing after dental procedures.</li> <li>Recent (within 6 weeks) or planned dental or jaw surgery (e.g. extraction, implants)</li> </ol> </p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Breast Neoplasms"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Weinshilboum, Richard, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Mayo Clinics, Rochester, Minnesota, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>U01 HG005160</AttName>
			<Institution>GARNET: Genomics and Randomized Trials Network, National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping">
			<AttName>U01HG004438-01</AttName>
			<Institution>NIH GEI Grant &#39;JH/CIDR Genotyping for Genome-Wide Association Studies&#39;, National 			Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects."/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="BCETC" longName="Breast cancer, study drug efficacy and toxicity, and covariates"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHGRI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Human Genome Research Institute</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000547.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000547.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000547.v1.p1" FileName="GARNET_DUC_SUCCESS_A-updated_10.3.10.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Breast cancer, study drug efficacy and toxicity, and covariates</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>BCETC</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Limited to research within the study objectives, which are the efficacy of the study drugs and toxicity of the study drugs, quality of life and association with co-variates which have an influence on these outcome data. SUCCESS A is a breast cancer clinical trial. Study drugs include 5-flurouracil-epirubicin-cyclophosphamide (FEC), docetaxel and gemcitabine. Covariates include: metastatic axillary lymph node involvement, hormone receptor status, menopausal status, age at treatment, CYP2D6 genotype. Outcomes include: breast cancer-free survival and overall survival.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>
  <Documents>
    <Document phd="phd004143.1" type="protocol" createDate="2013-01-02" modDate="2013-01-04" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004143.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000547.v1.p1&amp;phd=4143">
      <OrigName>PART1_StudienprotokollSuccess_(Weinshilboum).pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>SUCCESS-Trial Protocol Part 1</DisplayName>
      <Description>SUCCESS-Trial Protocol Part 1</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
    <Document phd="phd004144.1" type="consent-form" createDate="2013-01-02" modDate="2013-01-04" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004144.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000547.v1.p1&amp;phd=4144">
      <OrigName>SUCCESS Consent Form.pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>SUCCESS Consent Form</DisplayName>
      <Description>SUCCESS Consent Form</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
    <Document phd="phd004145.1" type="consent-form" createDate="2013-01-02" modDate="2013-01-04" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004145.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000547.v1.p1&amp;phd=4145">
      <OrigName>SUCCESS Data Protection Consent Form.pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>SUCCESS Data Protection Consent Form</DisplayName>
      <Description>SUCCESS Data Protection Consent Form</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
    <Document phd="phd004146.1" type="consent-form" createDate="2013-01-02" modDate="2013-01-04" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004146.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000547.v1.p1&amp;phd=4146">
      <OrigName>SUCCESS Patient Information.pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>SUCCESS Patient Information</DisplayName>
      <Description>SUCCESS Patient Information</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
  </Documents>



</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
