<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
	<Project/>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000255.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000255.v1.p1" createDate="2010-04-26" modDate="2011-04-01">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Ellen Li, MD, PhD</td><td>Washington University St. Louis, St. Louis, MO, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>UH2 DK083994</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Effect of Crohn&#39;s Disease Risk Alleles on Enteric Microbiota</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Effect of Crohn&#39;s Disease Risk Alleles on Enteric Microbiota</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>This UH2/UH3 demonstration project entitled "Effects of Crohn&#39;s disease risk alleles on enteric microbiota" is 	focused on characterizing intestinal associated microbiota in patients with ileal Crohn&#39;s disease (ileal CD), 	ulcerative colitis (UC) and control patients without inflammatory bowel diseases (non-IBD).  We hypothesize that 	genetic factors that affect Paneth cell function, contribute to compositional changes in intestinal microbiota. 	These changes in microbiota may lead to reduction of protective commensal organisms and increased numbers of 	aggressive organisms that incite intestinal inflammation. This hypothesis is being tested by high throughput 16S 	rRNA sequence analysis of de-identified ileal and colonic tissues that have been archived at Washington University 	St. Louis, University of North Carolina, Mount Sinai Hospital and the Cleveland Clinic.  Multivariate analysis of 	the metagenomic data will be conducted with genotyping metadata (highly reproducible CD risk alleles, including NOD2 	and ATG16L1) and phenotyping metadata (e.g. age, gender, race, body mass index, medications and smoking.)</p> 	<p>Shotgun sequencing will be performed on selected fecal specimens linked to ileal tissues to identify additional, 	or auxiliary, or synergistic pathogenic factors or other functional changes in the microbiome. Because members of 	this research team have observed that a chronic viral infection is required for the Paneth cell defect in Atg16l1 	hypomorphic mice, a major focus of these studies will be towards identifying potential viral triggers for the 	defective Paneth cell phenotype in individuals harboring the ATG16L1 risk allele.  Novel genetic probes for 	protective and aggressive organisms will be developed by mining bacterial genome and shotgun sequencing data. 	Genomic sequences will be produced for candidate protective and aggressive strains (e.g. adherent-invasive 	strains of E. coli) isolated from human intestinal tissues where there is limited existing genome information. 	Quantitative qPCR assays using the novel as well as established genetic probes will be conducted to test the 	hypothesis that an imbalance between protective and aggressive organisms is associated with genetic factors that 	affect Paneth cell function.</p> 	<p>Our combined expertise in multiple disciplines across multiple institutions, our demonstrated ability to collect 	a large number of well-phenotyped samples with longitudinal clinical information that will be linked to host 	response and morphologic studies, and our consortium&#39;s capacity for high-throughput sequencing will be 	used to investigate how alterations in human microbiome relate to CD risk alleles and CD pathogenesis.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Inclusion: 		<ol> 			<li>Existing ileal Crohn&#39;s disease, nonileal inflammatory bowel diseases (Crohn&#39;s colitis, 			ulcerative colitis, indeterminate colitis) and control non-inflammatory bowel disease specimens 			archived within the Washington University Digestive Diseases Research Core Center Tissue Procurement 			Facility.</li> 			<li>Existing ileal Crohn&#39;s disease specimens archived at the University of North Carolina are from 			clinical trial NCT00609973.</li> 		</ol> 	</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Crohn Disease"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Colitis, Ulcerative"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Ellen Li, MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University St. Louis, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>UH2 DK083994</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="HMP" longName="Human Microbiome Research"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="BSDO" longName="Bacterial Sequence Data Only"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIDDK</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIDDK Central Repository GWAS Data Access Committee</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>niddk-dac@mail.nih.gov</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacFax>301-480-3510</DacFax>
      <DacUrl>http://www3.niddk.nih.gov/researchprograms/repositories/FAQ.shtml</DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000255.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
               http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000255.v1.p1
            </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000255.v1.p1" FileName="HMP_CrohnsRisk_Li.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Human Microbiome Research</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HMP</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Studies related to the human microbiome. Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>Bacterial Sequence Data Only</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>BSDO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Consented for bacterial, fungal and viral sequence release, not consented for phenotype or genotype data release. Sequence data generated from microbiome samples will be used only for the purpose of studying the microbial components of the microbiome and will not be used to make inferences about the human host DNA itself.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
