<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000383.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000383.v1.p1" createDate="2011-07-15" modDate="2011-07-15">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Olufunmilyao I. Olopade</td><td>University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>R01 CA142996</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>GWAS of Breast Cancer in the African Diaspora</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genome-Wide Association Study of Breast Cancer in the African Diaspora - the ROOT study</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The paucity of data on the genetic epidemiology of breast cancer for racial/ethnic groups other than those of European ancestry     hinders the development of innovative interventions to reduce health disparities. Women in the African Diaspora experience a     disproportionate burden of pre-menopausal breast cancer in comparison to all other races for reasons that remain unknown and     understudied. This higher proportion of early-onset breast cancer might suggest a stronger genetic component in these populations.     Genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have revealed several genetic loci that confer risk of breast cancer. Because all GWAS     started the discovery stage in women of European ancestry and replicated mainly in women of European ancestry, we propose a novel     approach for a GWAS in indigenous African women to identify alleles associated with breast cancer risk which will then be replicated     in other populations.  This innovative design builds on our current understanding of the etiologic heterogeneity in breast cancer     and the distribution of breast cancer molecular subtypes which differ between women of African ancestry and women of European ancestry.     The major objective of the proposed studies is to get to the "root" causes of breast cancer by identifying breast cancer risk alleles     in a pooled sample of women of African ancestry and to replicate our findings in other populations.</p>     <p>To achieve this objective, we conducted a case control study of breast cancer in women of African ancestry, including Africans     living in Nigeria, African Americans and African Barbadians. We will genotype ~3800 individuals using the Illumina HumanOmni2.5-Quad     platform.  We will conduct both standard and novel genetic analyses of the data to map genes associated with breast cancer     susceptibility, verify genotyping and carry out fine-mapping studies in genes or regions showing association with breast cancer risk,     and replicate in other African American and non-African American populations. By pooling unique resources from studies throughout     the African Diaspora, this study has the potential to identify risk alleles in several genes that contribute to increased     breast cancer risk and may have implications for early detection, prognosis and treatment of breast cancer in ALL women.     This should ultimately lead to improved outcomes for those who suffer a disproportionate burden of early-onset breast cancer.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Women of African descent, 18 years old and older.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Breast Neoplasms"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Olufunmilyao I. Olopade</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01 CA142996</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects."/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="3" shortName="HRGM" longName="Health Research and General Methods"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000383.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000383.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000383.v1.p1" FileName="BC_in_African_Diaspora_DUC.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="3">
        <ConsentName>Health Research and General Methods</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>HRGM</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the dataset is limited to scientific research relevant to learn about, prevent or treat health problems, including applications proposing analytical methods, software or other research tool development. Intelligence research, forensic research, and research on behaviors (alcohol or tobacco use, etc) are NOT acceptable uses of the data.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
