<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000912.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000912.v1.p1" createDate="2015-05-04" modDate="2015-05-12">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Elad Ziv, MD</td><td>University of California, San Francisco, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>R01CA120120</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>San Francisco Bay Area Latina Breast Cancer Study</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>San Francisco Bay Area Latina Breast Cancer Study</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>The genome-wide association study (GWAS) includes participants enrolled into two different studies. The first study, the San Francisco Bay Area Cancer Study (SFBCS) is a population-based case-control study of breast cancer conducted in the San Francisco Bay Area and included women ages 35-79 years from three racial/ethnic groups: Non-Hispanic whites, African Americans, and Hispanics/Latinas. For the GWAS, only Hispanic/Latina women were included. Women diagnosed with invasive breast cancer between 1995 and 2002 were identified through the Greater Bay Area Cancer Registry. Controls were identified by random digit dialing and were frequency-matched to cases by age in 5 year increments and by race/ethnicity. Hispanic/Latina ethnicity was assessed by self-report. 175 Hispanic/Latina cases and 307 Hispanic/Latina controls from the SFBCS had given adequate consent and provided biospecimens that were used in the GWAS to be included in this data submission.</p> <p>The second study is the Northern California site of the Breast Cancer Family Registry (NC-BCFR). This population-based family study recruited breast cancer cases ages 18-64 years diagnosed from 1995-2009 that were identified through the Greater Bay Area Cancer Registry. Cases included all women at increased genetic susceptibility for breast cancer who met one or more of the following criteria: (a) being diagnosed with breast cancer at age &#60;35 years; b) having a personal history of ovarian cancer or childhood cancer; (c) being diagnosed with two different breast cancers (bilateral breast cancers), with the first one diagnosed at age &#60;50 years; and d) having one or more first-degree relatives with breast cancer, ovarian cancer or childhood cancer. Cases not meeting these criteria were randomly sampled and racial/ethnic minorities were oversampled. Controls were recruited by random digit dialing and were matched by 5-year age increments and by race/ethnicity. For the current GWAS only Latina/Hispanic cases and controls were included. Latina/Hispanic ethnicity was assessed by self-report. 631 Hispanic/Latina cases and 61 Hispanic/Latina controls from the NC-BCFR had given adequate consent and provided biospecimens that were used in the GWAS to be included in this data submission.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Inclusion Criteria:<br/> Cases:<br/> San Francisco Bay Area Cancer Study: Women who are of self-reported Latina/Hispanic ethnicity with invasive breast cancer who lived in the 5 Bay Area Counties (San Francisco, San Mateo, Alameda, Santa Clara, Marin) ages 35-79. Cases were identified through the San Francisco Bay Area Cancer Registry </p> <p>Northern California Breast Cancer Family Registry: Women who are of self-reported Latina/Hispanic ethnicity who lived in the 5 Bay Area Counties (San Francisco, San Mateo, Alameda, Santa Clara, Marin) diagnosed with invasive breast cancer and had at least one of the following criteria: family history of at least one first degree relative with breast cancer, personal diagnosis of breast cancer at age 35 or younger, personal diagnosis of bilateral breast cancer. Cases were identified through the San Francisco Bay Area Cancer Registry</p> <p>Exclusion Criteria:<br/> Cases were excluded if their physician reported that they had a contraindication to participation in a research study, if they could not complete the informed consent or the questionnaire in English or Spanish<br/> Northern California Breast Cancer Family Registry: </p> <p>Controls:<br/> Controls were excluded if their physician reported that they had a contraindication to participation in a research study, if they could not complete the informed consent or the questionnaire in English or Spanish </p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19047150"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22228098"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="25327703"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Breast Neoplasms"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Receptors, Estrogen"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Receptors, Progesterone"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Elad Ziv, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of California, San Francisco, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01CA120120</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The San Francisco Bay Area Cancer Study recruited cases and controls between 199X and 200X. The Cancer Family Registry recruited cases and controls between 199X and 200X.</p> <p>The SFBCS was used to demonstrate that ancestry is associated with breast cancer risk (Fejerman et al Cancer Research 2008). The investigators used 106 ancestry informative markers to infer genetic ancestry for all of the women in the study. They found that European ancestry was associated with higher risk of breast cancer while Indigenous American ancestry was associated with lower risk.</p> <p>The GWAS was performed on stored biospecimens between 2008 and 2010. The first analysis of the GWAS data used an admixture mapping approach to identify loci at which ancestry was associated with risk (Fejerman et al Hum Mol Genetics 2012). This analysis also included Hispanic/Latina women from the Multi-ethnic cohort which are not included in this dbGAP submission. The investigators identified 6q25 as a locus by admixture mapping. The investigators then fine mapped this region and replicated in additional datasets (Fejerman et al Nature Communications 2014). They found two SNPs in linkage disequilibrium at 6q25 that were associated with breast cancer risk. The minor allele for these SNPs was only common in women with some Indigenous American ancestry and was highly protective for breast cancer. In addition, the investigators replicated several previously identified SNPs associated with breast cancer at different loci in other populations, although only SNPs at the TOX3 locus met the criteria for genome wide significance.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="CHALLENGE" longName="Up for a Challenge (Publication required)"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="CHALLENGE-COL" longName="Up for a Challenge (Collaboration required, Publication required)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000912.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000912.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000912.v1.p1" FileName="eNCI_0211_DUC_Ziv_5.27.2015.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Up for a Challenge (Publication required)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>CHALLENGE</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of these data is limited to research described for the National Cancer Institute (NCI) "Up for A Challenge" breast cancer genetic epidemiology competition. The goal of this challenge is to use innovative approaches to identify novel biology involved in breast cancer susceptibility including new genes, genetic variants, or sets of genomic features, leading to novel biological hypotheses. Individuals NOT participating in the challenge would NOT be granted access. Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>Up for a Challenge (Collaboration required, Publication required)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>CHALLENGE-COL</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of these data is limited to research described for the National Cancer Institute (NCI) "Up for A Challenge" breast cancer genetic epidemiology competition. The goal of this challenge is to use innovative approaches to identify novel biology involved in breast cancer susceptibility including new genes, genetic variants, or sets of genomic features, leading to novel biological hypotheses. Individuals NOT participating in the challenge would NOT be granted access. Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community. Requestor must provide a letter of collaboration with the primary study investigator(s). A blank copy of the letter of collaboration for this study can be found at the end of the study&amp;#x2019;s Data Use Certification Agreement (see dbGaP study page). Requestor must provide this signed form documenting approval. Approval can be obtained by contacting Esther M. John at esther.john@cpic.org</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="999">
        <ConsentName>Exchange Area</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>EA</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Pre-release exchange area for use by study investigators only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
