<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000769.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000769.v1.p1" createDate="2014-06-26" modDate="2015-11-17">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Homer L. Twigg III</td><td>Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Mary A. Foulkes</td><td>George Washington University, The Biostatistics Center, Washington, DC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Kathleen A. Jablonski</td><td>George Washington University, The Biostatistics Center, Washington, DC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Laurence Huang</td><td>University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Susan V. Lynch</td><td>University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>NHLBI Lung HIV Microbiome Project (LHMP)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI) Data Coordinating Center, Microbiome of the Lung and Respiratory Track, Lung HIV Microbiome Project (LHMP)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Observational</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Humans interact with countless microorganisms in multiple environments. The Lung HIV Microbiome Project (LHMP) characterized the microbiome of the lung and respiratory tract. This effort provided initial data to develop further hypotheses addressing differences between HIV-infected and HIV-uninfected individuals. The project involved multiple studies, either single center or multiple-center studies. The research design of each study varies with the objective of that study.</p> <p>The Lung HIV Microbiome Project (LHMP) worked collaboratively to ensure the clinical and scientific integrity and success of this project. The LHMP characterized the microbiome of the lung alone or in combination with the oropharyngeal cavities in HIV-infected individuals and HIV-uninfected controls using molecular techniques to identify bacteria.</p> <p>Knowledge of the lung microbiome and that of other components of the respiratory tract in healthy and diseased states may lead to the identification of predictors of disease progression and therapeutic targets for translation into better preventive and treatment strategies.</p> <p>Study datasets and biospecimens are available for request from <a href="https://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/lhmp/" target="_blank">https://biolincc.nhlbi.nih.gov/studies/lhmp/</a>.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p><b>Smoker vs. Non-Smoker Paper</b> (PMID: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23491408" target="_blank">23491408</a>)</p> <p><u>Eligibility Criteria</u></p> <p>Inclusion <ul> <li>Age 18</li> <li>Able to understand and provide informed consent for participating in LHMP</li> <li>Meeting criteria of either non-smoker or current smoker in exposure status defined below:</li> <ul> <li>Non-Smokers</li> <ul> <li>Less than 100 cigarettes lifetime and currently not a smoker</li> <li>Have not used illicit drugs during the past year and not currently a cigar or pipe smoker</li> </ul> <li>Current Smokers</li> <ul> <li>Current smoker is defined as smoking greater than 5 cigarettes daily</li> <li>Any level of use of marijuana, cigar, pipe, or crack cocaine is acceptable</li> </ul> </ul> </ul> </p> <p>Exclusion <ul> <li>Intravenous drug use within the past year</li> <li>Stated history of chronic, unresolved hepatitis</li> <li>Previously diagnosed with COPD or chronic bronchitis (chronic productive cough for at least three months in each of two successive years), asthma, pulmonary hypertension, or other chronic lung disease based on patient report, pulmonary function test (PFT) or medical record documentation.</li> <li>History of malignancy</li> <li>Cardiovascular disease (coronary artery disease, congestive heart failure), excluding hypertension</li> <li>Abnormal spirometry (&lt; 80% predicted FEV1, FVC, TLC or FEV1/FVC &lt; 0.70, Dlco &lt; 0.70% predicted - if PFTs are done)</li> <li>Antibiotic or oral steroid use within 3 months</li> <li>Chemotherapy or immunosuppressive therapy within the past 3 months</li> <li>Diagnosis of diabetes</li> <li>HIV positive</li> </ul> </p> <p><b>HIV Infected (HIV Positive on Therapy and HIV Positive Na&#239;ve to Therapy) vs. HIV Non-Infected (HIV Negative) Paper</b> (PMID: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26247840" target="_blank">26247840</a>)</p> <p><u>Eligibility Criteria HIV Infected (HIV Positive on Therapy and HIV Positive Na&#239;ve to Therapy vs. HIV Non-Infected (HIV Negative) Group</u></p> <p>Inclusion <ul> <li>Patients must be at least 18 years old</li> <li>Patients must have provided informed consent for use of their data and samples by the LHMP consortium</li> <li>Patients must have oral and BAL samples</li> <li>The diagnosis of HIV+ and negative must be recorded on the LHMP data collection forms and includes the following information: <ul> <li>must be HIV non-infected</li> <li>must be HIV infected and na&#239;ve to antiretroviral therapy or</li> <li>must be HIV infected and on antiretroviral therapy currently or within the last 6 months and for at least 6 months with a viral load of less than 1000 raw copies/ml.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </p> <p>Exclusion <ul> <li>All patients with pneumonia in the past 6 months</li> <li>All patients who used oral steroids in the 3 months prior to BAL</li> <li>All patients who used immunosuppressants in the 3 months prior to BAL</li> <li>All patients who used chemotherapy in the 3 months prior to BAL</li> <li>All patients who have ever been diagnosed with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), emphysema, or chronic bronchitis</li> <li>All patients who have ever been diagnosed with pulmonary hypertension</li> <li>All patients who have ever been diagnosed with asthma and have used a steroid or bronchodilator inhaler in the three months prior to the BAL</li> </ul> </p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23491408"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23392441"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="24429191"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22760045"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="26247840"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="HIV"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Homer L. Twigg III</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Mary A. Foulkes</AttName>
			<Institution>George Washington University, The Biostatistics Center, Washington, DC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Kathleen A. Jablonski</AttName>
			<Institution>George Washington University, The Biostatistics Center, Washington, DC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Laurence Huang</AttName>
			<Institution>University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Susan V. Lynch</AttName>
			<Institution>University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Robert Knight</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Colorado, Boulder, CO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Thomas Campbell</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Colorado, Denver, CO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Sonia C. Flores</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Colorado, Denver, CO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Andrew Fontenot</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Colorado, Denver, CO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Jeffrey Curtis</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Vincent Young</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>James Beck</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI and University of Colorado, Denver, CO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Ronald Coleman</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Frederick Bushman</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Alison Morris</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Elodie Ghedin</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>George M. Weinstock</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University in St. Louis, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>(U01) Microbiome of the Lung and Respiratory Tract in HIV-Infected Individuals and HIV-Uninfected Controls</AttName>
			<Institution>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="Lung HIV Microbiome Project" url="https://lhmp.bsc.gwu.edu"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The Lung HIV Microbiome Project (LHMP) was initiated in 2008 by NHLBI with the announcement Microbiome of the Lung and Respiratory Tract in HIV-Infected Individuals and HIV-Uninfected Controls (RFA-HL-09-006). Six clinical centers, six sequencing centers and a data coordinating center were funded in 2009 (institutions listed below). HIV-infected individuals and HIV-negative controls were screened, consented and enrolled; subject histories and status recorded; and bronchial lavage and other samples collected. The LHMP formulated several hypotheses to explore, resulting in the relevant publications listed below. The data collection occurred from 2009 through early 2014.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="2" shortName="DS-HIV" longName="Disease-Specific (Human Immunodeficiency Virus)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHLBI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute DAC</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000769.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000769.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000769.v1.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data is limited only by the terms of the model Data Use Certification.
The informed consent documents signed by the Lung HIV Microbiome Project (LHMP) study participants allows de-identified data (phenotype and sequencing) to be used for research purposes by investigators who request the data via the controlled-access review process. The sequencing files are from bronchoalveolar lavage, bronchoalveolar lavage prewash control, oral wash, oral wash control and extraction control specimens.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="2">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Human Immunodeficiency Virus)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-HIV</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Human Immunodeficiency Virus.
LHMP study participants who limited the future research use of their de-identified data (phenotype and sequencing) to HIV Related Studies only.  They are not included in the General Research Use group.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
