<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000485.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000485.v1.p1" createDate="2012-03-26" modDate="2012-03-26">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Patricia Donahoe, MD</td><td>Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>U54 HG003067</td><td>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Gene Mutation and Rescue in Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Gene mutation and rescue in congenital diaphragmatic hernia</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Probands</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Mendelian</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Family</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia (CDH) is a common and life-threatening malformation. The most common phenotype is left-sided posterolateral (Bochdalek-type) hernia accompanied by pulmonary hypoplasia. Due to the high mortality, most of the cases have no family history for CDH. The rare presumed Mendelian instances of CDH have the potential to be extremely informative about the molecular mechanisms generating this phenotype. Three multiplex families were deemed meritorious for study by whole exome sequencing: <ol> <li>Parents who were 1<sup>st</sup> cousins gave birth to 2 children with CDH (one of whom also had cleft lip and palate), both now deceased. A DNA sample was available from one child. We proposed to perform a SNP array to identify regions of homozygosity by descent and intersect these regions with variants detected on exome sequencing. This effort has led to the identification of 3 confirmed variants. We are determining which if any are expressed in the primordial developing diaphragm and are also using bioinformatic approaches to determine which of these candidates interact with known CDH genes.</li> <li>This non-consanguineous couple gave birth to 2 affected boys with an identical and lethal CDH phenotype (consisting of diaphragmatic hernia, epigastric hernia, and facial dysmorphism) and one healthy boy. We predicted X-linked inheritance and findings from X chromosome microsatellite marker analysis are consistent with this. Accordingly, we are focusing on sequence variants mapping to the X chromosome. We have identified a single candidate gene and confirmed that the variant follows an X-linked pattern of inheritance in all family members. Expression studies are underway.</li> <li>These affected males are second cousins. By virtue of their position in the pedigree, we predicted an inheritance pattern consistent with X-linked inheritance. Data from WES and microsatellite marker analysis are currently being integrated.</li> </ol> </p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Members of likely Mendelian families with apparent autosomal recessive or X-linked inheritance of congenital diaphragmatic hernia (CDH). Family history and genetic data were collected for every individual in the study. Additionally, a study geneticist performed a clinical assessment of the patients. Medical records were obtained and reviewed for every affected individual.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Congenital diaphragmatic hernia"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Patricia Donahoe, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>U54 HG003067</AttName>
			<Institution>National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="Massachusetts General Hospital/Pediatric Surgical Research Laboratories" url="http://www.massgeneral.org/research/researchlab.aspx?id=1486"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="CDH" longName="Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia and Related Disorders"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NHGRI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>National Human Genome Research Institute</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000485.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000485.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000485.v1.p1" FileName="ConDiaphragHernia.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia and Related Disorders</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>CDH</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Research data use restricted to Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia and Related Disorders</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
