<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000328.v2.p1" parentStudy="phs000328.v2.p1" createDate="2013-08-12" modDate="2013-08-13">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Riccardo Dalla-Favera</td><td>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Laura Pasqualucci</td><td>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>PO1-CA-092625</td><td>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>RO1 CA-37295</td><td>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Genome-wide Analysis of Lymphoma</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genome-wide Analysis of Diffuse Large B-Cell Lymphoma (de novo and derived from the high grade transformation of follicular lymphoma)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Tumor vs. Matched-Normal</StudyType>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p><b>Version 1.</b> Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma (DLBCL) represents the most common form of B-cell non-Hodgkin Lymphoma (B-NHL), accounting for ~30% of the <i>de novo</i> diagnoses and also arising as a frequent clinical evolution of Follicular Lymphoma (FL). The molecular pathogenesis of DLBCL is associated with multiple genetic lesions that in part distinctly segregate with individual phenotypic subtypes, suggesting the involvement of distinct oncogenic pathways. However, the lesions identified so far likely represent only a fraction of those necessary for malignant transformation. In order to characterize the entire set of structural alterations present in the DLBCL genome, we have integrated next generation whole exome sequencing analysis of 6 DLBCL cases and genome-wide high-density SNP array analysis of 72 DLBCL cases. We report here that FL and DLBCL harbor frequent structural alterations inactivating <i>CREBBP</i> and, more rarely, <i>EP300</i>, two highly related histone and non-histone acetyltransferases (HATs) that act as transcriptional co-activators in multiple signaling pathways. Overall, ~37% of DLBCL and 36% of FL cases display genomic deletions and/or somatic point mutations that remove or inactivate the HAT coding domain of these two genes. These lesions commonly affect a single allele, suggesting that reduction in HAT dosage is important for lymphomagenesis. We demonstrate specific defects in the acetylation-mediated inactivation of the BCL6 oncoprotein and activation of the p53 tumor suppressor. These results identify <i>CREBBP/EP300</i> mutations as a major pathogenic mechanism shared by common forms of B-NHL, and have direct implications for the use of drugs targeting acetylation/deacetylation mechanisms.</p> <p><b>Version 2.</b> Follicular lymphoma (FL) is an indolent, but incurable disease that, in 30-40% of cases, undergoes transformation to an aggressive diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL). The history of clonal evolution and the mechanisms that underlie transformation to DLBCL (tFL) remain largely unknown. Using whole exome sequencing and copy number analysis of 39 tFL patients, including 12 with paired sequential FL/tFL biopsies, we show that, in most cases, FL and tFL arise by divergent evolution from a common mutated precursor cell through the acquisition of distinct genetic lesions. Mutations in epigenetic modifiers (e.g., <i>MLL2, CREBBP, EZH2, ARID1A</i>) and anti-apoptotic genes (<i>BCL2, FAS</i>) were observed in 93% (36/39) and 78% (30/39) of cases, respectively, and were invariably shared between the two disease phases, suggesting an early acquisition in the common mutated precursor. Conversely, the development of tFL is associated with deregulation of genes involved in the control of cell proliferation, cell cycle progression and DNA damage responses (<i>CDKN2A/2B, MYC, TP53</i>), as well as with an aberrant activity of the somatic hypermutation mechanism. Finally, we show that the genomic profile of tFL shares significant similarities with that of germinal center B-cell type <i>de novo</i> DLBCL, but also displays unique combinations of altered genes that may explain the dismal clinical course of tFL.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p><b>Version 1.</b> <ol> <li>Previously untreated, <i>de novo</i> diagnoses of Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma, nodal involvement.</li> <li>For the whole exome sequencing study, matched tumor and normal genomic DNA.</li> </ol> </p> <p><b>Version 2.</b> <ol> <li>Diffuse Large B-cell Lymphoma derived from the transformation of Follicular Lymphoma (tFL).</li> <li>For 12 patients, longitudinal biopsies from the FL and tFL phase.</li> <li>For 6 patients, matched normal DNA.</li> </ol> </p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21390126"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21804550"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="21156281"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19412164"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Pasqualucci et al." title="Genetic determinants of follicular lymphoma transformation" journal="2013. Submitted."/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Lymphoma, Large B-Cell, Diffuse"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Lymphoma, Follicular"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Riccardo Dalla-Favera</AttName>
			<Institution>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Laura Pasqualucci</AttName>
			<Institution>Institute for Cancer Genetics, Herbert Irving Comprehensive Cancer Center, Columbia University, New York, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>PO1-CA-092625</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>RO1 CA-37295</AttName>
			<Institution>National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-CA-PUB-MDS" longName="Disease-Specific (Cancer, PUB, MDS)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000328.v2.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000328.v2.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000328.v2.p1" FileName="Data_Use_Certification-Genome-wide_Analysis_of_Lymphoma-11.25.10.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Cancer, PUB, MDS)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-CA-PUB-MDS</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Cancer.
Requestor agrees to make results of studies using the data available to the larger scientific community.
Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms).</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
