<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000486.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000486.v1.p1" createDate="2012-03-28" modDate="2014-04-15">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Patrick F. Sullivan, MD</td><td>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Fred Wright, PhD</td><td>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Wei Wang, PhD</td><td>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Wei Sun, PhD</td><td>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Fei Zou, Phd</td><td>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Integration of Genomics and Transcriptomics in unselected Twins and in Major Depression</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Integration of Genomics and Transcriptomics in unselected Twins and in Major Depression</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Cohort</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Our goals are to develop a comprehensive understanding of the genomics of transcription in a population based unselected sample and to discover DNA and RNA biomarkers for major depressive disorder (MDD). This work is essential to developing a more complete understanding of the biological basis of MDD, a common complex trait associated with considerable morbidity, mortality, and personal/societal cost. All biological samples have been collected from well-defined populations, and are now available.</p> <p>First, we conduct a "genetical genomics" or eQTL study of ~800 MZ and ~800DZ twin pairs. Each subject has been assayed for genome-wide SNPs and CNVs and gene expression from peripheral blood sampled under standardized conditions. We determine the genetic architecture (genetic and non-genetic proportions of variance via twin analyses) for every transcript, and the genome-wide associations (i.e., SNP-transcript eQTL pairs). These analyses will be expanded to consider transcriptional modules. The key deliverable is a detailed catalogue of the general and specific architecture of transcription plus raw intensity files.</p> <p>Second, we seek to discover DNA and RNA biomarkers relevant to MDD, capitalizing on the results of a large MDD study with repeated clinical and biological assessments; we have previously shown that PB is a reasonable proxy for CNS expression and employ an advanced modelling framework: (a) Using baseline data, we identify biomarkers for MDD by comparing ~1000 controls with ~1400 MDD cases via comparisons of SNP, CNV, expression transcripts, and transcriptional modules. (b) Using longitudinal data, we contrast gene expression signatures assessed at baseline and two years later in ~200 controls and ~500 MDD cases.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p><u>Netherlands Twin Registry (NTR)</u>. The NTR has collected longitudinal data on twins and their families via 8 surveys every 2-3 years, beginning in 1991 (~22,000 participants from ~5,000 families). Most twins were recruited as young adults through City Council registration, and additional twins via a variety of approaches. Longitudinal phenotyping includes assessment of DSM-IV MDD by CIDI, depressive symptoms (multiple instruments), anxiety, neuroticism, and other personality measures. Additionally, subjects are asked about major medical illnesses/health, medications, life events, and lifestyle, and a genetic factor score for MDD liability is available. There are banked RNA and DNA samples from ~1600 pairs, with an almost equal distribution of monozygotic and dizygotic twin pairs. Most of these individuals are controls but some meet case definitions.</p> <p><u>Netherlands Study of Depression and Anxiety (NESDA)</u>. NESDA is an ongoing cohort study designed to investigate the long-term course and consequences of depressive and anxiety disorders. Participants were 18-65 years at baseline in 2004-2007 and were recruited from the community (19%), general practice (54%), and mental health settings (27%). At baseline, there were ~1000 individuals with current MDD and ~1100 with past but not current history of MDD. The baseline assessment included the CIDI, demography, and medical assessment. DSM-IV MDD diagnoses were established with the CIDI which has high inter-rater reliability, test-retest reliability, and validity for MDD. Of the baseline subjects, 87% participated in a two year follow-up. The CIDI was repeated to query MDD in the time since baseline (augmented by the use of a Life Chart Interview). These measures allow classification into distinct clinical trajectories over two years of follow-up: chronic or recurrent course with symptoms &gt;1y (poor course) and remission within one year (good course, initial MDD episode lasts &lt;1y with complete remission &gt;1y). Of subjects with current MDD at baseline, a minority (44.9%) were taking antidepressants (usually SSRIs). Antidepressant use data are now being coded. Most NESDA subjects are cases but an independent, longitudinally-assessed sample of controls was also collected.</p> <p><u>Harmonized Biological Sampling</u>. Processing and storage protocols were harmonized between the NESDA and NTR studies. Blood sampling in NESDA took place between 0830-0930h and between 0700-1000h for NTR. All venous blood samples were taken after an overnight fast.</p> <p><u>RNA Sampling</u>. Within 20 minutes of sampling, heparinized blood was transferred into PAXgene tubes and stored at &#8722;20&#176;C. DNA isolation. EDTA tubes were used. For NESDA, FlexiGene DNA AGF3000 kits were used on an AutoGenFlex 3000 workstation. For NTR, Puregene DNA isolation kits were used on frozen whole blood samples. DNA concentrations were determined using PicoGreen dsDNA kits. All procedures were performed via manufacturer&apos;s protocols.</p> <p><u>Covariates</u>. Available covariates include: sampling time/date; age at sampling; sex; complete blood count with differential; consumption/quantity of tobacco and alcohol near the time of sampling; detailed list of medications (including antidepressants); and detailed health status (chronic/recent acute medical illness, allergies, etc.).</p> <p><u>Data upload</u>: The GODOT project has typed DNA and RNA from peripheral blood for large samples from both the NESDA and NTR studies. The available data are Affy6 genotype assays, as well as Affymetrix U219 expression assays on the same set of individuals (except for minor lack of overlap due to quality control flagging). Additional subject information includes twin pedigree descriptions (for the NTR subjects), major depressive disorder phenotyping for the NESDA subjects, and a set of patient/covariates that may influence expression levels.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Wright et al." title="Heritability and genomics of gene expression in peripheral blood." journal="Nature Genetics, 2014, <i>in press</i>."/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19065144"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18763692"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17254420"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="24438232"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18197199"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="20477721"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Depressive Disorder, Major"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Patrick F. Sullivan, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Fred Wright, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Wei Wang, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Wei Sun, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Fei Zou, Phd</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Sandra Batista, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Vered Madar, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Kai Xia, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Andrew Brooks, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Jay Tischfield, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Qi Wang, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Ani Qu, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Jaspreet Kochar, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>David D&#39;Ambrosia, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers The State University of New Jersey, New Brunswick, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dr. Brenda Penninx</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dr. Johannes Smit</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dr. Rick Jansen</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Gerard van Grootheest</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dr. Dorret Boomsma</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dr. Eco deGeus</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dr. Gonneke Willemsen</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Dr. Jouke-Jan Hottenga</AttName>
			<Institution>VU University, Amsterdam, The Netherlands</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>5-RC2-MH089951-01 (Patrick F. Sullivan, MD)</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute of Mental Health, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="Netherlands Study of Depression and Anxiety (NESDA)" url="http://www.nesda.nl/en/"/>
		<Url name="Netherland Twin Register" url="http://www.tweelingenregister.org/en/"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects"/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-PD-RSC" longName="Disease-Specific (Psychiatric Disorders and Related Somatic Conditions)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIMH</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIMH</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000486.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000486.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000486.v1.p1" FileName="Sullivan_DUC_normal_twins_and_MDD.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Psychiatric Disorders and Related Somatic Conditions)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-PD-RSC</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Psychiatric Disorders and Related Somatic Conditions.
Psychiatric and related somatic conditions: Psychiatric refers to DSM-IV psychiatric disorders, while related somatic conditions refers to general medical disorders whose risks have been shown to be elevated in individuals with psychiatric disorders. Examples: cardiovascular disease, migraine, type 2 diabetes, etc.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
