<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000763.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000763.v1.p1" createDate="2014-06-20" modDate="2015-01-16">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Principal Investigators</td><td>Bernice  Porjesz*, PhD (*Administrative PI)</td><td>SUNY Health Sciences Center, Brooklyn, NY, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Principal Investigators</td><td>Howard J. Edenberg, PhD</td><td>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Principal Investigators</td><td>Laura J. Bierut, MD</td><td>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Principal Investigators</td><td>Victor Hesselbrock, PhD</td><td>University of Connecticut School of Medicine, Farmington, CT, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Steering Committee</td><td>Bernice Porjesz*, PhD</td><td>SUNY Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn NY, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>The Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism (COGA)</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>The Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism (COGA)</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Family</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>COGA is a family study of alcoholism, in which the subjects have been drawn from the Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism (COGA), a large, ongoing family-based study that includes subjects from seven sites around the US. COGA has gathered detailed, standardized data on study participants, including diagnostic and neurophysiological assessments. This sample has already proved successful in identifying several genes that influence the risk for alcoholism and neurophysiological endophenotypes, which have been independently replicated. COGA data were included as part of two Genetic Analysis Workshops, and the phenotypes are familiar to the genetics community.</p> <p>Alcoholic probands were recruited from treatment facilities, assessed by personal interview, and after securing permission, other family members were also assessed. A set of comparison families was drawn from the same communities as the families recruited through an alcoholic proband. Assessment involved a detailed personal interview developed for this project, the Semi-Structured Assessment for the Genetics of Alcoholism (SSAGA), which gathers detailed information on alcoholism related symptoms along with other drugs and psychiatric symptoms. Many participants also came to the laboratories for electroencephalographic studies. Neurophysiological features that have been shown to be useful endophenotypes for which we have linkage and in some cases association results, are included for a subset of the case-control sample: <ul><li>the beta power of the resting electroencephalogram (EEG),</li> <li>the P3(00) amplitude of the visual event-related potential (ERP) and the </li> <li>theta and delta event-related oscillations (EROs) underlying the P3.</li> </ul> </p> <p>As part of COGA, a set of informative families was selected to have Genome-Wide Association data obtained within families. Genotyping was performed using the Illumina Human OmniExpress array 12.VI to genotype 2,282 subjects selected from 118 densely affected families. Genotyping was performed at the Genome Technology Access Center at Washington University School of Medicine in St. Louis. In addition, we also included genotypes for subjects (n=275 subjects) from these 118 families who were genotyped in a previous case-control GWAS using the Illumina 1M array. For quality control purposes, 51 of the 275 subjects were genotyped again on the Illumina Human OmniExpress array at the Washington University School of Medicine core facility.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>COGA recruited patients who were currently in a psychiatric inpatient or outpatient program for alcohol and/or chemical dependency. Detoxification must be complete before approaching the individual.</p> <p>A potential proband: must not have used intravenous drugs more than 30 times in a lifetime and not within six months of screening, must not have any life-threatening illness other than alcohol-related terminal illnesses such as cirrhosis or Korsakoff&#39;s, must not be infected with the HIV virus, and his/her first-degree relatives must speak English, and live within one of the following six COGA catchment areas. </p> <p>Each COGA site recruited Control families consisting of two living parents and three or more full siblings, aged 14 or older. The Control Probands and families were ascertained via random consecutive sampling from either HMOs or dental clinics. They were to be representative of the general population and do not have to be unaffected individuals. Therefore, a Control family would not be eliminated if alcoholism is present among any of its members. </p> <p>We extend families through all affecteds, alive and dead, which means the standard protocol was administered to all first-degree relatives of all affecteds. If any of these relatives were affected, we extend to his/her first-degree relatives, and continue if any of them are affected. In addition, extension by leapfrogging over a living or dead unaffected into a branch containing at least two first-degree relatives of the "leapfrogee" who have 3 implications by history. </p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23089632"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="22554406"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="23743675"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Alcoholism"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Co-Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Bernice  Porjesz*, PhD (*Administrative PI)</AttName>
			<Institution>SUNY Health Sciences Center, Brooklyn, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Howard J. Edenberg, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Laura J. Bierut, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Victor Hesselbrock, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Connecticut School of Medicine, Farmington, CT, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Bernice Porjesz*, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>SUNY Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Howard J. Edenberg, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Laura J. Bierut, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Victor Hesselbrock, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Connecticut School of Medicine, Farmington, CT, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Arpana Agrawal, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Laura Almasy, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio, San Antonio, TX, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Andrew Brooks, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers University, Piscataway, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Kathleen Bucholz, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Danielle Dick, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Tatiana Foroud, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Alison Goate, DPhil</AttName>
			<Institution>Icahn School of Medicine at Mt. Sinai, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>John Kramer, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Iowa, Iowa City, IA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Samuel Kuperman, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Iowa Hospitals, Iowa City, IA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>John I. Nurnberger, Jr., MD, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>John Rice, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Marc A. Schuckit, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of California, San Diego, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Robert Taylor, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Howard University, Washington, DC, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Jay A. Tischfield, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Rutgers University, Piscataway, NJ, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Abbas Parsian, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Steering Committee">
			<AttName>Matt Reilly, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Fazil Aliev, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Sarah Bertelsen</AttName>
			<Institution>Icahn School of Medicine at Mt. Sinai, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>John Budde</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Grace Chan</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Connecticut School of Medicine, Farmington, CT USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>David B. Chorlian</AttName>
			<Institution>SUNY Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Manav Kapoor, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Icahn School of Medicine at Mt. Sinai, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Jeanette N. McClintick, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Vivia McCutcheon, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Niklas Manz, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>SUNY Downstate Medical Center, Brooklyn NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Scott Saccone, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Jessica Salvatore, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, VA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Jen-Chyong Wang, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Icahn School of Medicine at Mt. Sinai, New York, NY, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Leah Wetherill</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Other Analysts/Investigators">
			<AttName>Xiaoling Xuei, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Indiana University School of Medicine, Indianapolis, IN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>U10 AA008401</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyURLs>
		<Url name="COGA" url="https://niaaagenetics.org"/>
	</StudyURLs>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>COGA was initiated in 1989, with Henri Begleiter as the Principal Investigator and Theodore Reich as the Co-Principal Investigator for 15 years. In 2004, while Henri Begleiter remained the PI, 4 Co-PIs were put into place: Howard Edenberg, Victor Hesselbrock, Bernice Porjesz and Laura Bierut. In 2006, the structure of the leadership changed again, with these 4 scientific Co-PIs leading the project, and Bernice Porjesz additionally serving as the Administrative PI. In addition to Henri Begleiter and Theodore Reich, several past key members of COGA were T.K. Li, Raymond Crowe, Wendy Reich and C. Michael Conneally, who have moved on to new positions or have retired.</p> <p>In 1990, Phase I of COGA began, systematically ascertaining probands in treatment within six catchment areas, located across the United States (Indiana, New York, St. Louis, Connecticut, Iowa, San Diego). Probands met criteria of alcohol dependence based upon personal interview using the Semi-Structured Assessment for the Genetics of Alcoholism (SSAGA), a polydiagnostic instrument developed by COGA, and had at least two first-degree relatives available for evaluation. Over the next 5 years, affected probands and family members participated in the study. During this time, Control families with the same family structure were also ascertained from the community, to be representative of the general population; controls did not have to be unaffected individuals. All families completed the same battery of tests. A subset of families underwent neurophysiological assessments.</p> <p>In Phase II, between 1995 and 1999, some recruitment of new families continued, and the first follow-up protocol (5 year) was initiated. Affected families were extended. Adult clinical interviews conducted at this time used the SSAGA2 (a slight modification of the SSAGA to meet new diagnostic criteria).</p> <p>Phase III began in 1999, and was primarily an extension of Phase II with an emphasis on recruiting high-risk families with young children. At this time Howard University became an additional recruitment site.</p> <p>In 2004, COGA began Phase IV, the prospective study of adolescents and young adults from pedigrees ascertained in Phases I-III, which is ongoing. Participants are reassessed every two years.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-ALC-IRB-RD" longName="Disease-Specific (Alcoholism, IRB, RD)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIAAA</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIAAA</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000763.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000763.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000763.v1.p1" FileName="COGA_CIDR_FAM_DUC_rev012110.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Alcoholism, IRB, RD)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-ALC-IRB-RD</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Alcoholism and related disorders.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>
  <Documents>
    <Document phd="phd004551.1" type="protocol" createDate="2014-09-29" modDate="2015-01-15" urlToXml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/GetDocumentXml.cgi?document_id=phd004551.1" urlToHtml="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/gap/cgi-bin/document.cgi?study_id=phs000763.v1.p1&amp;phd=4551">
      <OrigName>Description_theta_ERO_FAM_GWAS.pdf</OrigName>
      <DisplayName>Visual Oddball Experiment and Event-Related Oscillations (ERO)</DisplayName>
      <Description>Visual Oddball Experiment and Event-Related Oscillations (ERO)</Description>
      <displayStatus>public</displayStatus>
      <xmlStatus>public</xmlStatus>
    </Document>
  </Documents>

  <Annotations>
    <DocumentPart phd="phd004551.1" sectionId="p1">
      <phvList>
        <phvRef variableId="217639"/>
        <phvRef variableId="217640"/>
      </phvList>
    </DocumentPart>
    <DocumentPart phd="phd004551.1" sectionId="sec1b">
      <phvList>
        <phvRef variableId="217639"/>
        <phvRef variableId="217640"/>
      </phvList>
    </DocumentPart>
  </Annotations>


<Analyses>
	<Analysis pha="3861" genomeBuild="38" snpBuild="141" analysisType="">
		<Description>The goal of the present study was to perform a genome-wide association  study (GWAS) in extended families from the Collaborative Study on the Genetics of Alcoholism to identify novel genes affecting risk for alcohol dependence (AD). To maximize the power of the extended family design, we used a quantitative endophenotype, measured in all individuals: number of alcohol-dependence symptoms endorsed (symptom count (SC)). Secondary analyses were performed to determine if the single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) associated with SC were also associated with the dichotomous phenotype, DSM-IV AD.  To reduce the heterogeneity in the sample, only families that were primarily of Caucasian descent were selected for genotyping, yielding a total of 2322 subjects from 118 extended families who were genotyped.</Description>
		<Method>Quantitative trait analysis</Method>
		<GtyPlatform probeNum="747309" snpBatchId="1056552">
			<Vendor>Illumina</Vendor>
			<VendorURL>HumanOmniExpress-12v1_H</VendorURL>
			<Platform>HumanOmniExpress-12v1_C</Platform>
		</GtyPlatform>
		<Comment></Comment>
	</Analysis>
</Analyses>

</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
