<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000274.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000274.v1.p1" createDate="2010-05-21" modDate="2011-11-25">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Susan Neuhausen, PhD</td><td>Beckman Research Institute at the City of Hope, Duarte, CA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigators</td><td>Chad Garner, PhD</td><td>University of California, Irvine, CA, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Joseph Murray, MD</td><td>Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Alessio Fasano, MD</td><td>University of Maryland, Baltimore, MD, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Co-Investigators</td><td>Peter Green, MD</td><td>Columbia University, New York, New York, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Genome-Wide Association Study of Celiac Disease</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Genome-Wide Association Study of Celiac Disease</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case-Control</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Celiac disease (gluten-sensitive enteropathy, celiac sprue) is a common disease with significant morbidity and mortality. 	It is caused by sensitivity to the dietary protein gluten, resulting in a chronic enteropathy in the small intestine.  Celiac 	disease is now recognized to be a common disease, with reports that the disease frequency is 1:133 in the United States, 	similar to European estimates.  There is recent evidence to suggest that the incidence of the disease is rising. Occult 	disease is frequently present with minimal classic symptoms or signs. The ratio of symptomatic to asymptomatic celiac 	disease is estimated to be 1:7.  Some complications of celiac disease include lymphoma, osteoporosis, anemia, 	miscarriages, seizures, vitamin deficiencies, and co-occurrence of other autoimmune diseases. The only treatment 	is a gluten-free diet, so that recurrence of symptoms and complications may occur after minor dietary indiscretions. 	Identifying the underlying genetic causes of celiac disease may allow us to identify susceptible individuals, as well 	as advance new ways to prevent the disease and to treat it once it occurs.</p> 	<p>Several genome-wide linkage studies and one genome-wide association study of celiac disease have been conducted. Other than 	the common locus at HLA, few putative celiac disease loci have been replicated between studies, suggesting that the disease 	is heterogeneous and complex.  A portion of the genetic predisposition can be attributed to HLA, but the etiology is likely 	due to a number of rare, high penetrant genes (as would be identified in linkage analysis) and to more common, low 	penetrant genes (as would be identified in association studies).</p> 	<p>The objective of this study is to identify new loci that increase risk to develop celiac disease.  We will capitalize 	on existing North American resources, including three large collections of celiac cases and controls (Aim 1) and an 	independent set of celiac cases and their families (Aim 3).  We propose a comprehensive multi-stage approach, with 	the following specific aims. In Aim 1, we will conduct a genome-wide association (GWA) study of single nucleotide 	polymorphisms (SNPs) and copy number variants (CNVs). The GWA will include1900 disease cases and 3400 matched 	controls, genotyped using the Illumina Human 610-quad chip.  Statistical analyses will be performed to test 	for associations with celiac disease. In Aim 2, we will conduct a combined analysis of our GWA dataset from 	Aim 1 and a previous GWA dataset to identify additional low-penetrance loci. In Aim 3, we will attempt to 	replicate significant findings from the GWA study in two independent sample sets. At the conclusion of this 	study, we expect to have validated a number of SNPs and CNPs from regions in the genome that alter the risk of 	developing celiac disease. These SNPs may prove useful at both the clinical and research level. The data from 	the study will be shared with the scientific community.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>An individual is considered as having celiac disease if the diagnosis has been by small intestinal biopsy with the ESPGHAN 	criteria fulfilled, biopsy proven dermatitis herpetiformis, or positive serologic EMA and tTG results.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19648293"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="17136122"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="12578508"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Celiac Disease"/>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Dermatitis Herpetiformis"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Susan Neuhausen, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>Beckman Research Institute at the City of Hope, Duarte, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Principal Investigators">
			<AttName>Chad Garner, PhD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of California, Irvine, CA, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Joseph Murray, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Alessio Fasano, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Maryland, Baltimore, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Co-Investigators">
			<AttName>Peter Green, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Columbia University, New York, New York, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>R01DK081645</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases, National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source for Genotyping">
			<AttName>HHSN268200782096C. NIH contract &quot;High throughput genotyping for studying the genetic contributions to human disease&quot;</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>The celiac disease study began 14 years ago with familial studies of celiac disease to identify non-HLA genes predisposing 	to the disease (NIH DK50678).  As part of that work, families with two or more cases of celiac disease were enrolled.  From 	studies of subsets of these families, we have reported the results of linkage analysis and candidate gene analysis, have 	developed a rapid, inexpensive PCR-based HLA-genotyping method, and have examined risk of celiac disease and issues of 	diagnoses in family members.  As we and others were unable to identify high penetrant rare alleles through linkage 	analysis, we moved to association studies.  For that study, a North American Consortium was formed to utilize previously 	collected cases and controls.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="0" shortName="NRUP" longName="Subjects did not participate in the study, did not complete a consent document and are included only for the pedigree structure and/or genotype controls, such as HapMap subjects."/>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="GRU" longName="General Research Use"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIDDK</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIDDK Central Repository GWAS Data Access Committee</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>niddk-dac@mail.nih.gov</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacFax>301-480-3510</DacFax>
      <DacUrl>http://www3.niddk.nih.gov/researchprograms/repositories/FAQ.shtml</DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000274.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>12</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
               http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000274.v1.p1
            </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000274.v1.p1" FileName="ModeNIDDKdbGaPlDUC_2010April7_FINAL_1_edited_for_format_and_links_2-2011.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>General Research Use</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>GRU</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>These data may be used for general research</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
