<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000201.v2.p1" parentStudy="phs000201.v2.p1" createDate="2014-04-08" modDate="2014-04-08">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Timothy J. Ley, MD</td><td>Department of Medicine, Department of Genetics, The Genome Center, Siteman Cancer Institute, MO, USA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>P01 CA101937</td><td>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Acquired Copy Number Alterations in Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia Genomes</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Acquired Copy Number Alterations in Adult Acute Myeloid Leukemia Genomes</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Tumor vs. Matched-Normal</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>We performed genome-wide copy number analysis with paired normal and tumor DNA obtained from 86 adult patients with de novo AML using the Affymetrix Genome-Wide Human SNP array 6.0 containing 1.85 million features. Acquired copy number alterations (CNA) were confirmed using an independent, higher resolution, custom array comparative genomic hybridization platform.</p> <p>A total of 201 somatic CNA were found in the 86 AML genomes (mean 2.34 CNA/genome), with FAB M6 and M7 AML genomes containing the most changes (10-29 CNA/genome). Twenty-four percent of AML patients with normal cytogenetics had CNA, while 40% of patients with an abnormal karyotype had additional CNA detected by SNP array, and several regions contained CNA in multiple AML genomes. The mRNA expression levels of 57 genes were significantly altered in 27 of 50 recurrent CNA regions &lt;5 megabases in size. Array data are available online at <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/" target="_blank">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</a> as GEO accession #GSE10358. A total of 8 uniparental disomy (UPD) segments were identified in the 86 genomes and 6/8 UPD regions occurred in samples with a normal karyotype. Collectively, 40% of AML genomes contained alterations not found with cytogenetics, and 96% of these regions contained known or novel AML associated genes. 43/86 AML genomes had no CNA or UPD at this level of resolution. The number of CNA per genome was not associated with overall survival, independent of cytogenetic classification.</p> <p>In this study of 86 adult AML genomes, subcytogenetic CNAs or UPD did not add prognostic information to standard cytogenetics. However, arrays identified many somatically mutated oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes, and also genes not previously implicated in AML that may be relevant for pathogenesis.</p> <p>AML CNA segments from 86 adult AML patients are available through dbVar at <a href="ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pub/dbVar/data/Homo_sapiens/nstd11_Walter_et_al_2009">ftp://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pub/dbVar/data/Homo_sapiens/nstd11_Walter_et_al_2009</a>.</p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>All participants are adults (&gt;18 years) with de novo AML, bone marrow containing 30% or greater blasts, and chosen for the study based on availability of high quality, abundant, paired bone marrow (tumor) and skin (normal) DNA samples. Preference was also given to patients with 2 or fewer cytogenetic abnormalities.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="19651600"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18270328"/>
		</Publication>
		<Publication>
			<Pubmed pmid="18987736"/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Timothy J. Ley, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>Department of Medicine, Department of Genetics, The Genome Center, Siteman Cancer Institute, MO, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>P01 CA101937</AttName>
			<Institution>National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, MD, USA</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-HEM-MDS-GSO" longName="Disease-Specific (Hematologic Disease, MDS, GSO)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NCI</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NCI</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000201.v2.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>no</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000201.v2.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000201.v2.p1" FileName="Data_Use_Certification_Requirements-Acquired_Copy_Number_Alteration_in_Adult_Acute_Myeloid_Leukemia_Genomes-Revised_7.18.pdf"/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Hematologic Disease, MDS, GSO)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-HEM-MDS-GSO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Hematologic Disease. Use of the data includes methods development research (e.g., development of software or algorithms). Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>No</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
