<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<GaPExchange xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="./dbGaPEx2.1.5.xsd">

<MetaVariables>
	<Submitter/>
	<Method/>
</MetaVariables>
<MetaLinks/>

<Projects>
	<Project/>
</Projects>

<Studies>

<Study source="dbGaP" accession="phs000960.v1.p1" parentStudy="phs000960.v1.p1" createDate="2015-07-21" modDate="2015-07-23">

<Configuration>
	<Data_Provider><![CDATA[
		<table border="1">
		<tr><th>Title</th><th>Name</th><th>Institute</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Principal Investigator</td><td>Rakesh Sindhi, MD</td><td>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Funding Source</td><td>Intramural and Philanthropic</td><td>Hillman Foundation of Pittsburgh and Children&#39;s Hospital of Pittsburgh Research Foundation</td></tr>
		</table>
	]]></Data_Provider>
	<StudyNameEntrez>Biomarkers in Transplant Recipients</StudyNameEntrez>
	<StudyNameReportPage>Biomarkers in Transplant Recipients: Genome-wide Association Study of Biliary Atresia</StudyNameReportPage>
	<StudyTypes>
		<StudyType>Case Set</StudyType>
	</StudyTypes>
	<Description><![CDATA[
<p>Biliary atresia causes jaundice and liver failure in newborn children. In this study, single nucleotide polymorphisms were characterized in children with biliary atresia and identified ARF6 as a susceptibility gene for this disease. Knockdown of this gene in zebrafish embryos impaired formation of bile ducts and excretion of bile from the zebrafish liver.</p> <p><b>Subject enrollment</b>: Children with biliary atresia were enrolled at Children&#39;s Hospital of Pittsburgh (CHP) after obtaining written consent from parents for the University of Pittsburgh IRB approved protocol number 0405628. At the Center for Applied Genomics (CAG), all subjects were enrolled after obtaining written consent from parents per Children&#39;s Hospital of Philadelphia IRB approval number 06-004886</p> <p><b>Genotyping array</b>: Genotyping of DNA obtained from blood was performed with the Infinium HumanHap550K BeadChip (Illumina, San Diego, CA).</p> <p><b>Statistical methods and software</b>: SNP genotype frequencies were compared between cases and controls with a chi-square test statistic applied in Plink [Purcell et al, 2007] for SNPs with at least 90% call rate and 1% minor allele frequency (MAF).</p> <p><b>Cases and controls</b>: All DNA samples had excellent data quality with call rates &#62; 98%. A total of 63 Caucasian BA cases and 1907 controls were compared at &#62; 550000 SNPs, and demonstrated a very low genomic inflation factor of 1.00627.</p> <p><b>Description of Cases</b>: Biliary atresia patients had received a Kasai procedure and demonstrated histopathological features of biliary obstruction, and were recruited at evaluation for transplantation or after liver transplantation.</p> <p>Reference: Purcell S, Neale B, Todd-Brown K, Thomas L, Ferreira MA, et al. (2007) PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses. Am J Hum Genet 81: 559-575 (PMID: <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=17701901">17701901</a>). </p><p></p> <p></p>]]>
	</Description>
	<StudyInEx><![CDATA[
<p>Biliary atresia patients who have received a Kasai procedure and demonstrated histopathological features of biliary obstruction were recruited at evaluation for transplantation or after liver transplantation. Those subjects who did not meet these criteria were not recruited.</p>]]>
	</StudyInEx>
	<StudyProjects>
		<Project/>
	</StudyProjects>
	<Publications>
		<Publication>
			<Journal authors="Ningappa M, So J, Glessner J, Ashokkumar C, Ranganathan S, Min J, Higgs BW, Sun Q, Haberman K, Schmitt L, Vilarinho S, Mistry PK, Vockley G, Dhawan A, Gittes GK, Hakonarson H, Jaffe R, Subramaniam S, Shin D, Sindhi R." title="The role of ARF6 in biliary atresia" journal="PLoS ONE, 2015. <i>In press</i>."/>
		</Publication>
	</Publications>
	<Diseases>
		<Disease vocab_source="MESH" vocab_term="Biliary Atresia"/>
	</Diseases>
	<Attributions>
		<Header title="Principal Investigator">
			<AttName>Rakesh Sindhi, MD</AttName>
			<Institution>University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA</Institution>
		</Header>
		<Header title="Funding Source">
			<AttName>Intramural and Philanthropic</AttName>
			<Institution>Hillman Foundation of Pittsburgh and Children&#39;s Hospital of Pittsburgh Research Foundation</Institution>
		</Header>
	</Attributions>
	<DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
	<StudyHistory><![CDATA[
<p>Children with biliary atresia were enrolled at Children&#39;s Hospital of Pittsburgh (CHP) after obtaining written consent from parents for the University of Pittsburgh IRB approved protocol number 0405628. At the Center for Applied Genomics (CAG), all subjects were enrolled after obtaining written consent from parents per Children&#39;s Hospital of Philadelphia IRB approval number 06-004886.</p>]]>
	</StudyHistory>
	<ConsentGroups>
		<ConsentGroup groupNum="1" shortName="DS-BA-IRB-NPU-GSO" longName="Disease-Specific (Biliary Atresia, IRB, NPU, GSO)"/>
	</ConsentGroups>
</Configuration>

  <AuthorizedAccess>
    <DacInfo ssDacId="0">
      <DacName>NIDDK</DacName>
      <DacFullName>NIDDK Central Repository GWAS Data Access Committee</DacFullName>
      <DacEmail>0</DacEmail>
      <DacPhone></DacPhone>
      <DacUrl></DacUrl>
    </DacInfo>
    <Policy Policy_ID="phs000960.v1.p1_policy" ref_ssDacId="0">
      <DisplayResearchStatement>yes</DisplayResearchStatement>
      <DisplayPublicSummary>yes</DisplayPublicSummary>
      <EmbargoLength>0</EmbargoLength>
      <YearsUntilRenewal>1</YearsUntilRenewal>
      <WeeksCancelRequest>8</WeeksCancelRequest>
      <PdfSupplementReqired>yes</PdfSupplementReqired>
      <AcknowledgementText>
        <para>
          http://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000960.v1.p1
        </para>
      </AcknowledgementText>
      <DocumentSet>
        <DataUseCertificate Label="Data Use Certificate" FilePath="https://dbgap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/aa/wga.cgi?page=DUC&amp;view_pdf&amp;stacc=phs000960.v1.p1" FileName=""/>
      </DocumentSet>
    </Policy>
    <ConsentGroups>
      <ParticipantSet groupNum-REF="1">
        <ConsentName>Disease-Specific (Biliary Atresia, IRB, NPU, GSO)</ConsentName>
        <ConsentAbbrev>DS-BA-IRB-NPU-GSO</ConsentAbbrev>
        <UseLimitation>Use of the data must be related to Biliary Atresia.
Requestor must provide documentation of local IRB approval.
Use of the data is limited to not-for-profit organizations.
Use of the data is limited to genetic studies only.</UseLimitation>
        <IrbRequired>Yes</IrbRequired>
      </ParticipantSet>
    </ConsentGroups>
  </AuthorizedAccess>


</Study>

</Studies>

</GaPExchange>
